<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <meta>
    <effective>0001-01-01</effective>
    <print>
      <volumes>
        <volume start="TCT"/>
        <volume start="GNC"/>
      </volumes>
    </print>
    <recency through="2024-09-09">
      <doc id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" type="resolution"/>
    </recency>
  </meta>
  <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law</heading>
  <xi:include href="./TCT.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./MCC.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CTZ.xml"/>
  <container containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>GWE</num>
    <heading>General Welfare Exclusion</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>GWE.1</num>
      <heading>General Welfare Exclusion Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to promote the traditional value that children are the most important asset of the Tribe, which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite> empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people" and pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(j)">Article V, §1(j)</cite> "to administer any funds within  the control of the Band; to make expenditures from available funds for public purposes…All expenditures by the Governing Board shall be in accord with a previously approved budget, and the amount so paid shall be a matter of public record at all times." As such the Tribal Governing Board adopts this Ordinance to memorialize and confirm existing procedures used in the administration of general welfare assistance programs and services and is not to be construed as the creation of new general welfare assistance rights that previously did not exist. Assistance provided prior to the enactment of this Ordinance is hereby ratified and confirmed as general welfare assistance pursuant to the authority of the Tribal Constitution. It is intended to establish a framework to improve the coordination of general welfare doctrine compliance. Programs and Services referred to herein must be authorized by independent action of the Tribe or its designees.</text>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.1</num>
        <heading>Introduction</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.010</num>
          <heading>Title</heading>
          <text>This ordinance shall be known as the General Welfare Exclusion Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Tribe").</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.020</num>
          <heading>Authority</heading>
          <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h)</cite> and (j) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people" and pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(j)">Article V, §1(j)</cite> "to administer any funds within  the control of the Band; to make expenditures from available funds for public purposes…All expenditures by the Governing Board shall be in accord with a previously approved budget, and the amount so paid shall be a matter of public record at all times." On September 18, 2014, the Tribal General Welfare Exclusion Act of 2014 passed both houses of Congress, and was signed into law on September 29, 2014. The Tribal Governing Board now expressly embraces the forgoing principles as an integral part of this Ordinance and as guiding principles in construing the Tribe's compliance with Code Section 139E, the Safe Harbor Rules, and the General Test. The assistance payments and services authorized by this Ordinance are intended to qualify for favorable tax treatment under the general welfare doctrine to the fullest extent permitted by law and shall be construed accordingly.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.030</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <text>This ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The purpose of this Ordinance is to further empower Tribal self-determination.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Governing Board have a long history of providing critical benefits to Tribal Members, and these programs are fundamental to the sovereignty and cultural integrity of the Tribe. The Tribe, and not the IRS, are in the best position to determine the needs of their members and provide for the general welfare of their tribal citizens and communities.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.040</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.050</num>
          <heading>Interpretation</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe as the Indian General Welfare Exclusion Act requires that "any ambiguities in new Code section 139E shall resolved by the IRS in favor of Indian Tribal governments and deference shall be given to Indian Tribal governments for programs administered and authorized by the Tribe to benefit the general welfare of the Tribal community."</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Does not waive the sovereign immunity of the Tribe in any respect.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.060</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a Court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.070</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
          <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.2</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.2.010</num>
          <heading>General Definitions</heading>
          <text>Any term not defined in <cite path="|GWE.1.2.010">this section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Assistance" </strong>means any Program benefits or payments that qualify for tax free treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Beneficiary" </strong>means any person or persons entitled to receive Assistance in accordance with specific Program guidelines. Programs designed to qualify for exemption under Code Section 139E may benefit Members, spouses of a Member, and/or Dependents of a Member. Programs designed to meet the Safe Harbor may benefit any Member or Qualified Nonmember.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Code"</strong> means the internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Compensation"</strong> for services should reflect that qualifying Programs are not disguised employment. However, this shall not prevent the Tribe  from structuring Programs with community service ties so long as such ties are consistent with the General Welfare Exclusion. For example, Programs similar to the Workforce Investment Act may include tax free Assistance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Constitution"</strong> means the Constitution of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"Custodian"</strong> means a person having care and custody of a child under any arrangement with the child's parent or guardian or pursuant to order of the Tribal or State Court.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"General Welfare Exclusion"</strong> means assistance shall be treated as non-taxable so long as it satisfies the requirements under Code Section 139E, it is provided under a Safe Harbor Program, or it meets the General Test.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"General Test" </strong>means assistance will be treated as meeting the General Test under the General Welfare Exclusion if the benefits are:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>paid by or on behalf of a Tribe,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>under a social benefit program,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>based on either needs of the Indian community itself or upon individual needs of the recipient (which need not be financial in nature), and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>are not Compensation for services or per capita payments.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Lavish" or "Extravagant"</strong> Except as otherwise required for compliance with final guidance issued under Code Section 139E following consultation, lavish and extravagant shall be determined by the Tribal Governing Board in its sole discretion based on all facts and circumstances, taking into account needs unique to the Tribe as well as the social purpose being served by the particular Assistance at hand.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Ordinance"</strong> means the General Welfare Ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text><strong>"Pay"</strong> or "<strong>Paid" </strong>or "<strong>Payment</strong>" means pay or reimbursement in whole or in part.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text><strong>"Program"</strong> or "<strong>Approved Program</strong>" means any program established by or under authority of the Tribal Governing Board, including any program authorized through the annual budget process, to provide Assistance hereunder. A program shall not fail to be treated as an Indian tribal government Program solely by reason of the Program being established by tribal custom or government practice.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <text><strong>"Promotion of the General Welfare"</strong> or "<strong>Social Benefit</strong>" should reflect a goal or goals established by the Tribal Governing Board for the promotion of the general welfare of the Tribe, for example, in furtherance of tribal self-determination, culture and tradition.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <text><strong>"Qualified Nonmember"</strong> means a spouse, former spouse, legally recognized domestic partner or former domestic partner, ancestor, descendant, or Dependent of a member of the Tribe. Individual Tribal Programs may, but are not required to, cover Qualified nonmembers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(o)</num>
            <text><strong>"Reservation"</strong> means the reservation of the Lac Courte Oreille Reservation boundaries or, if the context so permits, any other Indian reservation as defined in Internal Revenue Code Section 162(j).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(p)</num>
            <text><strong>"Safe Harbor Program"</strong> shall refer to a Program that meets the safe harbor requirements set forth herein and IRS Revenue Procedure 2014-35, as the same may hereafter be amended. Need shall be presumed for Assistance provided under a Safe Harbor Program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(q)</num>
            <text><strong>"Service Area"</strong> has the same meaning as in 25 C.F.R. Section 20.100.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(r)</num>
            <text><strong>"Spouse"</strong> shall be determined in accordance with Tribal laws, customs and traditions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(s)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong>  means Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.3</num>
        <heading>Indian General Welfare Benefits (Code Section 139E)</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.010</num>
          <heading>. Non-Binding Designation</heading>
          <text>General welfare services and payments hereunder are paid from assets of Tribal Governing Board; all payments are based on budget availability, and the Tribal Governing Board  does not guarantee any payments hereunder. Benefits paid hereunder on the basis of need shall not be treated as a resource of the Member for any purpose. The Tribal Governing Board reserves the right to cancel, adjust, modify or revoke any benefits that are treated as a resource of the Tribal Member.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.020</num>
          <heading>Indian General Welfare Benefits (Code Section 139E)</heading>
          <text>Programs that meet the following criteria for exemption under Code Section 139E shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion without the applicant having to demonstrate individual need.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.030</num>
          <heading>General Criteria for Qualification Under Code 139E</heading>
          <text>Each payment must be made or service provided to or on behalf of a Member (or any Spouse or Dependent of the Member) pursuant to a Program under this Ordinance shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion so long as the following criteria are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Program is administered under specified guidelines and does not discriminate in favor of the members of the governing body of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are available to any Tribal Member who meets such guidelines;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are for the "promotion of the general welfare";</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are not Lavish or Extravagant; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are not Compensation for services.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.040</num>
          <heading>Ceremonial Activities</heading>
          <text>Any items of cultural significance, reimbursement of costs, or cash honorarium for participation in cultural or ceremonial activities for the transmission of tribal culture shall not be treated as Compensation for services.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.050</num>
          <heading>Special Effective Dates</heading>
          <text>Code Section 139E is effective for Assistance in taxable years for which the period of limitations on a refund or credit under Code Section 6511 has not expired. If the period of limitation on a refund or credit resulting from the application of Code Section 139E (a) would otherwise expire before the one-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of Code Section 139E, a refund or credit (to the extent attributed thereto) may be made or allowed if a claim is filed before the close of such one-year period.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.060</num>
          <heading>Safe Harbor Programs</heading>
          <text>Programs that meet the following general criteria for safe harbor treatment, and provide qualifying safe harbor benefits, shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion without the applicant having to demonstrate individual need.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.070</num>
          <heading>General Criteria for Safe Harbor Treatment</heading>
          <text>Each Safe Harbor Program shall satisfy the following general criteria:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The benefit is provided under a specific Approved Program of the Tribe</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Program has written guidelines specifying how individuals may qualify for the benefit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The benefit is available to any tribal member, Qualified Nonmember, or identified group of Tribal Members or Qualified Nonmembers who satisfy the Program guidelines, subject to budgetary restraints;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The distribution of benefits from the Program does not discriminate in favor of the governing body of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The benefit is not Compensation for services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The benefit is not Lavish or Extravagant under the facts and circumstances</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.080</num>
          <heading>Qualifying Safe Harbor Benefits</heading>
          <text>The following benefits may be provided under a Safe Harbor Program. The benefits listed in the parenthetical language herein are illustrative only, rather than an exhaustive list. Thus, a benefit may qualify for exclusion from gross income as a Safe Harbor Program even though the benefit is not expressly described in the parenthetical language herein, provided that it meets all other requirements of Article VI and Revenue Procedure 2014-35 (as may be amended):</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Housing programs. Programs relating to principal residences and ancillary structures that are not used in any trade or business, or for investment purposes that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay mortgage payments, down payments, or rent payments (including but not limited to security deposits) for principal residences.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Enhance habitability of housing, such as by remedying water, sewage, or sanitation service, safety issues (including but not limited to mold remediation), or heating or cooling issues.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide basic housing repairs or rehabilitation (including but not limited to roof repair and replacement).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay utility bills and charges (including but not limited to water, electricity, gas, and basic communications services such as phone, internet, and cable).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Pay property taxes or make payments in lieu of taxes (PILOTs).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Educational Programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Provide students (including but not limited to post-secondary students) transportation to and from school, tutors, and supplies (including but not limited to clothing, backpacks, laptop computers, musical instruments, and sports equipment) for use in school activities and extracurricular activities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Provide tuition payments for students (including but not limited to allowances for room and board on or off campus for the student, spouse, domestic partner, and Dependents) to attend preschool, school, college or university, online school, educational seminars, vocational education, technical education, adult education, continuing education, or alternative education.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide for the care of children away from their homes to help their parents or other relatives responsible for their care to be gainfully employed or to pursue education.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Provide job counseling and programs for which the primary objective is job placement or training, including but not limited to allowances for expenses for interviewing or training away from home (including but not limited to travel, auto expenses, lodging, and food); tutoring; and appropriate clothing for a job interview or training (including but not limited to an interview suit or a uniform required during a period of training).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Elder and disabled programs. Programs for individuals who have reached age 55 or are mentally or physically disabled (as defined under applicable law, including but not limited to tribal government disability codes or laws) that provide:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Meals through home-delivered meal programs or at a community center or similar facility.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Home care such as assistance with preparing meals or doing chores, or day care outside the home.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Local transportation assistance.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Improvements to adapt housing to special needs (including but not limited to grab bars and ramps).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Cultural and religious programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay expenses (including but not limited to admission fees, transportation, food, and lodging) to attend or participate in an Indian Tribe's cultural, social, religious, or community activities such as pow-wows, ceremonies, and traditional dances.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Pay expenses (including but not limited to admission fees, transportation, food, and lodging) to visit sites that are culturally or historically significant for the Tribe, including but not limited to other Indian reservations.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Pay the costs of receiving instruction about the Tribe's culture, history, and traditions (including but not limited to traditional language, music, and dances).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay funeral and burial expenses and expenses of hosting or attending wakes, funerals, burials, other bereavement events, and subsequent honoring events.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Pay transportation costs and admission fees to attend educational, social, or cultural programs offered or supported by the Tribe.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Other qualifying assistance programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay transportation costs such as rental cars, substantiated mileage, and fares for bus, taxi, and public transportation between an Indian reservation, service area, or service unit area and facilities that provide essential services to the public (such as medical facilities and grocery stores).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Pay for the cost of transportation, temporary meals, and lodging of a Tribal Member or Qualified Nonmember while the individual is receiving medical care away from home.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance to individuals in exigent circumstances (including but not limited to victims of abuse), including but not limited to the costs of food, clothing, shelter, transportation, auto repair bills, and similar expenses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay costs for temporary relocation and shelter for individuals displaced from their homes (including but not limited to situations in which a home is destroyed by a fire or natural disaster).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance to individuals temporary displaced from their homes for the costs of food, clothing, transportation, auto repair bills, and similar expenses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance for transportation emergencies (for example, when stranded away from home) in the form of transportation costs, a hotel room, and meals.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Pay the cost of nonprescription drugs (including but not limited to traditional Indian tribal medicines).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.4</num>
        <heading>Programs Meeting the General Test</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.010</num>
          <heading>Programs Meeting the General Test</heading>
          <text>Programs that do not qualify for non-taxable treatment under Code Section 139E or under an IRS Safe Harbor, will nonetheless be treated as non-taxable if Program benefits meet the General Test for treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion. For purposes of the General Test only, needs must be shown in one manor described in <cite path="GWE.1.4.020">GWE.1.4.20</cite> or <cite path="GWE.1.4.030">GWE.1.4.030</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.020</num>
          <heading>Individual Needs</heading>
          <text>Individual Needs. Certain Programs may be based on individual need, rather than an overall need of the Tribe. For those Programs, the Tribal Governing Board may establish income guidelines unique to the Tribe or may use readily available income guidelines used by state or federal programs to demonstrate individual or family need. When individual or family need must be shown, the Program may take into account individual circumstances or extraordinary need to overcome presumptions based on income alone.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.030</num>
          <heading>Community Needs</heading>
          <text>Certain Programs may be based on community needs, which are so important to the self-determination, culture and traditions of the Tribe that Assistance may be deemed necessary regardless of individual income or wealth. For example, states provide public education to all citizens regardless of individual income or wealth. Some Programs may address both individual and community-based needs. The Tribal Governing Board reserves the right to require any applicant applying for consideration based on non-financial or community-based needs to demonstrate how the Program benefits will benefit the tribal community as a whole, including preservation of culture, tradition and self-determination. Approval based on non-financial need criteria is made on a facts and circumstances basis and will be guided by traditional values and culture. A Program will be deemed to be based on community or non-financial needs if so designated by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.040</num>
          <heading>Purpose of the Program</heading>
          <text>All Assistance disbursed pursuant to this Ordinance shall be designed to promote the general welfare, self-determination, culture and tradition of the Tribe. The Tribal Governing Board shall establish objectives for the furtherance of the general welfare, self-determination, culture and tradition of the Tribe and assess progress on said objectives in connection with its budgeting and/or strategic planning process. Approved Programs shall be renewed, established, modified, or terminated based upon the needs of the Tribe as compared to the objectives set by the Tribal Governing Board from time to time hereunder. All Programs hereunder shall provide a social benefit for the promotion of the general welfare of the Band and be limited to purposes consistent with treatment under this Ordinance. Such purposes may include, for example, and not by way of limitation, assistance for medical care, food, shelter, health, education, subsistence, housing, elder and disabled care, assistance to meet cultural, traditional and religious needs of the Tribe and its membership, and assistance to promote self-sufficiency, self-determination, Tribal image, entrepreneurship, and the employment of Tribal Members. Designation by the Tribal Governing Board if a Program as falling under this Ordinance shall be conclusive evidence that the Tribal Governing Board, following a good faith review of Tribal needs and goals, has determined that said Program is established to achieve a social benefit and to promote the general welfare of the Tribe.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.050</num>
          <heading>Eligibility and Application Procedures</heading>
          <text>Each approved Program shall set forth the specific eligibility rules and limitations applied to that Program. Each designated department shall present program descriptions, which include eligibility rules and limitations, along with application forms and procedures, for approval by the Tribal Governing Board or its designee. Only those descriptions, application forms and procedures which are approved by the Tribal Governing Board or its designee shall be in force and effect. Program guidelines may limit benefits to an identified group of Members or Qualified Nonmembers, as applicable. All Programs may be limited by budget availability. In the absence of specific Program guidelines to the contrary, all Programs shall be deemed to incorporate eligibility criteria necessary for compliance with Code Section 139E.</text>
          <text>All Assistance disbursed or provided pursuant to this Ordinance must be used for the purpose stated in the approved Program description, and any application for the applicable Assistance. The Tribe or its designee shall keep books or records deemed appropriate to demonstrate compliance with the Ordinance. Recipients of benefits hereunder are responsible for maintaining books or records as may be required for substantiation to the IRS for individual income tax purposes. In the event that Assistance payments and/or services are used or pledged for a purpose inconsistent with the purpose set forth in the applicable approved Program or the Member's application, the Tribal Governing Board or designee may require the repayment of the welfare assistance payment. The Tribal Governing Board or designee is authorized to offset any other payments owed to a Tribal member if such an offset is necessary to secure repayment of a welfare assistance payment in accordance with <cite path="GWE.1.4.030">this Section</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.060</num>
          <heading>Limitations on Welfare Assistance Payments</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Governing Board, within its annual budgets, by resolution or by motion, may adopt guidelines establishing the maximum Assistance payments to be made to Tribal members for certain specified purposes or programs or may delegate the establishment of such limitations to the program level. Such guidelines may also include, by way of example, factors to be considered in determining whether deviations from the general payment limitations should be permitted. Departments charged with administering particular programs may be delegated authority to adopt program guidelines to the extent not contrary to the overall guidelines and limitations established by the Tribal Governing Board. In no event shall Assistance be lavish or extravagant.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.070</num>
          <heading>Annual Budgeting: Unfunded Program</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Governing Board, through its annual budgeting process, by resolution or by motion, shall designate those funding sources that are available for the payment of Assistance benefits. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary, the Assistance payments authorized hereunder shall be “unfunded” for tax purposes and no Beneficiary shall have an interest in or right to any funds budgeted for or set aside for Assistance payments until actually paid. Assistance benefits shall remain assets of the Tribe until distributed, and the Approved Programs shall be administered to avoid premature taxation through the doctrines of constructive receipt and/or economic benefit.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.080</num>
          <heading>Forfeiture</heading>
          <text> Notwithstanding anything herein to the contrary, Assistance benefits may be revoked or forfeited for any Beneficiary who is found to have misapplied program funds or to have made any misrepresentations during the application process. Assistance may also be forfeited should said benefits be treated as a resource to the detriment of the Tribe or a Beneficiary. The Tribe shall have a right of recovery with regard to any excess or improper payments hereunder.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.090</num>
          <heading>Programs Not Limited to Means Testing</heading>
          <text>Programs that qualify under Code Section 139E or the IRS Safe Harbor shall not require a showing of individual need or means testing in order to achieve non-taxable treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion. The Tribe also reserves the right to provide community-based Programs and Programs based on non-financial need under the General Test that are not individually means tested. The Tribe recognizes that means testing can distort certain tribal cultural and community values. The Tribe has participated in consultation with the United States Treasury Department and IRS and will evaluate Programs periodically as guidance is further developed through consultation with the Tribe.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.100</num>
          <heading>Other Tax Exemptions</heading>
          <text>Notwithstanding anything herein to the contrary, the Tribe reserves the right to waive income limits or needs basis criteria, to the extent otherwise applicable, for expenditures that otherwise qualify for tax exemptions including tax exemptions under Titles 25 or 26 of the United States Code so long as the conditions for exemption are met. Without limitation, this includes Member medical benefits exempt under Section 9021 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010 (Code Section 139D) and per capita expenses exempt under 25 U.S.C. Sections 1407 and 1408.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>GWE.2</num>
      <reason>Repealed</reason>
      <heading>General Welfare Services Immediate Assistance Funds</heading>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.2.1</num>
        <heading>General Welfare Services Immediate Assistance Funds</heading>
        <section placeholder="Repealed">
          <reason>Repealed</reason>
          <num>GWE.2.1.010</num>
          <heading>Policy Declaration</heading>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2023-10-23" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-129" eff="2023-10-23" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2024-09-09" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" eff="2024-09-09" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section placeholder="Repealed">
          <reason>Repealed</reason>
          <num>GWE.2.1.020</num>
          <heading>Tribal Governing Board Responsibilities</heading>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2023-10-23" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-129" eff="2023-10-23" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2024-09-09" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" eff="2024-09-09" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section placeholder="Repealed">
          <reason>Repealed</reason>
          <num>GWE.2.1.030</num>
          <heading>Budget Allocations</heading>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2023-10-23" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-129" eff="2023-10-23" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2024-09-09" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" eff="2024-09-09" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section placeholder="Repealed">
          <reason>Repealed</reason>
          <num>GWE.2.1.040</num>
          <heading>Procedure</heading>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2023-10-23" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-129" eff="2023-10-23" path="" type="History"/>
            <annotation app="2024-09-09" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" eff="2024-09-09" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <annotation app="2023-10-23" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-129" eff="2023-10-23" path="" type="History"/>
      <annotation app="2024-09-09" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-94" eff="2024-09-09" path="" type="History"/>
    </container>
  </container>
  <xi:include href="./ELE.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CSV.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./DMR.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./GNC.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./VEH.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./PHS.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./PRP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CMP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./LLC.xml"/>
  <container containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>ITP</num>
    <heading>Information Technology Policy</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>ITP.1</num>
      <heading>Information and Technology Use and Security Policy</heading>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to provide for the decent, safe, and sanitary dwellings for the members of the Tribe which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a Tribal Governing Board, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation." (<cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, § 1(l)</cite>). Pursuant to this inherent sovereign authority, the Tribal Governing Board hereby enacts this ordinance.</text>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.1</num>
        <heading>Introduction</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.010</num>
          <heading>Title</heading>
          <text>This policy and procedure manual shall be known as the Lac Courte Oreilles Information and Technology Policy.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.020</num>
          <heading>Authority</heading>
          <text>This policy and procedure manual is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to promote the traditional value that children are the most important asset of the Tribe, which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(q)">Article V, § 1 (q),</cite> <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">(s)</cite>, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(t)">(t)</cite>, and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(u)">(u)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowered the Tribal Governing Board to establish a Children's Court Division of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court..."</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.030</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <text>The Tribe depends heavily on its information resources today and will become even more dependent on them in the future. Information is one of the Tribe's most important assets. Protection of information assets is necessary to establish and maintain trust between Tribal members, Tribal Departments and Entities,  Tribal leadership, and third-party  vendors . The security of the Tribe's systems and information is essential to its safety and to the privacy of Tribal financial information. The purpose of this policy is to establish general guidelines for maintaining a computing environment within the Tribe that is controlled, consistent and secure. The policy's primary objective is to enhance the productivity of users by optimizing network performance, reducing wasted use of resources and the risk of legal liability caused by illegal or inappropriate use of the Network, and to provide for Network security and safety. The Tribe is establishing standards relating to administrative, technical, and physical safeguards for Tribal records and information. These safeguards are to ensure the security and confidentiality of Tribal records and information, protect against any anticipated threats or hazards to the security or integrity of these records, and protect against unauthorized access to or use of these records or information that would result in substantial harm or inconvenience to the Tribe or a Tribal member. Attacks frequently compromise personal and business data; it is critical for the Tribe to respond quickly and effectively when security breaches occur by implementing an Incident Response Program that responds to incidents in a consistent manner so that the appropriate actions are taken. These incident response measures help personnel to minimize loss or theft of information and disruption of services, including the ability to use information gained during the incident to better prepare for handling future incidents and to provide stronger protection for systems and data.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.040</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this policy and procedural manual shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.050</num>
          <heading>Interpretation</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to the Information Technology activities subject to this ordinance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of this ordinance, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court may use tribal law, federal law, or the State law for guidance.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.070</num>
          <heading>Relation to Other Laws</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Applicable Law.</heading>
            <text>Unless affected or displaced by this ordinance, principles of law and equity common law of the Tribe and tribal customs and traditions are applicable, and the general principles of law of any other Tribe or any other state may be used as a guide to supplement and interpret this ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Conflicts with Other Laws.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Tribal Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that this ordinance may conflict with tribal laws or ordinances which have been enacted to comply with statutes or regulations of any agency of the United States, such tribal laws or ordinances shall govern over the provisions of this Code if it has specific applicability, and it is clearly in conflict with the provisions of this Code.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>State Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that the laws of any state may be applicable to the subject matter of this ordinance, such laws shall be read to be advisory and not directly binding and shall not govern the relations of the parties.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.080</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision, or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.090</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
          <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.2</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.2.010</num>
          <heading>General Definitions</heading>
          <text>Any term not defined in <cite path="§ITP.1.2.010">this section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Agent"</strong> shall mean a person who is authorized to act on behalf of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians with respect to a specific transaction or transactions. For the purposes of this ordinance, agent shall include all individuals elected or appointed to serve on a board, committee, or commission of the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Employee"</strong> shall mean any individual who is employed by the Tribe and is subject to the direction and control of the Tribe with respect to the material details of the work performed, or who has the status of an employee under the usual common law rules applicable to determining the employer-employee relationship. For the purposes of this ordinance, employee shall include individuals employed by a tribal entity or Tribally Chartered corporation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Network or Information Technology (IT)"</strong> shall encompass desktop computers, laptops, network resources, internet, intranet, email, world wide web, telephone systems, social media, etc.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Officer" </strong>shall mean a person elected or appointed to serve on a board, committee, or commission of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Personal electronic devices" </strong>shall include, but shall not be limited to, employee-owned desktop, laptop, tablet, handheld or worn computing devices, whether wired or wireless, USB drives, cameras and smartphones/cellular telephones.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"Reservation or Reservation Lands"</strong> shall mean those lands located within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Entity"</strong> shall mean a corporation or other organization which is wholly owned by the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and is operated for governmental or commercial purposes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> shall mean the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, and includes all departments, divisions, business units, and other subdivisions of the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Court"</strong> shall mean the court of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong> shall mean the Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.3</num>
        <heading>Information Security</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.010</num>
          <heading>Responsibilities</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Governing Board hall oversee the Tribe's efforts to develop, implement, and maintain an effective Information Security Program. The Tribal Governing Board Counsel shall be responsible for approving this policy and the written report on the effectiveness of the Tribe's Information Security Program on an annual basis.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribe's IT Department shall assist with the enforcement and adherence to the standards and guidelines established within this policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Tribe's IT Department shall provide direction and control for information security at the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall exercise due diligence in selecting its service providers and require its service providers by contract to implement security measures that safeguard Tribal information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Employees shall know and understand their duties with respect to the Information Security Policy and comply with the terms of this policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Security Objectives.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall meet its business objectives by implementing business systems with due consideration of information technology (IT) related risks to the Tribe, business and trading partners, technology service providers, and customers. The Tribe shall meet this goal by striving to accomplish the following objectives:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Availability, integrity and confidentiality of data or systems</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Accountability and assurance of processes and controls</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <heading>Security Process.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall implement an ongoing security process and shall assign clear and appropriate roles and responsibilities to the Tribal Governing Board, management, and employees. The process shall be designed to identify, measure, manage and control the risks to system and data availability, integrity, and confidentiality, and ensure accountability for system actions.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.020</num>
          <heading>Risk Assessment</heading>
          <text>Information security risk assessment is the process to identify and understand risks to the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information and information systems. The Tribe shall maintain an ongoing information security risk assessment program that effectively involves three phases:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Information gathering.</heading>
            <text>Gather data regarding the information and technology assets of the Tribe, threats to those assets, vulnerabilities, existing security controls and processes, and the current security standards and requirements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Analysis.</heading>
            <text>Analyze the probability and impact associated with the known threats and vulnerabilities to its assets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Prioritize responses.</heading>
            <text>Rank the risks present due to threats and vulnerabilities to determine the appropriate level of training, controls, and testing necessary for effective mitigation.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.030</num>
          <heading>Strategy</heading>
          <text>The Tribe strives to mitigate risks while complying with legal, statutory, contractual, and internally developed requirements. In building this strategy, the Tribe shall define its control objectives and establish an implementation plan. The security strategy shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Cost comparisons of different strategic approaches appropriate to the Tribe's environment and complexity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Layered controls that establish multiple control points between threats and Tribe assets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Educating officers and employees in implementing the information security program.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.040</num>
          <heading>Controls Implementation</heading>
          <text>The following security controls shall be implemented as available:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Access rights admin.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall have an effective process to administer access to system resources. The Tribe shall strive to identify and restrict access to any system resource to the minimum required for work to be performed. The process shall include the following controls:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Assign end-users and system resources only the access required to perform their required functions;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Update access rights based on personnel or system changes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Periodically review users' access rights based on the risk to the application or system; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Design appropriate acceptable-use and end-user policies.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Authentication.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall use effective authentication methods appropriate to the level of risk by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Selecting authentication mechanisms based on the risk associated with a particular application or service;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Considering whether multiple forms of authentication are appropriate for each application, considering that multi-forms authentication is increasingly necessary for many forms of electronic communication and electronic payment activities; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Encrypting the transmission and storage of authenticators (e.g., passwords, PINs).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Network access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure access to their computer networks through multiple layers of access controls to protect against unauthorized access. Access control measures shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Group network servers, applications, data, and users into security domains;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Require use of unique user IDs and strong passwords;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Establishing appropriate access requirements within and between each security domain; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Implementing appropriate controls to meet those access requirements consistently</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <heading>Operating System access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure access to the operating systems of all system components by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Securing access to system utilities;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Restricting and monitoring privileged access;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Logging and monitoring user or program access to sensitive resources;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Updating the operating systems with security patches; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Securing the devices that can access the operating system through physical and logical means</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <heading>Application access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall control access to applications by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Using authentication and authorization controls appropriate for the risk of the application;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Monitoring access rights to ensure they are the minimum required for the user's current business needs;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Using time of day limitations on access as appropriate; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Logging access and security events</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Remote access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure remote access to and from their systems by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Controlling access through management approvals;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Implementing controls over configuration to disallow potential malicious use;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Monitoring remote access;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Securing remote access devices; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Using strong authentication and encryption to secure communications.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <heading>Physical Security.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall implement appropriate preventative and detective controls to protect against the risk to physical security.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <heading>Encryption.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall employ encryption to mitigate the risk of disclosure or alteration of sensitive information and storage transit. Encryption implementations shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Encryption strength sufficient to protect the information while in transit between unsecure systems;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Effective encryption key management practices; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Appropriate protection of the encrypted communication's endpoints.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>USB storage devices shall not be authorized for general use. If a USB storage device is needed to store sensitive or confidential information, then something like "bit locker" with encryption that requires a username and password shall be used.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <heading>Malicious code.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall protect against the risk of malicious code by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Using anti-virus products on clients and servers;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Using an appropriate blocking strategy on the network perimeter;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Filtering input to applications; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Educating staff in appropriate computing policies and procedures</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <heading>Systems development, acquisition, and maintenance.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall ensure that systems are developed, acquired, and maintained with appropriate security controls. These steps shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Defining security requirements before developing or acquiring new systems;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Incorporating recognized standards in developing security requirements;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Incorporating appropriate security controls, audit trails, and logs for data entry and data processing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Implementing an effective change control process;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Hardening systems before deployment;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Establishing an effective patch process for new security vulnerabilities; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Overseeing vendors to protect the integrity and confidentiality of application source code.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <heading>Personnel security.</heading>
            <text>The Employee Handbook and Human Resources policies shall discuss risk mitigation posed by internal users</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <heading>Virtualization.</heading>
            <text>The Virtual environment and the Virtualization of servers shall be the responsibility of the  IT Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <heading>Electronic and paper-based media handling.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall control and protect access to paper, film, and computer-based media to avoid loss or damage. The Tribe shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Establish and ensure compliance with policies for handling and storing information;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Ensure safe and secure disposal of sensitive media and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Secure media in transit or transmission to third parties.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Employees are instructed to save data to "shared drives" or other network drives for security and backup purposes.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <heading>Logging and data collection.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall take reasonable steps to ensure that sufficient data is collected from secure log files to identify and respond to security incidents and to monitor and enforce policy compliance. The Tribe shall have appropriate logging controls to ensure that security personnel can review and analyze log data to identify unauthorized access attempts and security violations, provide support for personnel actions, and aid in reconstructing comprised systems.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(o)</num>
            <heading>Service provider oversight.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall review security responsibilities for outsourced operations through</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Appropriate due diligence in service provider research and selection;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Contractual assurances regarding security responsibilities, controls, and reporting;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Nondisclosure agreements regarding the Tribe's systems and data; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Third-party review of the service provider's security through appropriate audits and tests.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(p)</num>
            <heading>Intrusion detection and response.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall strive to detect and respond to an information system intrusion commensurate with risk. Risk mitigation practices shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Preparation.</heading>
              <text>Analysis of data flows, decisions on the nature and scope of monitoring, consideration of legal factors, appropriate procedures governing detection and response; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Response to an intrusion.</heading>
              <text>Containment and restoration of systems and appropriate reporting.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(q)</num>
            <heading>Business continuity considerations.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall develop a plan that includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Identification and training of personnel with key security roles during continuity plan implementation; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Security needs for back-up sites and alternate communications.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(r)</num>
            <heading>Insurance.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall evaluate the extent and availability of coverage in relation to the specific risks they are seeking to mitigate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(s)</num>
            <heading>Equipment disposal/destruction.</heading>
            <text>When equipment is retired from use, the hard drive shall be removed and stored or deleted and cleaned with software of a Department of Defense grade. Other equipment such as copiers, printers, and multi-function machines Shall have memory or other data storage devices deleted or destroyed. Equipment shall then be recycled, disposed of, or donated with no software or data.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.050</num>
          <heading>Security testing</heading>
          <text>The Tribe shall gain assurance of the adequacy of their risk mitigation strategy and implementation by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Basing their testing plan, test selection, and test frequency on the risk posed by potentially non-functioning controls;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Establishing controls to mitigate the risks posed to systems from testing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Using test results to evaluate whether security objectives are met.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.060</num>
          <heading>Monitoring and updating</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall continuously gather and analyze information regarding new threats and vulnerabilities, actual and potential attacks on the Tribe or others, and the effectiveness of the existing security controls.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The information in par. (a) shall be used to update the risk assessment, strategy, and implemented controls.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>To complete the goals of (a) and (b) the Tribe shall utilize malware, antivirus, and other security programs.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.070</num>
          <heading>Reporting</heading>
          <text>Employees that become aware of any system misuse; potential threat, intrusion, or unexplained occurrence; or violations of this IT policy, shall inform a member of the IT Department immediately.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.080</num>
          <heading>Incident response program</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Incident Response Team.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall establish an Incident Response Team that is available for anyone who discovers or suspects that an incident has occurred. One or more team members are responsible for handling the incident, analyzing the incident data, determining the impact of the incident, and acting appropriately to limit the damage and restore normal services.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The primary Incident Response Team shall consist of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>IT Director</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>IT Department personnel</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>More severe or extensive incidents can include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Office of Attorney General</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Tribal Law Enforcement</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Compliance/Audit Officer</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>All Tribal employees shall be aware of the possibility of system or security incidents.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Physical building incidents shall be directed to the Tribe's security officer.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Computer security related incidents shall be directed to the IT or Operations Departments.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Individuals shall work with the response team and executive management to execute an incident response.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Phases of Incident Response</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Preparation.</heading>
              <text>This initial phase involves establishing and training a response team and acquiring the necessary tools and resources. During preparation, the Tribe shall attempt to limit the number of incidents that will occur by selecting and implementing a set of controls based on the results of risk assessments. Other preparation items include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Risk Assessment</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>Host Security</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <text>Network Security</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <text>Malware Prevention</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>User Awareness and Training</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>System Hardening Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>System Access Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>Facilities Security Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>Insurance Policies</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Detection and analysis.</heading>
              <text>The process of monitoring and awareness. Training creates an awareness of what constitutes an incident and who to contact when it occurs. Log monitoring, with knowledge of baseline system activities, will create trigger points. Once detected, the Tribe may mitigate the impact of the incident by containing it and ultimately recovering from it.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <heading>Containment, eradication, and recovery.</heading>
              <text>The response to the Incident.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <heading>Post incident activity.</heading>
              <text>Once the incident is over, an overall assessment report of the incident shall be developed detailing the cause of the incident, steps to prevent future incidents, and steps to mitigate consequences of future incidents.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>
                <strong>Unauthorized access to tribal information procedures</strong>
              </text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <heading>Audit.</heading>
              <text>The Tribe shall utilize both internal and external audit procedures to provide independent assessments that evaluate the Tribe's:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Quality of internal controls associated with the acquisition, development, implementation, and operational use of information technology.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Exposure to risks throughout the Tribe and its service provider(s) in the areas of user and data center operations, client/server architecture, local and wide area networks, telecommunications, information security, electronic data interchange, systems development, and contingency planning, including risk management and mitigation techniques implemented by the Tribe; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Compliance with this and other related policies, procedures and processes concerning information technology related risks.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.4</num>
        <heading>Acceptable Use</heading>
        <text>Network access is deemed to be a business tool providing a source of information with the potential for benefiting all areas of the tribe and enhancing customer service, customer retention, and growth. The Information Technology department shall approve Network access as deemed appropriate and shall determine what components of the Network shall be available (email, internet, World Wide Web, etc.). All employees accessing the Network on tribal equipment, on tribal premises, or on a tribal Internet access account shall become proficient in its capabilities, practice proper network etiquette, and agree to the conditions and requirements of this agreement.</text>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.010</num>
          <heading>General principles</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Network, internet, and email privileges provided by the Tribe, shall be considered tribal resources, and shall be used for tribal business purposes. Network and Internet usage shall not be private. Usage shall be monitored for unusual or unacceptable activity and can be monitored at any time for any reason.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Internet use includes, but is not limited to:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>email received and sent,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>websites visited,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>social media posts,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>uploads, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>downloads</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall own the Network, messaging systems, and the information transmitted and stored within it.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Employees shall have no expectation of privacy or confidentiality in any of their emails or network files. Employee email, web history and phone usage may be monitored for policy, security, network and/or tribal management reasons from time to time and is subject to inspection at any time.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Correspondence, internal or external, via email, or instant messaging (IM) shall not be private. Email shall not be guaranteed protection from other employees or from others outside the tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The distribution of any information through the Network, computer-based services, or email shall be subject to the scrutiny of tribal management and its auditors. The Tribe reserves the right to determine the suitability of this information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Employees shall be restricted in their usage of employee-owned personal electronic devices and media storage devices on the Tribal Network.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Employees utilizing web sites and social media sites at work for personal use shall do so during break and lunch times in a professional manner as to not interfere with their job duties and responsibilities. Excessive use, as deemed by their supervisor and/or management, shall result in loss of privilege for the user and possibly other disciplinary action as outlined in this agreement.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.020</num>
          <heading>Conditions of use</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Users shall</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Comply with all current tribal policies</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Lock or log off computers when leaving them unattended for any length of time</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Use unique user IDs and strong passwords as indicated by tribal policy and maintain password credentials in a confidential manner</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Contact the IT and Department manager immediately upon discovering suspicious activity on the Network, Including a Tribal workstation, network resource, or email</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Immediately notify IT and management if a business-related mobile device is lost, stolen, exchanged, unusable, or no longer used</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>The user shall be required to maintain and safeguard the equipment issued and return it to the Tribe if they leave the employment position from which it was issued. This includes when an employee transfers to a new department. If the employee is leaving the employment of the Tribe, they shall return all equipment before they receive their last paycheck.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Users shall not</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Knowingly visit Internet sites that contain illegal, obscene, hateful, or other objectionable materials</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Knowingly access ads or other solicitations commonly seen in the margins of reputable website pages or that popup while on a site</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Knowingly open an attachment or access a link provided in an unsolicited, unfamiliar email. The IT Department shall review any suspicious email</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Send non-encrypted emails containing sensitive customer information.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Send or receive any material, whether by IM, email, memoranda, or oral conversation, which is obscene, defamatory, harassing, intimidating, offensive, illegal, discriminatory, or which is intended to annoy, harass, or intimidate another person.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Solicit non-tribal business for personal gain or profit</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Download any software or electronic files to a tribal workstation or the Network unless authorized by the IT department</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Represent personal opinions as those of the tribe or purport to represent the tribe when not authorized to do so.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>Upload, download, or otherwise transmit software or any copyrighted materials in violation of its copyright or license whether it belongs to parties outside of the tribal, or the tribe itself</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>Reveal or publicize confidential or proprietary information which includes, but is not limited to: financial information, customer information, marketing strategies and plans, databases and any information contained therein, customer lists, computer software source codes, computer/network access codes, passwords/login information and business relationships.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(11)</num>
              <text>Intentionally interfere with the normal operation of the Network, including the propagation of computer viruses and sustained high volume network traffic, which substantially hinders others in their use of the network.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(12)</num>
              <text>Examine, change, or use another person's username, password, files, and output, for which they do not have explicit authorization.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(13)</num>
              <text>Perform any other uses identified by the tribe as inappropriate.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(14)</num>
              <text>Use tribal equipment or other resources for any purpose other than that authorized by tribal management and IT department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(15)</num>
              <text>Use tribal email accounts (xxxxx@lco-nsn.gov) to open or maintain personal Internet accounts, such as social media, websites, blogs, etc.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(16)</num>
              <text>Use film cameras, digital cameras, digital camcorders, and personal devices with camera and/or video capabilities (i.e., a cellular phone including a camera capable of capturing and transmitting still or full motion images) in any way that violates Tribal policies, including illicit and illegal use. Photos showing tribal security measures, secure areas such as vaults, information on computer screens or any Network resources are strictly prohibited.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(17)</num>
              <text>And are prohibited from connecting personal electronic devices or media, including but not limited to smartphones, tablets, CD/DVD burners, special keyboards, mice, external hard drives, and USB "jump" drives, to Tribal workstations or Network resources; even for the purpose of charging the device unless authorized by the department manager and the IT department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(18)</num>
              <text>And are prohibited from using portable media storage devices, including but not limited to USB drives and other external drives, to duplicate and/or distribute Tribal information, including confidential information copyrighted materials, music, video, movies, and software unless authorized by the department manager and the IT Department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(19)</num>
              <text>Load a bootable, alternate operating system on any Tribal owned computer from any employee-owned source or media, including CD/DVD discs or USB devices ("jump" drives), without prior permission of the department manager and IT Department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(20)</num>
              <text>Connect any employee-owned electronic device whether desktop, laptop, tablet, handheld, wearable or media storage device, through a wired connection to Tribal provided network or Internet access without the prior permission of the department manager and IT Department. Wireless internet access is provided at the main lobby and Peter Larson room for guest and employees to use with personal devices.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.030</num>
          <heading>Personal posts</heading>
          <text>The Tribe recognizes that employees may post personal information on the Internet through personal websites, social media, blogs and/or uploading content to websites and the like. The Tribe respects our employee's interest in participating in these forms of personal expression on their own time. Employees should be aware; however, that problems can arise when personal postings identify or appear to be associated with the Tribe, or when a personal posting is used in ways that violate the Tribe's rights or the rights of other employees.</text>
          <text>Each employee is legally responsible for content they post on the Internet, whether on a social network, website or otherwise. You can be held personally liable for defaming others, revealing trade secrets, confidential information or proprietary information, etc. Tribal policies apply to what you post on the Internet. For example, you may not use personal postings to harass or threaten other employees or reveal confidential tribal information. Embarrassing or unkind comments about tribal employees or members, customers, or competitors are also inappropriate. Posting anonymously or under a pseudonym, does not protect your real identity; it can be discovered relatively easily.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.040</num>
          <heading>Violations</heading>
          <text>Users who violate any of the guidelines set in this agreement may be subject to disciplinary action including written warnings, revocation of access privileges, and termination. Unacceptable use of personal electronic devices will result in the immediate confiscation of the involved device(s) or media as appropriate. Depending upon the nature and severity of the violation, the confiscated device(s) or media may be held as evidence indefinitely. The Tribe also retains the right to perform personal property searches in relation to any guideline violation and report any illegal violations to the appropriate authorities.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.5</num>
        <heading>Backup and Recovery</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.5.010</num>
          <heading>Backup and Recovery</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>All tribal critical data that is stored locally on the domains file server shall be backed up daily and kept off site in the cloud.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Backups shall be done on all critical information that is stored on the shared network.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The backup shall be set up to run automatically after normal working hours and a log of the success shall be kept.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>These backups shall be based on an incremental or differential backup methodology</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Backup shall be performed in such a way that information can be restored from a time frame requested up to ninety (90) days incrementally from the past.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Information shall be restored monthly at the discretion of the IT department to ensure backups are functioning properly and that the information shall be available if needed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Department Directors shall request IT to restore information from a backup by email or memo.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Generally, the requested information shall be available to the department within twenty-four (24) hours of the request.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If the data recovery is needed do to a minor or major system failure it may take longer to restore depending on the level of failure.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The servers or equipment that are performing the backups shall be in a locked and restricted location. These servers or equipment shall also be on Uninterruptible Power Supply (UPS) to help mitigate problems resulting from power fluctuations or short power outages.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>TUC</num>
    <heading>Utility Code</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>TUC.1</num>
      <heading>Regulation of Utilities on the Lac Courte Oreilles Indian Reservation</heading>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This Code shall be known as the Utility Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.  This Code is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to regulate activities on its Reservation and protect the well-being of its membership.</text>
      <text>The purpose of this Code is to (1) establish the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Utility Commission and to set forth the terms governing the activities of the LCO Utility Commission, (2) recognize and assert the authority of the Tribe to provide a regulatory framework for all Utilities located, operating, or providing services within the Reservation, (3) to provide all retail consumers of Utilities with adequate and reliable services at reasonable rates that are consistent with the financial and economic requirements of such Utilities, (4) and to promote self-determination, encourage economic development and self-sufficiency, and facilitate and control the use of the Tribe's resources on the Tribe's Reservation.</text>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.1.1</num>
        <heading>Introduction</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.1.1.010</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this Code shall be effective on the date adopted by the Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.1.1.020</num>
          <heading>Interpretation</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this Code:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.1.1.030</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision or portion of this Code is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this Code shall not be affected thereby.  The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this Code.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.1.1.040</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Codes</heading>
          <text>All Codes and resolutions inconsistent with this Code are hereby repealed.  To the extent that this Code imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, Code or regulation, the provisions of this Code shall govern.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.1.1.050</num>
          <heading>General Definitions</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity"</strong> means the Certificate required under <cite path="TUC.2.6">Subchapter 2.6</cite> of this title.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Commission" </strong>means the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Indians ("LCO") Utility Commission established pursuant to this Code.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Commissioner" </strong>means one of the duly appointed persons comprising the LCO Utility Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Cooperative Association" </strong>means an organization that qualifies as a Utility under this Code but only authorized by its governing documents and/or by applicable law to provide Utility Service to its members.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Director"</strong> means the Director of the Lac Courte Oreille Band Utility Authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electric Energy Conversion Facility"</strong> means a plant, addition, or combination of plant and addition, designed for or capable of: (1) Generation by wind energy conversion exceeding one-half megawatt of electricity; or (2) Generation by any means other than wind energy conversion exceeding fifty megawatts of electricity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electric Transmission Facility"</strong> means an electric transmission line and associated facilities with a design in excess of one hundred fifteen kilovolts.  "Electric Transmission Facility" does not include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>A temporary electric transmission line loop that is: (i) connected and adjacent to an existing Electric Transmission Facility that was sited under <cite path="TUC.1.1">this Subchapter</cite>; (ii) within the Corridor of the sited Facility and does not cross known exclusion areas; and (iii) In place for less than one year; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>An electric transmission line that is less than one mile [1.61 kilometers] long.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electric Facility" </strong>means an Electric Energy Conversion Facility, Electric Transmission Facility, or the combination of facilities under the ownership or control of a single Person or its affiliates which, in the cumulative, is capable of generating or transmitting electricity above the minimum thresholds to qualify as an Electric Energy Conversation Facility or Electric Transmission Facility under <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electric Utility Service"</strong> means the delivery of electric energy or power generated on the Reservation to an agreed-upon point of delivery.  This includes all activities incident to the delivery of electric energy, including, but not limited to, development of infrastructure, asset acquisition, construction, and/or the operation of electricity service infrastructure (e.g., generation, transmission, distribution and control area services) as may be required to effectuate delivery of electricity generated to the end user.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Energy Utility Service"</strong> means the transmission, delivery, or furnishing of natural gas, heat, light, or power.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text><strong>"Governing Board"</strong> means the Lac Court Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians authorized under the Constitution of the Lac Court Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to approve and implement this Code.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text><strong>"Person"</strong> means any individual, group of individuals, corporation, partnership, association, state, municipality, commission, political subdivision of a state, interstate body, the federal government or any federal agency or any other entity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <text><strong>"Power Emergency"</strong> means an electric transmission line and associated facilities that have been damaged or destroyed by natural or manmade causes resulting in a loss of power supply to consumers of the power.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <text><strong>"Public Utility"</strong> means any Person that owns, operates, manages or controls any part of a plant or equipment, within the Reservation, for the production, transmission, delivery or furnishing of heat, light, water or power either directly or indirectly to or for the public.  "Public Utility" does not include Cooperative Associations as defined in this Code.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(o)</num>
            <text><strong>"Rates"</strong> means the charges established in rate schedule(s) for Utility Services provided to a customer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(p)</num>
            <text><strong>"Reservation"</strong> means all those lands on and within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(q)</num>
            <text><strong>"Site"</strong> means the location of an Electric Energy Conversion Facility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(r)</num>
            <text><strong>"Telecommunications Service"</strong> means the offering for sale of the conveyance of voice communication, including the sale of service for collection, storage, forwarding, switching, and delivery incidental to such communication, regardless of the technology or mode used to make such offering.  "Telecommunications service" includes Switched Access Service but does not include cable service or broadcast service.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(s)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> means the Lac Court Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(t)</num>
            <text><strong>"Utility"</strong> means any Person owning Utility Personal Property or providing any Utility Service to retail or wholesale customers on the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(u)</num>
            <text><strong>"Utility Personal Property"</strong> - means (i) any of the following that are used to provide a Utility Service and which are permanently or temporarily affixed to land on the Reservation: infrastructure, equipment, poles, wires, transformers, circuit breakers, switches, electrical busses, concrete pads, pipelines, compression stations, pumps, conduits, communication towers, or other facilities and (ii) any gas, water, power communication data or similar commodities or products passing through or being delivered within the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text><strong>"Utility Service"</strong> means the production, transmission, delivery or furnishing of heat, light, water or power to one or more customers.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>TUC.2</num>
      <heading>Regulation of Utilities</heading>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.1</num>
        <heading>Tribal Utility Commission</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.010</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Tribal Utility Commission</heading>
          <text>The Lac Courte Oreille Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Utility Commission ("Commission") is hereby established.  The Governing Board shall appoint the Commission Members and the Commission shall be operated and governed in accordance with the provisions of this Code, the Tribe's Constitution as well as any subsequent amendments to this Code.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.020</num>
          <heading>Mission of the Commission</heading>
          <text>The Commission's mission is to regulate Utilities located, operating, or providing services within the Reservation for the benefit of the Tribe and its members, and in furtherance of promoting the general welfare of the Tribe and its members.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.030</num>
          <heading>Commission Organization</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Commission shall comprise five (5) voting members appointed by the Governing Board.  At Least three (3) Commissioners shall be members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Commissioners shall be appointed on the basis of merit in consideration of factors including, but not limited to:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Ability to exercise sound judgment and knowledge and understanding of management, business administration, public administration, regulated industries and similar or related areas of importance to the operations of the Commission;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Expertise, experience or knowledge of public utility systems of the types under the regulatory authority of the Commission; Qualities of integrity, judgment, and sensitivity unique to Indian cultural, economic and social conditions and the goals of the Tribe and the Commission;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Knowledge of the organization and entities, governmental and private, that may be involved and provide assistance to the Commission.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Commission shall elect from among its members a Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, and a Secretary- Treasurer.  The Chairperson, or in the Chairman's absence, the Vice-Chairperson, shall preside over all Commission meetings and hearings.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.040</num>
          <heading>Terms of Office, Vacancies, Resignation, Removal</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Commissioners shall serve three (3) year terms and shall hold office until their successors have been appointed and have qualified: Provided however, the first LCO Utility Commission appointed shall serve a term of three (3) years.  One (1) Commissioner appointed to the first LCO Utility Commission shall serve a term of two (2) years.  The remaining Commissioner appointed to the first LCO Utility Commission shall serve a term of one (1) year.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If any Commissioner shall die, resign, be removed or, for any reason, be unable to serve as a Commissioner, the Governing Board shall declare his/her position vacant and shall appoint another person to fill the position.  Terms of office of all persons appointed to replace the initial Commissioners shall be for the balance of any unexpired term for each such position.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Any Commissioner may resign by delivering a written resignation to the Governing Board.  Such resignation shall be effective upon receipt, unless otherwise provided by the terms thereof.  A Commissioner's resignation or removal under <cite path="|TUC.2.1.040">this Section</cite> shall also terminate that Commissioner's status, if applicable, as a presiding officer of the Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>A Commissioner may be removed by the Governing Board for serious inefficiency or neglect of duty, or for malfeasance, misfeasance, or nonfeasance or for misconduct in office, as determined solely by Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.050</num>
          <heading>Compensation</heading>
          <text>Compensation of Commissioners, if any, shall be determined by the Governing Board and shall be paid from the Tribe's General Fund.  All fees received or charged by the Commission for any act or service rendered by the Commission in its official capacity, shall be accounted for and paid monthly to the Tribe and shall be credited to the Tribe's General Fund.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.1.060</num>
          <heading>Commission Meetings</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The regularly scheduled meetings of the Commission shall be established for each fiscal year in advance.  The Commission shall meet at least once during each quarter of the fiscal year on such dates, times and places as the Members shall determine.  In addition to the quarterly meetings, additional regularly scheduled meetings shall be held at such times as shall from time to time be fixed by the Chairperson.  Special meetings of the Commission for any purpose or purposes may be called at any time by the Commission, the Chairperson, or by a majority of Members then in office.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Commissioners may participate in a meeting through the use of a conference telephone, electronic video screen communication, or other communications equipment, so long as all Commission Members participating in such meeting can hear one another and arrangements are made for public participation at regularly scheduled meetings and, where time permits, any special meetings.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Participation in a meeting pursuant to this paragraph constitutes presence in person at that meeting if all of the following apply:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Each Commission Member participating in the meeting can communicate with all of the other Commission Members.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Each Commission Member is provided with the means of participating in all matters before the Commission, including the capacity to propose, or to interpose an objection to, a specific action to be taken by the Commission.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The Commission adopts and implements some means of verifying both of the following: (i) A person representing himself or herself to be a Commission Member communicating by telephone, electronic video screen, or other communications equipment is a Commission Member entitled to participate in such meeting; and (ii) All votes were made by such Commission Member and not by another person.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Notice of regularly scheduled and special meetings shall be given to the Commission Members not less than six (6) days prior to the meeting if delivered by first-class mail or not less than four (4) days prior to the meeting if the notice is delivered personally, by telephone, by facsimile or by electronic mail; provided, however, that notice of special meetings shall not be sent solely by electronic mail.  If mailed, such notice shall be deemed given when deposited in the United States mail, with first-class postage thereon prepaid, addressed to the Commission Member.  The notice requirements contained in <cite path="|TUC.2.1.060">this Section</cite> may be waived in writing by any Commission Member with respect to that Commission Member, either before or after the meeting.  The attendance of any Commission meeting without, as soon as reasonably practicable, protesting the lack of notice of such meeting shall constitute a waiver of notice by him or her.  All waivers shall be made part of the minutes of the meetings.  Waivers of notice for meetings shall be governed by the provisions described herein.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>A quorum for any Commission Meeting shall be three (3) of the Commission Members then in office.  A meeting at which a quorum is initially present may continue to transact business notwithstanding the withdrawal of a Commission Member, provided that any action taken is approved by the required number of Commission Members, as specified in this Governing Code.  A majority of the Commission Members then present, whether or not constituting a quorum, may adjourn any meeting to another time and place.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>In the case of an emergency situation involving matters upon which prompt action is necessary and in which it is not practicable to convene a regular or special meeting of the Commission, the Chairperson, or a majority of Commission Members then in office may call an emergency meeting or special executive session of the Commission.  During a meeting prior to the emergency meeting, or at the beginning of the emergency meeting, the Commission shall determine if an emergency exists under those standards.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Notice of an emergency meeting or special executive session shall be given to the Commission Members as soon as practicable and before the meeting is to be held.  Such notice shall be delivered personally or by telephone, including a voice messaging system or other system or technology designed to record and communicate messages, by facsimile, by electronic mail or by other electronic means and shall be deemed given at the time.  The notice requirements of <cite path="|TUC.2.1.060">this Section</cite> may be waived in writing by any Commission Member with respect to that Commission Member, either before or after the meeting.  The attendance of any Commission Member at an emergency meeting without, as soon as reasonably practicable, protesting the lack of notice of such emergency meeting shall constitute a waiver of notice by him or her.  All waivers shall be made part of the minutes of the emergency meeting.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.2</num>
        <heading>Powers and Duties of the Commission</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.010</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction and Powers of the LCO Utility Commission.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Subject to applicable laws, regulations, and the Tribe's Constitution and solely in furtherance of the mission set forth in this Code, the Commission's jurisdiction and powers include the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Investigate methods and practices of Utilities subject to the provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Initiate and preside over hearings involving the conduct of Utilities and as otherwise set forth in <cite path="TUC.2">this Chapter</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Issue orders of mandamus to enforce duly issued orders of the Commission.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Promulgate rules, regulations, and by-laws not inconsistent with this Code to carry out its duties and responsibilities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Maintain copies of reports, rates, classifications, schedules and timetables in effect and used by such Utilities and all other information desired by the Commission relating to such investigations and requirements to be filed with the Commission.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Adopt a schedule of fees and charges for services rendered relating to transcripts and the furnishing or certifying of copies of proceedings, files, and records.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Exercise all other authority delegated to it by the Governing Board that is not inconsistent with this Code.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.020</num>
          <heading>Supervision of Utility Rates and Tariffs</heading>
          <text>The Commission shall supervise all rates, tariffs, and charges of all Utilities located or operating within the Reservation.  It shall have the power, after notice and hearing as set forth herein, to establish, modify, adjust, promulgate, and enforce all rates (including rates associated with depreciation), tariffs, and charges of all Utilities.  Whenever the Commission, after hearing, shall find any existing Rates, tariffs, charges, or schedule unjust, unreasonable, insufficient, unjustly discriminatory, or otherwise in violation of any of the provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>, the Commission by order shall fix reasonable Rates, joint Rates, wheeling Rates, charges, or schedules to be followed in the future in lieu of those found to be unjust, unreasonable, insufficient, unjustly discriminatory, or otherwise in violation of any provision of law.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.030</num>
          <heading>Power of Commission to Regulate Services</heading>
          <text>Whenever the Commission shall find, after hearing that the rules and regulations, practices, facilities or services of any Utility or the methods of manufacture, distribution, transmission, storage, or supply employed by it are unjust, unreasonable, unsafe, improper, inadequate, or insufficient, the Commission shall determine the just, reasonable, safe, proper, adequate, or sufficient rules or regulations, services or methods to be observed, enforced or employed and, after hearing, shall fix the same by its orders, rule or regulation.  On demand, such utility shall furnish such commodity and render such service within the time and upon the conditions provided in such rules and regulations.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.040</num>
          <heading>Accounting Systems</heading>
          <text>The Commission shall establish a system of accounts to be kept by Utilities subject to its jurisdiction.  A Utility which maintains its accounts in accordance with the system of accounts prescribed by a federal agency or authority shall be deemed to be in compliance with the system of accounts prescribed by the Commission.  Where optional accounting is prescribed by a federal agency or authority, the Commission may prescribe which option is to be followed.  Every Utility engaged directly or indirectly in any other business than that of the production, transmission or furnishing of natural gas or electrical service shall, if required by the Commission, keep and render separately to the Commission in like manner and form the accounts of all the other business, in which case all provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite> shall apply to the books, accounts, papers, and records of the other business.  Every Utility is required to keep and render its books, accounts, papers, and records accurately and faithfully in the manner and form prescribed by the Commission and to comply with all directions of the Commission relating to these books, accounts, papers, and records.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.050</num>
          <heading>Annual Reports</heading>
          <text>The Commission may require any Utility to file annual reports in such form and content as the Commission may require, and special reports concerning any matter about which the Commission is authorized to inquire or to keep itself informed.  The Commission may require the reports to be verified.  The basic financial statements in the annual report of a Utility may, at the direction of the Commission, be examined by an independent certified public accountant and the opinion thereof included in the annual report filed with the Commission.  The Commission may require the examination and audit of all accounts, and all items shall be allocated to the accounts in the manner prescribed by the Commission.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.060</num>
          <heading>Right of Entrance and Inspection</heading>
          <text>The Commissioners and duly authorized agents, officers, and employees of the Commission, during regular business hours, may enter upon any premises of a Utility for the purpose of making examinations and tests and to inspect the accounts, books, papers, and documents, of any Utility for the purpose of exercising any power or duty provided for in this Code, and may set up and use on the premises any apparatus necessary therefore.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.070</num>
          <heading>Production of Records</heading>
          <text>The Commission may require, by Order, any Utility to produce at a reasonable time and place as the Commission designates, the records, accounts, books or papers of the Utility relating to its business or affairs within the Reservation, pertinent to any lawful inquiry regardless of whether the records are kept within or outside of the Reservation.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.080</num>
          <heading>Investigation</heading>
          <text>The Commission, upon complaint or its own initiative and whenever it may deem necessary in the performance of its duties or exercise of its authority, may investigate and examine the condition and operation of any Utility.  In conducting the investigation, the Commission may proceed with or without a hearing, but it shall make no order without affording the affected parties notice and an opportunity for a hearing.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.090</num>
          <heading>Standards; Classifications</heading>
          <text>The Commission may ascertain and fix just and reasonable standards, classifications, rules or practices to be observed and followed by any or all public Utilities with respect to the service to be furnished; ascertain and fix adequate and reasonable standards for the measurement of the quantity, quality pressure, initial voltage, or other condition pertaining to the supply of the service; prescribe reasonable rules for the examination and testing of the service and for the measurement thereof; establish or approve reasonable rules, specifications, and standards to secure the accuracy of all meters, instruments and equipment used for the measurement of any service of any Utility.  Any standards, classifications, rules, or practices now or hereafter observed or followed by any Utility may be followed by it with the Commission, and the same shall continue in force until amended by the Utility or until changed by the Commission as herein provided.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.100</num>
          <heading>Records of the Tribal Utility Commission</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The books, records and property of the Commission, including current financial and operating statements, shall be kept on file in the main office of the Commission and shall be available for inspection at all reasonable times by authorized representatives of the Commission, the Governing Board, and such others authorized by the Commission or the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Information regarding the Commission and its operations must be kept confidential, including information received by the Commission that is subject to a confidentiality obligation.  Information considered by the Commission as non-confidential shall be publicly available at requesting recipient's expense.  With the exception of records relating to the business of a named particular Utility, any records of the Commission are public records of the Tribe.  For reasonable business purposes only, such records shall be available for public inspection and copying during the Commission's regular business hours.  Copies may be obtained by payment of such copying costs as may be established by rule of the Commission.  However, the names and other identification of any Utility appearing in such records shall be redacted prior to release of such copies unless <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite> otherwise allows release of such information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Financial Statements &amp; Annual Reports shall be prepared as soon as reasonably practicable after the close of the fiscal year.  Such financial statements shall be accompanied by any report thereon of independent accountants, or, if there is no such report, the certificate of an authorized officer of the Commission that such statements were prepared without audit, under generally accepted accounting principles, from the books and records of the Commission.  Financial Statements, books, records, and property of the Commission shall be available for inspection at all reasonable times by authorized representatives of the Commission and the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Commission shall keep or cause to be kept a minute book that shall be available for public inspection during the Commission's normal business hours and shall contain the record of all meetings of the Commission, including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The date, place, those attending the proceedings thereof (other than members of the public).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>A copy of the notice of the meeting and when and how given.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Waivers of notice of meeting.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Written consents to hold meeting.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Written approvals of minutes of meeting.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>All meeting Minutes, including Minutes of committee meetings of the Commission.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Every Commissioner shall have the right at any reasonable time to inspect and copy all books, records, and documents, and to inspect the physical properties of the Commission.  No Commission Member shall use or disseminate any non-public information obtained as a result of any such inspection, or otherwise in his or her capacity as a Commission Member, for his or her own personal gain, to the detriment of the Commission or to the detriment of any competitors of any entity with which the Commission Member is affiliated except in connection with the enforcement of a tariff, contract or applicable law and consistent with the Commission policy regarding confidential information.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.110</num>
          <heading>Oversight and Directives of the Governing Board</heading>
          <text>The Commission shall serve under the Governing Board and shall comply with all directives of the Governing Board not inconsistent with this Code.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.2.120</num>
          <heading>Standard of Care.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Commissioners shall perform the duties of the Board of Commissioners, including duties as a Commissioner of any committee of the Board of Commissioners on which the Commissioner may serve, in good faith, in a manner that such Commissioner believes to be in the best interest of the Tribe and its members and with such care, including reasonable inquiry, as an ordinarily prudent person in a like situation would use under similar circumstances.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A person who performs the duties of a Commissioner shall have no liability to the Tribe, any other Commissioner or any other person based upon any failure or alleged failure to discharge that person's obligations as a Commissioner, including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, any actions or omissions that exceed or defeat a public or charitable purpose to which the Authority, or assets held by it, are dedicated. Nothing herein shall be construed to limit the liability of any Commissioner acting outside the scope of his or her duties and responsibilities as a Commissioner.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Commissioners must avoid conflicts of interest and shall exercise reasonable prudence and diligence in identifying actual or possible conflicts of interest.  A Commissioner shall recuse his or herself in any matter or decision in which one or more of the Commissioners or their employers has a material financial interest, a familial interest, or any other interest that creating a reasonably foreseeable conflict preventing the Commissioner from exercising sound and objective judgment over the matter in question.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.3</num>
        <heading>Commission Procedures</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.010</num>
          <heading>Complaints</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>An action to enforce the provisions of this Code may be initiated by the Commission <em>sua </em>sponte or by any Person with a concrete and immediate interest that will be adversely impacted by an alleged violation of this Code.  A Utility shall not have standing to initiate an action for declaratory judgment or other forms of relief arising from or in relation to this Code.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>An action under <cite path="|TUC.2.3.010">this Section</cite> shall be initiated by the filing of a Complaint in a form prescribed by the Commission.  The Complaint shall name the defendant, cite the alleged violation of this Code, all pertinent facts supporting the allegation(s), and the nature of the relief requested, and sufficient facts showing the Commission has jurisdiction over the matter in dispute.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Within ten (10) business days after receipt of a Complaint, the Commission shall make a preliminary determination on whether it possesses jurisdiction to preside over the dispute in question pursuant to this Code.  If the Commission determines that it does not possess jurisdiction over the dispute in question, the Commission shall issue a dismissal notice to the Complainant, in a form prescribed by the Commission, explaining the basis for this determination.  The dismissal notice shall constitute a final Commission order that may be appealed to the Tribal Court as set forth in <cite path="TUC.2">this Chapter</cite>.  A Commission's preliminary determination that it possesses jurisdiction shall not preclude the defendant from challenging the jurisdiction of the Commission during the course of the proceedings against it.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If the Commission determines that it possesses jurisdiction over the dispute in question, the Commission shall set a hearing date on the Complaint.  The Commission shall serve upon all parties, by personal delivery or U.S. Mail at the last known address, the Complaint, a Notice of Hearing, and copies of any Commission rules or procedures applicable to the hearing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The Commission shall give the Utility and the Complainant at least fourteen (14) days' notice of time and place when and where the hearing will be held and such matters to be considered and determined.  Both the Utility and complainant shall be entitled to be heard and to be represented by legal counsel.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.020</num>
          <heading>Witnesses and Subpoenas</heading>
          <text>The Commission may issue subpoenas and all necessary process in proceedings pending before the Commission; and each process shall extend to all parts of the Reservation and may be served by any person authorized to serve a summons and complaint pursuant to the Lac Courte Oreille Band Rules of Civil Procedure.  The Commission may adopt procedural rules not inconsistent with the provisions of this Code governing the requests for and service of subpoenas for the production of documents or testimony at a hearing or deposition setting.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.030</num>
          <heading>Enforcement</heading>
          <text>In case of failure on the part of any Person to comply with any subpoena, or in the case of the refusal of any witness to testify concerning any matter on which a witness may be interrogated lawfully, the Tribal Court, on application of the Commission, may compel obedience by proceedings for contempt as in the case of disobedience to the requirements of a subpoena issued from the Tribal Court or a refusal to testify therein.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.040</num>
          <heading>Oaths</heading>
          <text>The Commission or Commissioners may administer oaths and examine witnesses in proceedings pending before the Commission.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.050</num>
          <heading>Orders and Findings in Writing</heading>
          <text>Every order, finding, authorization, or certificate issued or approved by the Commission under any provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite> shall be in writing and filed with the Commission.  A Certificate under seal of the Commission that any order, finding, authorization or certificate has not been modified, stayed, suspended or revoked, shall be received as evidence in any proceeding as to the facts therein stated.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.060</num>
          <heading>Orders on Lawful Rates; Adequate Service</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Whenever, upon an investigation made under the provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>, the Commission shall find Rates, tolls, charges, schedules or joint Rates to be unjust, unreasonable, insufficient, preferential or unjustly discriminatory or otherwise unreasonable or unlawful, the Commission shall determine and by order fix reasonable Rates, tolls, charges, schedules or joint Rates to be imposed and observed in the future in lieu of those found to be unreasonable or unlawful.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Whenever the Commission shall find any regulations, measurements, practices, acts or service to be unjust, unreasonable, insufficient, preferential, unjustly discriminatory or otherwise unreasonable or unlawful, or shall find any service which can be reasonably demanded cannot be obtained, the Commission shall determine and by order fix reasonable measurements, regulations, acts, practices or service to be furnished, imposed, observed and followed in the future in lieu of those found to be unreasonable, inadequate or otherwise unlawful, and shall make any other order respecting measurements, regulations, acts, practices or services as shall be just and reasonable.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.070</num>
          <heading>Excessive or Discriminatory Charges; Reparation</heading>
          <text>When a complaint has been made to the Commission concerning any Rate or charge for any product or commodity furnished or service performed by any Utility, and the Commission has found, after notice and a hearing has been given as required by <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>, that the Utility has charged an excessive or discriminatory amount for such product or service, in excess of the schedules, Rates and tariffs on file with the Commission, or that the Utility has discriminated under such schedules against the complainant, the Commission may order that Utility make due reparation to the complainant therefore, with interest from the date of collection, if no discrimination will result for such reparation.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.080</num>
          <heading>Rescission or Amendment</heading>
          <text>The Commission may, at any time, on its own motion or upon motion of an interested party, and upon notice to the Utility after opportunity to be heard, rescind, alter or amend any order or decision made by the Commission and may reopen any case following the issuance of an order or decision therein, or the taking of further evidence or for any other purpose.  Any order rescinding, altering, amending, or reopening a prior decision shall have the same effect as an original order or decision.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.090</num>
          <heading>Effective Date of Orders and Decisions</heading>
          <text>Every decision made by the Commission constituting an order or decision shall be effective and enforced fourteen (14) days after it has been filed and has been served by personal delivery or by mailing a copy thereof to all parties to the proceeding in which the decision was made or to their attorneys, unless the Commission specifies a different date upon which the order or decision shall be effective.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.100</num>
          <heading>Rehearings Before Commission</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Within fourteen (14) days after service by the Commission of any decision constituting an order or decision, any party to the proceeding and any other Person aggrieved by the decision and directly affected thereby, may apply to the Commission for a rehearing in respect to any matters determined in the decision.  The Commission may grant a rehearing on any or all matters raised in the request for rehearing, if in its discretion sufficient reason exists.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Applications for rehearing shall be governed by general rules which the Commission may establish.  If, after rehearing, it shall appear that the original order or decision is in any respect unlawful or unreasonable, the Commission may reverse, change, modify or suspend the original action accordingly.  No order of the Commission shall become effective until the time for filing an application for rehearing expires or while a rehearing is pending and until ten (10) days after any such application for a rehearing is either denied, or the Commission has announced its final determination on rehearing, whichever first occurs.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The grant or denial of a rehearing shall be discretionary with the Commission.  A request for rehearing shall not be deemed a condition precedent to judicial review of a final administrative order or decision.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.110</num>
          <heading>Public Records</heading>
          <text>All decisions, transcripts, and orders of the Commission shall be public records.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.120</num>
          <heading>Transcription to be Kept</heading>
          <text>A full and complete record shall be kept of all proceedings at any formal hearing of the Commission and all testimony shall be taken down by a reporter appointed by the Commission.  A copy of the transcript shall be furnished on demand to any party to the proceedings upon payment of reasonable costs of reproduction.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.130</num>
          <heading>Appeal</heading>
          <text>Any party to any proceedings heard by the Commission who is aggrieved by the decision or by the entry of any final order or decision of the Commission therein may seek judicial review in the Tribal Court.  The rules of civil procedure and the civil provisions of this Code shall be fully applicable to any such judicial review.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.140</num>
          <heading>Judicial Review</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any party to any proceeding heard by the Commission who is aggrieved by the decision or by the entry of any final order or decision of the Commission is entitled to judicial review in the Tribal Court within thirty (30) days of the Commission's final order or decision.  A preliminary, procedural, or intermediate Commission action is not subject to review.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>An action in the Tribal Court seeking relief other than damages, attorneys' fees or costs against the Commission or an officer or employee thereof shall not be dismissed nor relief be denied on the grounds that it is against the Tribe or that the Tribe is an indispensable party and, for the limited purposes of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>, the Tribe hereby waives the sovereign immunity of the Director, the Commission, and its members for the limited purpose of Tribal Court review of decisions of the Director and the Commission.  Such waiver of immunity is further limited to prospective, equitable relief, including declaratory and injunctive relief, and does not include money damages of any kind.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Nothing herein either affects other limitations on judicial review or the power or duty of the Tribal Court to dismiss any action or deny relief on any other appropriate legal or equitable grounds; or confers authority to grant relief if any other tribal law that grants consent to suit expressly or impliedly forbids the relief which is sought.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>When the Commission finds that justice so requires, it may postpone the effective date of action taken by it, pending judicial review.  On such conditions as may be required, and to the extent necessary to prevent irreparable injury, the Tribal Court may issue all necessary and appropriate process to postpone the effective date of a commission action or to preserve the status quo or rights pending conclusion of the review proceeding.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>To the extent necessary, the Tribal Court shall decide all relevant questions of law, interpret constitutional provisions and all other tribal law, and determine the meaning or applicability of the terms of the Commission's action.  The Tribal Court may change the final order of the Commission only upon a finding that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The Commission action unlawfully withheld or unreasonably delayed the rights of the parties involved</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The findings and conclusions of the Commission are found to be, by clear and convincing evidence:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Arbitrary and capricious or an abuse of discretion;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Contrary to any right, power, privilege, or immunity accorded by the Tribal Constitution or the Indian Civil Rights Act, 25 U.S.C. § 1301, et. seq., as amended;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>In excess of jurisdiction, authority, or limitations granted by tribal law;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>In making the foregoing determinations, the Tribal Court shall review the whole record before the Commission or those parts of it cited by a party.  In order to facilitate such review, the administrative record shall be kept in complete form by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.150</num>
          <heading>Stay on Judicial Review; Bond</heading>
          <text>In case the order or decision of the Commission is stayed or suspended by order of the Tribal Court, the order of the Tribal Court shall not become effective until a bond first shall have been executed and filed with and approved by the Tribal Court, payable to the Commission, and sufficient in amount and security to insure the prompt payment by the party appealing of all damages assessed by the Commission's decision, as well as all costs and expenses related to or caused by the delay in the enforcement of the order or decision of the Commission and of all monies which any Person may be compelled to pay pending appeal or review, for transportation, transmission, product, commodity, or service including attorney's fees and costs, as well as damages, in excess of the charges fixed by the order or decision of the Commission, in case such order or decision is sustained.  The Tribal Court, in case it stays or suspends the order or decision of the Commission in any matter affecting Rates, also by order shall direct the Utility affected to pay into the Court, from time to time, there to be impounded until the final decision of the case, under such conditions as the Tribal Court may prescribe, all sums of money which may collect from any Person in excess of the sum which such Person would have been compelled to pay if the order or decision of the Commission had not been stayed or suspended.  Upon a final determination of the Tribal Court, the Court shall make an appropriate order disposing of the impounded funds in accordance with such determination.  In the event the Utility fails to comply with the conditions of the stay bond, the Commission may sue thereon for the use and benefit of the patrons or others who have suffered damage by reason of the stay.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.3.160</num>
          <heading>Step-in Rights and Other Remedies Under Tribal Law</heading>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite> shall be construed to limit or supersede any remedies available under any Tribal law or the jurisdiction of the Tribe over property and conduct on the Reservation.  In the event the Tribe assumes ownership or control over any Utility Personal Property in accordance with Tribal law, it shall be unlawful for any Person to interfere with the Tribe's or any agent of the Tribe's access to or operation of said Utility Personal Property.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.4</num>
        <heading>General Duties of Utilities</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.4.010</num>
          <heading>Adequate Service and Reasonable Rates</heading>
          <text>All Public Utilities shall furnish reasonably adequate service and facilities. The charge made by any Public Utility for any heat, light, water, telecommunications service or power produced, transmitted, delivered or furnished or for any service rendered or to be rendered in connection therewith shall be reasonable and just, and every unjust or unreasonable charge for such service is prohibited and declared unlawful.  In the case of a public utility furnishing water, the commission shall include, in the determination of water rates, the cost of fluoridating the water in the area served by the public utility furnishing water if the governing body of the city, village or town which owns or is served by the public utility furnishing water authorizes the fluoridation of water by the public utility furnishing water.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.4.020</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of Utility Personal Property</heading>
          <text>All Utilities shall maintain Utility Personal Property under its ownership or control in a manner that minimizes danger to the public and adverse environmental impacts while upholding all requirements under <cite path="TUC.2.4.010">Section TUC.2.4.010</cite> that may apply.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.4.030</num>
          <heading>Duty of Non-Discrimination</heading>
          <text>It shall be unlawful for any Utility to deny service, set rates, or develop plans for the improvement, development, or expansion of infrastructure, or engage in any preferential treatment of customers or prospective customers on the basis of race, gender, age, sexual orientation, disability, political affiliation, political classification, or tribal membership. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary under <cite path="TUC">this title</cite>, the Tribal Court shall have original jurisdiction over any claim alleging violation of <cite path="|TUC.2.4.020">this Section</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.4.040</num>
          <heading>Access to Land</heading>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite> shall be construed as a grant of a right of access to Tribal or restricted Indian land.  Access, use, and occupation of Tribal or restricted Indian land shall be governed by federal and tribal law governing easements, rights-of-way, and leases on said lands.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.4.050</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on Winter Shutoffs</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>"Winter Period" under <cite path="|TUC.2.4.050">this Section</cite> shall mean November 1st through March 31<sup>st</sup> or any other point in time in which there is reasonably foreseeable likelihood that the average temperature on the Reservation could have life-threatening effects in the absence of a reliable energy source.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A Utility that supplies Energy Utility Service on the Reservation is forbidden from disconnecting or ceasing Energy Utility Service to any household or facility where the Utility knows or has reason to know:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The household income is less than 185% of the federal poverty level;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>One or more residents is bedridden or is otherwise suffering the effects of a serious, life-threatening disease; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The disconnection of Energy Utility Service would have other serious life-threatening effects.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Any customer who pays the Utility at least 10% of the customer's income or the full amount of the Utility bill, whichever is less, during a Winter Period cannot be disconnected during that month; provided that for the purpose of <cite path="|TUC.2.4.050">this Section</cite>, the term "customer income" means the actual monthly income of the customer except for a customer who is normally employed only on a seasonal basis and whose annual income is over 135% of the federal poverty level, in which case the customer's income shall be the average monthly income of the customer computed on an annual calendar year basis.  The 10% figure in cited in this Subparagraph (c) must be prorated between Energy Utilities proportionate to each provider's share of the customer's total energy costs whenever the customer receives service from more than one provider.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If the Commission receives a Complaint alleging violation of <cite path="|TUC.2.4.050">this Section</cite>, the Commission shall issue an Interim Order within two (2) business days after receipt of the Complaint, in which the Commission shall determine whether the Utility must continue to provide Energy Service pending the outcome of the Complaint.  The Commission shall set a forthwith hearing on the Complaint for no more than fourteen (14) days after the Complaint is received by the Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.5</num>
        <heading>Utility Tariffs</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.5.010</num>
          <heading>Filing Tariffs</heading>
          <text>Every Utility operating or conducting business on the Reservation shall keep on file with the commission a tariff for each Utility Service provided on the Reservation, containing all the rules, rates and classifications used by it in the provision of its Utility Services.  Tariffs shall provide notice of any limitations on liability claimed by the Utility.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.5.020</num>
          <heading>Time to File Tariffs</heading>
          <text>Tariffs shall be filed with the Commission within sixty (60) days after the appointment of the Commission pursuant to the provisions of <cite path="TUC">this Title</cite>.  Upon appointment, the Commission or its duly delegated agent or representative shall publish a notice of commencement of the 60-day period to submit tariffs.  Failure to file tariffs within the prescribed time period shall result in a late fee of $250 per day for fourteen (14) days, and $500 per day each day thereafter.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.5.030</num>
          <heading>Publication of Tariffs</heading>
          <text>The Commission shall publish all Utility tariffs through one or more physical or digital media that is freely accessible to the public.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.5.040</num>
          <heading>Procedures to Amend Tariffs for Public Utilities</heading>
          <text>Public Utilities may not establish or implement any Tariff Alteration unless and until all procedures set forth in <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">this Section</cite> have been completed to the satisfaction of the Commission.  For the purposes of <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">this Section</cite>, a "tariff alteration" shall mean (i) an amendment to existing tariffs or any portion or provision thereof, or (ii) a change in or establishment of any rate, toll, or classification associated with the Utility Service in a manner that deviates from the terms of procedures established under existing tariff.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any Public Utility that wishes to establish a Tariff Alteration shall file a Petition for Tariff Alteration with the Commission.  The Petition shall be on a form prescribed by the Commission and shall contain, at a minimum:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The nature of the requested Tariff Alteration;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The basis for the requested Tariff Alteration with supporting documentation as necessary and appropriate;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Impacts to Customers under the proposed Tariff Alteration and under alternative actions to address the basis for the requested Tariff Alteration, including a no-action alternative.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>A certificate, on a form prescribed by the Commission, showing to the satisfaction of the Commission that the Utility has provided adequate notice of the Petition for Tariff Alteration to its customers receiving Utility Service on the Reservation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Within fourteen (14) days after receipt of a Petition for Tariff Alteration, the Commission shall publish a Notice of Comment Period providing notice to the public of its right to submit public comments on the proposed Tariff Alteration.  The Commission shall set rules and procedures associated with the form and system for filing public comments.  The Commission may determine the length of the public comment period based on, inter alia, the complexity of the proposed Tariff Alteration or the nature of the impacts on Customers.  However, public comment periods shall be for no less than thirty (30) days and no more than one hundred twenty (120) days.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>At the conclusion of the public comment period, the Commission may, at its discretion or at the direction of the Governing Board, set a public hearing on the proposed Tariff Alteration.  The Commission may set procedural rules and rules of conduct governing public hearings on proposed Tariff Alterations.  Public hearings shall be open to all Persons residing or conducting business on the Reservation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Within sixty (60) days after the conclusion of the public comment period, or within sixty (60) days after the public hearing if such public hearing takes place, the Commission shall issue an order approving or denying the proposed Tariff Alteration.  The proposed Tariff Alteration shall be deemed approved if the Commission fails to issue an order within the applicable time period, provided that the Commission may extend its timeline to issue a decision upon approval by the Governing Board and notice to the petitioning Utility.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Notwithstanding anything in <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">this Section</cite> to the contrary, the Commission may deny a requested Tariff Alteration without underdoing the public notice and comment procedures set forth in <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">this Section</cite> upon finding that the requested Tariff Alteration would constitute a <em>prima facie </em>violation of this Code.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.5.050</num>
          <heading>Cooperative Associations</heading>
          <text>Tariff Alterations by Cooperative Associations shall not be subject to the procedures under <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">Section TUC.2.5.040</cite>; <em>provided </em>that Cooperative Association tariffs maintained on file with the Commission contain procedures to ensure a Cooperative Association's membership receives adequate notice and a reasonable opportunity to be heard in relation to a proposed Tariff Alteration.  If a Cooperative Association fails to include procedures that meet these minimum requirements in its publicly filed tariffs, the Cooperative Association shall be required to undergo the procedures set forth in <cite path="|TUC.2.5.040">Section TUC.2.5.040</cite> prior to establishing or implementing any Tariff Alteration.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.2.6</num>
        <heading>Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity for Electric Facilities</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.010</num>
          <heading>Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity Required</heading>
          <text>A Utility may not begin construction of an Electric Facility within the Reservation, without first having obtained a Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity from the Commission pursuant to this Subhapter.  The Electric Facility must be constructed, operated, and maintained in conformity with the Certificate and any terms, conditions, or modifications of the Certificate.  A Certificate may be transferred, subject to the prior approval of the Commission, to any person who agrees to comply with its terms, conditions, and modifications.  Certificates shall have a term prescribed by the Commission.  The Commission may renew a Certificate in accordance with the Commission's duly adopted rules and regulations.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.020</num>
          <heading>Application for a Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>An application for a Certificate must contain the following information:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>A description of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>The type of Facility proposed;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>The gross design capacity;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>The net design capacity;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>The estimated thermal efficiency of the energy conversion process and the assumptions upon which the estimate is based;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>The number of acres that the proposed Facility will occupy; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>The anticipated timeline and schedule for:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>Acquisition of all permits and/or land use rights necessary to complete the proposed construction.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <text>Starting construction;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <text>Completing construction;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <text>Testing operations;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <text>Commencing commercial production; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <text>Beginning any planned expansions or additions.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Copies of any evaluative studies or assessments of the environmental impact of the proposed Facility submitted to any federal, regional, state, or local agency.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>An analysis of the need for the proposed Facility based on present and projected demand for the product or products to be produced by the proposed Facility, including the most recent system studies supporting the analysis of the need.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>A description of any feasible alternative methods of serving the need.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>A discussion of the Utility's policies and commitments to limit the environmental impact of its facilities, including copies of board resolutions and management directives.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>A map identifying the criteria that provides the basis for the specific location of the proposed Facility within the study area.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>A discussion of the criteria evaluated within the study area, including exclusion areas, selection criteria, policy criteria, design and construction limitations, and economic considerations.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>A discussion of the mitigative measures that the applicant will take to minimize adverse impacts which result from the location, construction, and operation of the proposed Facility.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>The qualifications of each person involved in the Facility Site location study.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>A map of the study area showing the location of the proposed Facility and the criteria evaluated.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>After determining that the application is complete, the Commission shall publish a Notice of Application for Certificate of Public Convenience of Necessity containing (1) an executive summary of the proposed Certificate, (2) instructions and timelines for filing public comments, and (3) Commission contact information to obtain a copy of the complete Application.  The following are hereby declared adequate means of publishing of the Notice of Application hereunder:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Posting the Notice on the official government website of the Tribe;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Publishing the Notice in a newspaper of general circulation on the Reservation.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The public comment period for the Application shall be set by the Commission; provided that the public comment period shall not be for less than thirty (30) days and not be for greater than one hundred twenty (120) days.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>At the conclusion of the public comment period, the Commission may, at its discretion or at the direction of the Governing Board, set a public hearing on the proposed Certificate.  The Commission may set procedural rules and rules of conduct governing public hearings on Certificate Applications.  Public hearings shall be open to all Persons residing or conducting business on the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Within ninety (90) days after the conclusion of the public comment period, or within ninety (90) days after the public hearing if such public hearing takes place, the Commission shall  issue an order approving or denying the proposed Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity.  The proposed Certificate shall be deemed approved if the Commission fails to issue an order within the applicable time period, provided that the Commission may extend its timeline to issue a decision upon approval by the Governing Board and notice to the petitioning Utility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The Commission may, at its discretion, allow an applicant to amend its application at any time during the pendency of an application.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>When a Certificate is denied and the Commission specifies a modification that would make it acceptable, the applicant may reapply.  In a reapplication:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The Utility shall indicate its acceptance or rejection of the suggested modification.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If a suggested modification is rejected by the applicant, it shall propose an alternative modification.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Reapplication must be made within six (6) months of the order denying an application.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.030</num>
          <heading>Factors to be Considered in Evaluating Applications</heading>
          <text>The Commission shall grant a Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity only when it determines that the construction and operation of the proposed facility is reasonably tailored to satisfying the public need for generation and/or delivery of electric power, that the public need satisfied will outweigh adverse impacts on the human environment, tribal natural resources, and public safety, and that there are no physically, economically, or legally feasible alternatives that would more effectively satisfy the public need.  The Commission shall be guided by, but is not limited to, the following considerations, where applicable, to aid in its evaluation of applications for a Certificate or Recertification:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Available research and investigations relating to the effects of the location, construction, and operation of the proposed Facility on public health and welfare, natural resources, and the environment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The effects of new electric energy conversion and electric transmission technologies and systems designed to minimize adverse environmental effects.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The potential for beneficial uses of waste energy from a proposed Electric Energy Conversion Facility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Adverse direct and indirect environmental effects and mitigation measures.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Alternatives to the proposed action.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Irreversible and irretrievable commitments of natural resources.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>The direct and indirect economic impacts of the proposed Facility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Existing plans for other developments or conservation measures at or in the vicinity of the proposed action.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The effect of the proposed action on existing scenic areas, historic and cultural sites and structures, and paleontological or archaeological sites.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text>The effect of the proposed action on areas unique because of biological wealth or because the areas are habitats for rare and endangered species.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text>The adequacy of the Utilities protocols and procedures in the event of a Power Emergency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text>Any input from other Tribal agencies and departments.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.040</num>
          <heading>Selection Criteria</heading>
          <text>An Application may be approved in an area only when it is demonstrated to the Commission by the applicant that any significant adverse effects resulting from the location, construction, and operation of the Facility in that area as they relate to the following, will be at an acceptable minimum, or that those effects will be managed and maintained at an acceptable minimum. The effects to be considered include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>With respect to wind energy conversion facilities:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The impact of sound levels within one hundred feet of an inhabited residence or a community building exceeding fifty (50) dBA, unless waived in writing by the owner of the occupied residence or the community building.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The impact of shadow flicker at any inhabited residence or a community building exceeding thirty (30) hours per year, unless waived in writing by the owner of the occupied residence or the community building.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The impact upon agriculture:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Agricultural production.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Family farms and ranches.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Land which the owner demonstrates has soil, topography, drainage, and an available water supply that cause the land to be economically suitable for irrigation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Surface drainage patterns and ground water flow patterns.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>The agricultural quality of the cropland.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The impact upon the availability and adequacy of:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Law enforcement.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>School systems and education programs.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Governmental services and facilities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>General and mental health care facilities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Recreational programs and facilities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Transportation facilities and networks.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Retail service facilities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Utility services.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The impact upon:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Local institutions.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Noise-sensitive land uses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Light-sensitive land uses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Rural residences and businesses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Aquifers.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Human health and safety.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Animal health and safety.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Plant life.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>Areas critical to the life stages of threatened or endangered animal or plant species.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>Temporary and permanent housing.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(11)</num>
              <text>Temporary and permanent skilled and unskilled labor.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The cumulative effects of the location of the Facility in relation to existing and planned facilities and other industrial development.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The impact upon military installations, assets, and operations.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.050</num>
          <heading>Policy Criteria.</heading>
          <text>The Commission may give preference to an applicant that will maximize benefits that result from the adoption of the following policies and practices, and in a proper case may require the adoption of such policies and practices. The Commission may also give preference to an applicant that will maximize interstate benefits. The benefits to be considered include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Less intrusion into and impact on human, animal, and plant life and habitat.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Energy conservation through location, process, and design.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Training and utilization of available employees and contractors from the Reservation for the general and specialized skills required.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Use of a primary energy source or raw material located within the region.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Avoidance of adverse impacts to residents' homes or the need to relocate residents.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The dedication of an area adjacent to the Facility to land uses such as recreation, agriculture, or wildlife management.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Economies of construction and operation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Secondary uses of appropriate associated facilities for recreation and the enhancement of wildlife.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The extent of outreach to and use of feedback from residents of the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text>A commitment of a portion of the energy produced for use on the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text>Strength of the Utility's labor relations track record.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.060</num>
          <heading>Effect of Issuance of Certificate</heading>
          <text>The issuance of a Certificate or a Permit shall be the sole approval required to be obtained from the Commission prior to commencing construction of an Electric Facility on the Reservation.  A Utility's receipt of a Certificate shall not establish an easement or other property right on or across Tribal trust lands or restricted Indian lands subject to Title 25, Part 169 of the United States Code of Federal Regulations.  Utilities that have acquired a valid Certificate under <cite path="TUC.2">this Chapter</cite> and any other required permits or land use rights, may proceed to construct or improve the site covered under the Certificate for the purposes set forth therein; provided, that if such construction and improvement commences more than four (4) years after a Certificate has been issued, then the Utility must certify to the Commission that such site and associated proposed Facilit(ies) continue to meet the conditions upon which the Certificate was issued.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.070</num>
          <heading>Rules and Regulations</heading>
          <text>The Commission may adopt rules and regulations in conformity with the provisions of <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite> and prescribe methods and procedures required therewith.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.080</num>
          <heading>Complaint and Hearing</heading>
          <text>Any Person aggrieved by the proposed issuance of a Certificate of Public Necessity and Convenience, a proposed Certificate transfer, or a proposed Recertification of an existing Certificate pursuant to <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite> may file a Complaint with the Commission within thirty (30) days after publication of the Application notice or Recertification notice.  A Person's right to challenge a proposed Certificate or Recertification shall be deemed waived; provided, that the Commission may accept a late filing at its discretion for good cause shown.  Unless otherwise provided in <cite path="|TUC.2.6.080">this Section</cite>, the Commission shall conduct a hearing on the Complaint pursuant to the procedures set forth herein and in the duly adopted rules and regulations of the Commission.  Applicable timelines associated with the Certificate, transfer, or Recertification application shall be held in abeyance pending the outcome of the hearing process as set forth in <cite path="|TUC.2.6.080">this Section</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.090</num>
          <heading>Revocation or Suspension of Certificate</heading>
          <text>A Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity may be revoked or suspended for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Discovery of any material false statement in the application or in accompanying statements or studies required of the applicant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Failure to comply with the Certificate or any terms, conditions, or modifications contained therein.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Violation of the provisions of <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite> or rules or regulations issued pursuant to <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite> by the Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>A determination by the Tribal Court.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.100</num>
          <heading>Penalties</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any person who willfully engages in any of the following conduct is subject to a civil penalty in an administrative action brought by the Commission not to exceed Ten Thousand Dollars ($10,000) for each such violation for each day the violations persist, plus any other remedy available under appliable Tribal law:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Begins construction of an Electric Energy Conversion Facility or an Electric Transmission Facility without having been issued a Certificate pursuant to <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Constructs, operates, or maintains an Electric Energy Conversion Facility or an Electric Transmission Facility other than in compliance with the Certificate or Permit and any terms, conditions, or modifications contained therein.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Violates any provision of <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite> or any rule adopted by the Commission pursuant to <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite></text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Falsifies, tampers with, or renders inaccurate any monitoring device or method required to be maintained pursuant to a Certificate issued pursuant to <cite path="TUC.2.6">this Subchapter</cite>.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.110</num>
          <heading>Approval for Temporary Operation or Variance</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The commission may approve temporary operation of facilities or a temporary variance from approved construction, operation, or maintenance of facilities upon a showing of good cause and receipt of a utility certification that the activities will have no adverse impacts upon the welfare of the Tribe or the environment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Commission may issue a temporary approval or variance without the necessity of notice, publication, or hearing with any additional terms, conditions, or modifications deemed necessary to minimize impacts.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.2.6.120</num>
          <heading>Use by One Utility of the Facilities of Another Utility</heading>
          <text>Whenever upon hearing, after due notice, the Commission has found that the public convenience and necessity requires the use by one Electric Utility of the conduits, wires, poles, pipes or other equipment or any part thereof on, over or under any street highway and belonging to another Electric Utility, and that such use will not result in irreparable injury to the owner or other users of such equipment, nor any substantial detriment to the service, and that such Electric utilities have failed to agree upon such use or terms and conditions or compensation for the same, the Commission, by order, may direct that such use be permitted, and prescribe reasonable compensation and reasonable terms and conditions for such joint use.  If such use is directed, the Electric Utility to which the use is permitted shall be liable to the owner or other users of such equipment for such damages as may result therefrom to the property of such owner or other users thereof.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>TUC.3</num>
      <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Utility Authority</heading>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.3.1</num>
        <heading>Utility Authority Established</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.1.010</num>
          <heading>Establishment of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Utility Authority</heading>
          <text>The Lac Courte Oreille Tribal Utility Authority ("Authority") is hereby established.  The actions, responsibilities, and limitations of the Authority are established under the terms of this Code, as the same may be amended in the future.  The Authority is established as an incorporated enterprise of the Tribal Government.  It is the intent of the Tribe that the Authority shall at all times be an instrumentality of the Tribal Government and shall serve under the direction of the Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.1.020</num>
          <heading>Constitutional Authority</heading>
          <text>The Authority is established pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, Section 1(l) of the Constitution and By Laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin</cite>, which authorizes the Tribe's Governing Board to "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a housing authority, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Tribe or residents of the reservation."</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.1.030</num>
          <heading>Sovereign Immunity</heading>
          <text>As an instrumentality of the Tribe, the inherent sovereign immunity of the Tribe is extended to the Authority pursuant to <cite path="|TCT.1.3.020">Section TCT.1.3.020</cite> of the Sovereign Immunity Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and the laws of the United States ("Sovereign Immunity Code").  The Authority may waive its sovereign immunity from suit only in accordance with the processes set forth in <cite path="|TCT.1.2.030">Section TCT.1.2.030</cite> of the Sovereign Immunity Code.  Except as otherwise expressly authorized by the Governing Board, any waiver of the Authority's immunity of suit shall be limited to the Authority and shall not extend to any other department, agency, or instrumentality of the Tribe, and such waiver shall further be limited to judgments effecting the assets and/or revenue streams of the Authority.  Notwithstanding anything herein to the contrary, the sovereign immunity of the Authority shall not apply to actions commenced against the Authority under the provisions of this Code.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.1.040</num>
          <heading>Mission of the Authority</heading>
          <text>The Authority's mission is to provide and manage Utility Services, as defined herein, to customers within and around the Reservation in furtherance of Tribal self-determination, the economic growth of the Tribe and its members, and promoting reliable access to Utility Services on the Reservation, and to furnish, provide, and maintain such service, instrumentalities, equipment, and facilities to promote the safety, health, comfort, and convenience of its customers, employees, and the public, and as shall be in all respects adequate, convenient, just, and reasonable, and without any unjust discrimination or preference.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.3.2</num>
        <heading>Utility Authority Personnel</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.2.010</num>
          <heading>Authority Director</heading>
          <text>The Governing Board shall hire an employee to serve as Director of the Authority.  The Director shall be the operating official of the Authority and shall have direction of all parts of the actual operations.  The Director's responsibilities shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Development, implementation, and monitoring of the Authority Implementation Plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Management and oversight of all Authority activities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Delegation of management duties to Authority employees, if any, to the extent that are not specifically designated by this Code, the Governing Board, or the Authority Implementation Plan as duties to be performed exclusively by the Director.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Supervision of all employees of the Authority, excluding the Board of Commissioners, including supervision of the performance of staff in respect to all matters such as conformance to approved budgets, standards, program inspection, cost control, employee relations and in-service training.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Interfacing with employees, contractors, and customers of the Authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Ensuring compliance with approved budgets and policies and procedures approved by the Board of Commissioners relating to standards, programs inspection, cost control, employee relations and service training.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Rendering regular reports to the Governing Board in accordance with this Code, the Authority Implementation Plan, or as otherwise requested by the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Performing all duties incident to the position of Director and such other duties as from time to time may be assigned by the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.2.020</num>
          <heading>Other Authority Employees</heading>
          <text>Nothing in this Code shall be construed to restrict the authority of the Governing Board to hire employees to a position not specifically identified herein to assist in carrying out the functions and mission of the Authority.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>TUC.3.3</num>
        <heading>Utility Authority Operations</heading>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.010</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Authority</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Subject to applicable laws, regulations, the Constitution and By-Laws of the Tribe and any duly enacted and approved policies and procedures of the Authority; and solely in furtherance of the mission set forth in this Code, the Authority's powers include the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>To operate and administer Utility Services;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>To establish Utility rates and tariffs, including procedures governing changes in rates and tariffs applicable to customers of the Authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>To enter into contracts with any governmental agency, federal, state or local, or any person, partnership, corporation or Indian tribe;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>To retain independent contractors as consultants or technical and/or maintenance personnel;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>To own property and assets in its separate and distinct capacity as an enterprise of the Tribal Government, including Utility Personal Property as defined in this Code;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>To sue and be sued in its separate and distinct capacity as an enterprise of the Tribal Government;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>To borrow money, to issue temporary or long-term evidence of indebtedness, and to repay the same.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>To pledge the assets and receipts of the Authority as security for debts; and to acquire, sell, lease, exchange, transfer or assign personal property or interests therein.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>To purchase land or interests in land or take the same by gift; to lease land or interests in land to the extent provided by law.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>To purchase insurance in any stock or mutual company for any property or against any risks or hazards.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(11)</num>
              <text>To adopt such policies, procedures, and bylaws necessary and appropriate, consistent with this Code.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.020</num>
          <heading>Records</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The books, records and property of the Authority, including current financial and operating statements, shall be kept on file in the main office of the Authority and shall be available for inspection at all reasonable times by the Director, then-serving members of the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Information regarding the Authority and its operations must be kept confidential, including information received by the Authority that is subject to a confidentiality obligation.  Information considered by the Authority as non-confidential shall be publicly available at requesting recipient's expense.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Financial Statements and Annual Reports shall be prepared as soon as reasonably practicable after the close of the fiscal year.  Such financial statements shall be accompanied by any report thereon of independent accountants, or, if there is no such report, the certificate of an authorized officer of the Authority that such statements were prepared without audit, under generally accepted accounting principles, from the books and records of the Authority.  Financial Statements, books, records, and property of the Authority shall be available for inspection at all reasonable times by the Governing Board and any other persons authorized by the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Every Commissioner shall have the right at any reasonable time to inspect and copy all books, records, and documents, and to inspect the physical properties of the Authority.  No Commissioner shall use or disseminate any non-public information obtained as a result of any such inspection, or otherwise in his or her capacity as a Commissioner, for his or her own personal gain, to the detriment of the Authority or to the detriment of any competitors of any entity with which the Commissioner is affiliated except in connection with the enforcement of a tariff, contract or applicable law and consistent with the Authority policy regarding confidential information.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.030</num>
          <heading>Reports to the Governing Board</heading>
          <text>The Director shall prepare and submit a report to the Governing Board on a quarterly basis.  The report shall include, but not be limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Authority financial conditions, including cashflow statements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Authority customer list;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Any rate changes or planned rate changes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Any proposed amendments to the Authority Implementation Plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Procurement, sale, or material change in any Utility Personal Property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Any other information requested by the Governing Board;</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.040</num>
          <heading>Authority Implementation Plan</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Prior to engaging in Utility Services, the Director shall prepare and present to the Governing Board for its approval an Authority Implementation Plan for the provision of Electric Utility Services.  The Implementation Plan may be modified from time to time by the Authority upon final approval of the Governing Board.  The Director or his/her delegee shall maintain a current version on file available for inspection by the Governing Board and any other person authorized by the Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Authority Implementation Plan shall establish the overall operational framework governing the operations of the Authority and shall include, without limitation, the following components:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Authority Operations Plan, including:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Plan for resources use and energy efficiency</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Accounting system</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Standards of Service designated to ensure sage, adequate, efficient and timely provision of Electric Utility Services</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>Customer outreach</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Start-Up Funding and Staffing Plan, including:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Staffing needs and requirements</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Capital requirements</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Start-up activities and cost summary</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>Estimated infrastructure costs</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>Estimated third party contractor costs</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Policy on rate setting and customer rights and responsibilities, including:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Initial rate schedule</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Procedure for setting and changing rates and tariffs, including procedures for noticing the public of changes to rates and tariffs</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.050</num>
          <heading>Revenue Allocation Plan</heading>
          <text>All revenue generated from the activities of the Authority shall be allocated in accordance with an Allocation Plan approved by the Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>TUC.3.3.060</num>
          <heading>Annual Budget</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Authority shall establish an annual budget enumerating the necessary costs of the Authority including operation, maintenance, administration of capital improvements, debt service, personnel, liability and other insurance, replacement, a reserve for major repairs and replacements, and lease payments for use of Tribal community resources and facilities.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A proposed Annual Budget shall be developed by the Director and shall be presented to the Governing Board for its approval prior to the commencement of the Tribe's fiscal year.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2024-03-18" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-38" eff="2024-03-18" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <xi:include href="./PAP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./attachments/index.xml"/>
</document>
