<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <meta>
    <effective>0001-01-01</effective>
    <print>
      <volumes>
        <volume start="TCT"/>
        <volume start="GNC"/>
      </volumes>
    </print>
    <recency through="2023-10-10">
      <doc id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" type="resolution"/>
    </recency>
  </meta>
  <heading>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law</heading>
  <xi:include href="./TCT.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./MCC.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CTZ.xml"/>
  <container containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>GWE</num>
    <heading>General Welfare Exclusion</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>GWE.1</num>
      <heading>General Welfare Exclusion Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</heading>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to promote the traditional value that children are the most important asset of the Tribe, which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite> empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people" and pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(j)">Article V, §1(j)</cite> "to administer any funds within  the control of the Band; to make expenditures from available funds for public purposes…All expenditures by the Governing Board shall be in accord with a previously approved budget, and the amount so paid shall be a matter of public record at all times." As such the Tribal Governing Board adopts this Ordinance to memorialize and confirm existing procedures used in the administration of general welfare assistance programs and services and is not to be construed as the creation of new general welfare assistance rights that previously did not exist. Assistance provided prior to the enactment of this Ordinance is hereby ratified and confirmed as general welfare assistance pursuant to the authority of the Tribal Constitution. It is intended to establish a framework to improve the coordination of general welfare doctrine compliance. Programs and Services referred to herein must be authorized by independent action of the Tribe or its designees.</text>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.1</num>
        <heading>Introduction</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.010</num>
          <heading>Title</heading>
          <text>This ordinance shall be known as the General Welfare Exclusion Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Tribe").</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.020</num>
          <heading>Authority</heading>
          <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h)</cite> and (j) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people" and pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(j)">Article V, §1(j)</cite> "to administer any funds within  the control of the Band; to make expenditures from available funds for public purposes…All expenditures by the Governing Board shall be in accord with a previously approved budget, and the amount so paid shall be a matter of public record at all times." On September 18, 2014, the Tribal General Welfare Exclusion Act of 2014 passed both houses of Congress, and was signed into law on September 29, 2014. The Tribal Governing Board now expressly embraces the forgoing principles as an integral part of this Ordinance and as guiding principles in construing the Tribe's compliance with Code Section 139E, the Safe Harbor Rules, and the General Test. The assistance payments and services authorized by this Ordinance are intended to qualify for favorable tax treatment under the general welfare doctrine to the fullest extent permitted by law and shall be construed accordingly.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.030</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <text>This ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The purpose of this Ordinance is to further empower Tribal self-determination.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Governing Board have a long history of providing critical benefits to Tribal Members, and these programs are fundamental to the sovereignty and cultural integrity of the Tribe. The Tribe, and not the IRS, are in the best position to determine the needs of their members and provide for the general welfare of their tribal citizens and communities.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.040</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.050</num>
          <heading>Interpretation</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe as the Indian General Welfare Exclusion Act requires that "any ambiguities in new Code section 139E shall resolved by the IRS in favor of Indian Tribal governments and deference shall be given to Indian Tribal governments for programs administered and authorized by the Tribe to benefit the general welfare of the Tribal community."</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Does not waive the sovereign immunity of the Tribe in any respect.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.060</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a Court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.1.070</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
          <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.2</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.2.010</num>
          <heading>General Definitions</heading>
          <text>Any term not defined in <cite path="|GWE.1.2.010">this section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Assistance" </strong>means any Program benefits or payments that qualify for tax free treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Beneficiary" </strong>means any person or persons entitled to receive Assistance in accordance with specific Program guidelines. Programs designed to qualify for exemption under Code Section 139E may benefit Members, spouses of a Member, and/or Dependents of a Member. Programs designed to meet the Safe Harbor may benefit any Member or Qualified Nonmember.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Code"</strong> means the internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Compensation"</strong> for services should reflect that qualifying Programs are not disguised employment. However, this shall not prevent the Tribe  from structuring Programs with community service ties so long as such ties are consistent with the General Welfare Exclusion. For example, Programs similar to the Workforce Investment Act may include tax free Assistance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Constitution"</strong> means the Constitution of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"Custodian"</strong> means a person having care and custody of a child under any arrangement with the child's parent or guardian or pursuant to order of the Tribal or State Court.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"General Welfare Exclusion"</strong> means assistance shall be treated as non-taxable so long as it satisfies the requirements under Code Section 139E, it is provided under a Safe Harbor Program, or it meets the General Test.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"General Test" </strong>means assistance will be treated as meeting the General Test under the General Welfare Exclusion if the benefits are:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>paid by or on behalf of a Tribe,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>under a social benefit program,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>based on either needs of the Indian community itself or upon individual needs of the recipient (which need not be financial in nature), and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>are not Compensation for services or per capita payments.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Lavish" or "Extravagant"</strong> Except as otherwise required for compliance with final guidance issued under Code Section 139E following consultation, lavish and extravagant shall be determined by the Tribal Governing Board in its sole discretion based on all facts and circumstances, taking into account needs unique to the Tribe as well as the social purpose being served by the particular Assistance at hand.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Ordinance"</strong> means the General Welfare Ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text><strong>"Pay"</strong> or "<strong>Paid" </strong>or "<strong>Payment</strong>" means pay or reimbursement in whole or in part.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text><strong>"Program"</strong> or "<strong>Approved Program</strong>" means any program established by or under authority of the Tribal Governing Board, including any program authorized through the annual budget process, to provide Assistance hereunder. A program shall not fail to be treated as an Indian tribal government Program solely by reason of the Program being established by tribal custom or government practice.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <text><strong>"Promotion of the General Welfare"</strong> or "<strong>Social Benefit</strong>" should reflect a goal or goals established by the Tribal Governing Board for the promotion of the general welfare of the Tribe, for example, in furtherance of tribal self-determination, culture and tradition.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <text><strong>"Qualified Nonmember"</strong> means a spouse, former spouse, legally recognized domestic partner or former domestic partner, ancestor, descendant, or Dependent of a member of the Tribe. Individual Tribal Programs may, but are not required to, cover Qualified nonmembers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(o)</num>
            <text><strong>"Reservation"</strong> means the reservation of the Lac Courte Oreille Reservation boundaries or, if the context so permits, any other Indian reservation as defined in Internal Revenue Code Section 162(j).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(p)</num>
            <text><strong>"Safe Harbor Program"</strong> shall refer to a Program that meets the safe harbor requirements set forth herein and IRS Revenue Procedure 2014-35, as the same may hereafter be amended. Need shall be presumed for Assistance provided under a Safe Harbor Program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(q)</num>
            <text><strong>"Service Area"</strong> has the same meaning as in 25 C.F.R. Section 20.100.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(r)</num>
            <text><strong>"Spouse"</strong> shall be determined in accordance with Tribal laws, customs and traditions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(s)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong>  means Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.3</num>
        <heading>Indian General Welfare Benefits (Code Section 139E)</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.010</num>
          <heading>. Non-Binding Designation</heading>
          <text>General welfare services and payments hereunder are paid from assets of Tribal Governing Board; all payments are based on budget availability, and the Tribal Governing Board  does not guarantee any payments hereunder. Benefits paid hereunder on the basis of need shall not be treated as a resource of the Member for any purpose. The Tribal Governing Board reserves the right to cancel, adjust, modify or revoke any benefits that are treated as a resource of the Tribal Member.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.020</num>
          <heading>Indian General Welfare Benefits (Code Section 139E)</heading>
          <text>Programs that meet the following criteria for exemption under Code Section 139E shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion without the applicant having to demonstrate individual need.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.030</num>
          <heading>General Criteria for Qualification Under Code 139E</heading>
          <text>Each payment must be made or service provided to or on behalf of a Member (or any Spouse or Dependent of the Member) pursuant to a Program under this Ordinance shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion so long as the following criteria are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Program is administered under specified guidelines and does not discriminate in favor of the members of the governing body of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are available to any Tribal Member who meets such guidelines;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are for the "promotion of the general welfare";</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are not Lavish or Extravagant; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Program benefits are not Compensation for services.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.040</num>
          <heading>Ceremonial Activities</heading>
          <text>Any items of cultural significance, reimbursement of costs, or cash honorarium for participation in cultural or ceremonial activities for the transmission of tribal culture shall not be treated as Compensation for services.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.050</num>
          <heading>Special Effective Dates</heading>
          <text>Code Section 139E is effective for Assistance in taxable years for which the period of limitations on a refund or credit under Code Section 6511 has not expired. If the period of limitation on a refund or credit resulting from the application of Code Section 139E (a) would otherwise expire before the one-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of Code Section 139E, a refund or credit (to the extent attributed thereto) may be made or allowed if a claim is filed before the close of such one-year period.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.060</num>
          <heading>Safe Harbor Programs</heading>
          <text>Programs that meet the following general criteria for safe harbor treatment, and provide qualifying safe harbor benefits, shall be treated as non-taxable Assistance under the General Welfare Exclusion without the applicant having to demonstrate individual need.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.070</num>
          <heading>General Criteria for Safe Harbor Treatment</heading>
          <text>Each Safe Harbor Program shall satisfy the following general criteria:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The benefit is provided under a specific Approved Program of the Tribe</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Program has written guidelines specifying how individuals may qualify for the benefit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The benefit is available to any tribal member, Qualified Nonmember, or identified group of Tribal Members or Qualified Nonmembers who satisfy the Program guidelines, subject to budgetary restraints;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The distribution of benefits from the Program does not discriminate in favor of the governing body of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The benefit is not Compensation for services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The benefit is not Lavish or Extravagant under the facts and circumstances</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.3.080</num>
          <heading>Qualifying Safe Harbor Benefits</heading>
          <text>The following benefits may be provided under a Safe Harbor Program. The benefits listed in the parenthetical language herein are illustrative only, rather than an exhaustive list. Thus, a benefit may qualify for exclusion from gross income as a Safe Harbor Program even though the benefit is not expressly described in the parenthetical language herein, provided that it meets all other requirements of Article VI and Revenue Procedure 2014-35 (as may be amended):</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Housing programs. Programs relating to principal residences and ancillary structures that are not used in any trade or business, or for investment purposes that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay mortgage payments, down payments, or rent payments (including but not limited to security deposits) for principal residences.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Enhance habitability of housing, such as by remedying water, sewage, or sanitation service, safety issues (including but not limited to mold remediation), or heating or cooling issues.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide basic housing repairs or rehabilitation (including but not limited to roof repair and replacement).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay utility bills and charges (including but not limited to water, electricity, gas, and basic communications services such as phone, internet, and cable).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Pay property taxes or make payments in lieu of taxes (PILOTs).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Educational Programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Provide students (including but not limited to post-secondary students) transportation to and from school, tutors, and supplies (including but not limited to clothing, backpacks, laptop computers, musical instruments, and sports equipment) for use in school activities and extracurricular activities.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Provide tuition payments for students (including but not limited to allowances for room and board on or off campus for the student, spouse, domestic partner, and Dependents) to attend preschool, school, college or university, online school, educational seminars, vocational education, technical education, adult education, continuing education, or alternative education.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide for the care of children away from their homes to help their parents or other relatives responsible for their care to be gainfully employed or to pursue education.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Provide job counseling and programs for which the primary objective is job placement or training, including but not limited to allowances for expenses for interviewing or training away from home (including but not limited to travel, auto expenses, lodging, and food); tutoring; and appropriate clothing for a job interview or training (including but not limited to an interview suit or a uniform required during a period of training).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Elder and disabled programs. Programs for individuals who have reached age 55 or are mentally or physically disabled (as defined under applicable law, including but not limited to tribal government disability codes or laws) that provide:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Meals through home-delivered meal programs or at a community center or similar facility.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Home care such as assistance with preparing meals or doing chores, or day care outside the home.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Local transportation assistance.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Improvements to adapt housing to special needs (including but not limited to grab bars and ramps).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Cultural and religious programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay expenses (including but not limited to admission fees, transportation, food, and lodging) to attend or participate in an Indian Tribe's cultural, social, religious, or community activities such as pow-wows, ceremonies, and traditional dances.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Pay expenses (including but not limited to admission fees, transportation, food, and lodging) to visit sites that are culturally or historically significant for the Tribe, including but not limited to other Indian reservations.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Pay the costs of receiving instruction about the Tribe's culture, history, and traditions (including but not limited to traditional language, music, and dances).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay funeral and burial expenses and expenses of hosting or attending wakes, funerals, burials, other bereavement events, and subsequent honoring events.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Pay transportation costs and admission fees to attend educational, social, or cultural programs offered or supported by the Tribe.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Other qualifying assistance programs. Programs that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Pay transportation costs such as rental cars, substantiated mileage, and fares for bus, taxi, and public transportation between an Indian reservation, service area, or service unit area and facilities that provide essential services to the public (such as medical facilities and grocery stores).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Pay for the cost of transportation, temporary meals, and lodging of a Tribal Member or Qualified Nonmember while the individual is receiving medical care away from home.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance to individuals in exigent circumstances (including but not limited to victims of abuse), including but not limited to the costs of food, clothing, shelter, transportation, auto repair bills, and similar expenses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Pay costs for temporary relocation and shelter for individuals displaced from their homes (including but not limited to situations in which a home is destroyed by a fire or natural disaster).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance to individuals temporary displaced from their homes for the costs of food, clothing, transportation, auto repair bills, and similar expenses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Provide assistance for transportation emergencies (for example, when stranded away from home) in the form of transportation costs, a hotel room, and meals.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Pay the cost of nonprescription drugs (including but not limited to traditional Indian tribal medicines).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>GWE.1.4</num>
        <heading>Programs Meeting the General Test</heading>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.010</num>
          <heading>Programs Meeting the General Test</heading>
          <text>Programs that do not qualify for non-taxable treatment under Code Section 139E or under an IRS Safe Harbor, will nonetheless be treated as non-taxable if Program benefits meet the General Test for treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion. For purposes of the General Test only, needs must be shown in one manor described in <cite path="GWE.1.4.020">GWE.1.4.20</cite> or <cite path="GWE.1.4.030">GWE.1.4.030</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.020</num>
          <heading>Individual Needs</heading>
          <text>Individual Needs. Certain Programs may be based on individual need, rather than an overall need of the Tribe. For those Programs, the Tribal Governing Board may establish income guidelines unique to the Tribe or may use readily available income guidelines used by state or federal programs to demonstrate individual or family need. When individual or family need must be shown, the Program may take into account individual circumstances or extraordinary need to overcome presumptions based on income alone.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.030</num>
          <heading>Community Needs</heading>
          <text>Certain Programs may be based on community needs, which are so important to the self-determination, culture and traditions of the Tribe that Assistance may be deemed necessary regardless of individual income or wealth. For example, states provide public education to all citizens regardless of individual income or wealth. Some Programs may address both individual and community-based needs. The Tribal Governing Board reserves the right to require any applicant applying for consideration based on non-financial or community-based needs to demonstrate how the Program benefits will benefit the tribal community as a whole, including preservation of culture, tradition and self-determination. Approval based on non-financial need criteria is made on a facts and circumstances basis and will be guided by traditional values and culture. A Program will be deemed to be based on community or non-financial needs if so designated by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.040</num>
          <heading>Purpose of the Program</heading>
          <text>All Assistance disbursed pursuant to this Ordinance shall be designed to promote the general welfare, self-determination, culture and tradition of the Tribe. The Tribal Governing Board shall establish objectives for the furtherance of the general welfare, self-determination, culture and tradition of the Tribe and assess progress on said objectives in connection with its budgeting and/or strategic planning process. Approved Programs shall be renewed, established, modified, or terminated based upon the needs of the Tribe as compared to the objectives set by the Tribal Governing Board from time to time hereunder. All Programs hereunder shall provide a social benefit for the promotion of the general welfare of the Band and be limited to purposes consistent with treatment under this Ordinance. Such purposes may include, for example, and not by way of limitation, assistance for medical care, food, shelter, health, education, subsistence, housing, elder and disabled care, assistance to meet cultural, traditional and religious needs of the Tribe and its membership, and assistance to promote self-sufficiency, self-determination, Tribal image, entrepreneurship, and the employment of Tribal Members. Designation by the Tribal Governing Board if a Program as falling under this Ordinance shall be conclusive evidence that the Tribal Governing Board, following a good faith review of Tribal needs and goals, has determined that said Program is established to achieve a social benefit and to promote the general welfare of the Tribe.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.050</num>
          <heading>Eligibility and Application Procedures</heading>
          <text>Each approved Program shall set forth the specific eligibility rules and limitations applied to that Program. Each designated department shall present program descriptions, which include eligibility rules and limitations, along with application forms and procedures, for approval by the Tribal Governing Board or its designee. Only those descriptions, application forms and procedures which are approved by the Tribal Governing Board or its designee shall be in force and effect. Program guidelines may limit benefits to an identified group of Members or Qualified Nonmembers, as applicable. All Programs may be limited by budget availability. In the absence of specific Program guidelines to the contrary, all Programs shall be deemed to incorporate eligibility criteria necessary for compliance with Code Section 139E.</text>
          <text>All Assistance disbursed or provided pursuant to this Ordinance must be used for the purpose stated in the approved Program description, and any application for the applicable Assistance. The Tribe or its designee shall keep books or records deemed appropriate to demonstrate compliance with the Ordinance. Recipients of benefits hereunder are responsible for maintaining books or records as may be required for substantiation to the IRS for individual income tax purposes. In the event that Assistance payments and/or services are used or pledged for a purpose inconsistent with the purpose set forth in the applicable approved Program or the Member's application, the Tribal Governing Board or designee may require the repayment of the welfare assistance payment. The Tribal Governing Board or designee is authorized to offset any other payments owed to a Tribal member if such an offset is necessary to secure repayment of a welfare assistance payment in accordance with <cite path="GWE.1.4.030">this Section</cite>.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.060</num>
          <heading>Limitations on Welfare Assistance Payments</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Governing Board, within its annual budgets, by resolution or by motion, may adopt guidelines establishing the maximum Assistance payments to be made to Tribal members for certain specified purposes or programs or may delegate the establishment of such limitations to the program level. Such guidelines may also include, by way of example, factors to be considered in determining whether deviations from the general payment limitations should be permitted. Departments charged with administering particular programs may be delegated authority to adopt program guidelines to the extent not contrary to the overall guidelines and limitations established by the Tribal Governing Board. In no event shall Assistance be lavish or extravagant.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.070</num>
          <heading>Annual Budgeting: Unfunded Program</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Governing Board, through its annual budgeting process, by resolution or by motion, shall designate those funding sources that are available for the payment of Assistance benefits. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary, the Assistance payments authorized hereunder shall be “unfunded” for tax purposes and no Beneficiary shall have an interest in or right to any funds budgeted for or set aside for Assistance payments until actually paid. Assistance benefits shall remain assets of the Tribe until distributed, and the Approved Programs shall be administered to avoid premature taxation through the doctrines of constructive receipt and/or economic benefit.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.080</num>
          <heading>Forfeiture</heading>
          <text> Notwithstanding anything herein to the contrary, Assistance benefits may be revoked or forfeited for any Beneficiary who is found to have misapplied program funds or to have made any misrepresentations during the application process. Assistance may also be forfeited should said benefits be treated as a resource to the detriment of the Tribe or a Beneficiary. The Tribe shall have a right of recovery with regard to any excess or improper payments hereunder.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.090</num>
          <heading>Programs Not Limited to Means Testing</heading>
          <text>Programs that qualify under Code Section 139E or the IRS Safe Harbor shall not require a showing of individual need or means testing in order to achieve non-taxable treatment under the General Welfare Exclusion. The Tribe also reserves the right to provide community-based Programs and Programs based on non-financial need under the General Test that are not individually means tested. The Tribe recognizes that means testing can distort certain tribal cultural and community values. The Tribe has participated in consultation with the United States Treasury Department and IRS and will evaluate Programs periodically as guidance is further developed through consultation with the Tribe.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>GWE.1.4.100</num>
          <heading>Other Tax Exemptions</heading>
          <text>Notwithstanding anything herein to the contrary, the Tribe reserves the right to waive income limits or needs basis criteria, to the extent otherwise applicable, for expenditures that otherwise qualify for tax exemptions including tax exemptions under Titles 25 or 26 of the United States Code so long as the conditions for exemption are met. Without limitation, this includes Member medical benefits exempt under Section 9021 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010 (Code Section 139D) and per capita expenses exempt under 25 U.S.C. Sections 1407 and 1408.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2023-10-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-125" eff="2023-10-10" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <xi:include href="./ELE.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CSV.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./DMR.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./GNC.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./VEH.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./PHS.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./PRP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./CMP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./LLC.xml"/>
  <container containing-doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>ITP</num>
    <heading>Information Technology Policy</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>ITP.1</num>
      <heading>Information and Technology Use and Security Policy</heading>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to provide for the decent, safe, and sanitary dwellings for the members of the Tribe which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a Tribal Governing Board, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation." (<cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, § 1(l)</cite>). Pursuant to this inherent sovereign authority, the Tribal Governing Board hereby enacts this ordinance.</text>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.1</num>
        <heading>Introduction</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.010</num>
          <heading>Title</heading>
          <text>This policy and procedure manual shall be known as the Lac Courte Oreilles Information and Technology Policy.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.020</num>
          <heading>Authority</heading>
          <text>This policy and procedure manual is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to promote the traditional value that children are the most important asset of the Tribe, which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(q)">Article V, § 1 (q),</cite> <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">(s)</cite>, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(t)">(t)</cite>, and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(u)">(u)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians empowered the Tribal Governing Board to establish a Children's Court Division of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court..."</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.030</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <text>The Tribe depends heavily on its information resources today and will become even more dependent on them in the future. Information is one of the Tribe's most important assets. Protection of information assets is necessary to establish and maintain trust between Tribal members, Tribal Departments and Entities,  Tribal leadership, and third-party  vendors . The security of the Tribe's systems and information is essential to its safety and to the privacy of Tribal financial information. The purpose of this policy is to establish general guidelines for maintaining a computing environment within the Tribe that is controlled, consistent and secure. The policy's primary objective is to enhance the productivity of users by optimizing network performance, reducing wasted use of resources and the risk of legal liability caused by illegal or inappropriate use of the Network, and to provide for Network security and safety. The Tribe is establishing standards relating to administrative, technical, and physical safeguards for Tribal records and information. These safeguards are to ensure the security and confidentiality of Tribal records and information, protect against any anticipated threats or hazards to the security or integrity of these records, and protect against unauthorized access to or use of these records or information that would result in substantial harm or inconvenience to the Tribe or a Tribal member. Attacks frequently compromise personal and business data; it is critical for the Tribe to respond quickly and effectively when security breaches occur by implementing an Incident Response Program that responds to incidents in a consistent manner so that the appropriate actions are taken. These incident response measures help personnel to minimize loss or theft of information and disruption of services, including the ability to use information gained during the incident to better prepare for handling future incidents and to provide stronger protection for systems and data.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.040</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this policy and procedural manual shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.050</num>
          <heading>Interpretation</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to the Information Technology activities subject to this ordinance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of this ordinance, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court may use tribal law, federal law, or the State law for guidance.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.070</num>
          <heading>Relation to Other Laws</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Applicable Law.</heading>
            <text>Unless affected or displaced by this ordinance, principles of law and equity common law of the Tribe and tribal customs and traditions are applicable, and the general principles of law of any other Tribe or any other state may be used as a guide to supplement and interpret this ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Conflicts with Other Laws.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Tribal Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that this ordinance may conflict with tribal laws or ordinances which have been enacted to comply with statutes or regulations of any agency of the United States, such tribal laws or ordinances shall govern over the provisions of this Code if it has specific applicability, and it is clearly in conflict with the provisions of this Code.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>State Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that the laws of any state may be applicable to the subject matter of this ordinance, such laws shall be read to be advisory and not directly binding and shall not govern the relations of the parties.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.080</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision, or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.1.090</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances</heading>
          <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.2</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.2.010</num>
          <heading>General Definitions</heading>
          <text>Any term not defined in <cite path="§ITP.1.2.010">this section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Agent"</strong> shall mean a person who is authorized to act on behalf of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians with respect to a specific transaction or transactions. For the purposes of this ordinance, agent shall include all individuals elected or appointed to serve on a board, committee, or commission of the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Employee"</strong> shall mean any individual who is employed by the Tribe and is subject to the direction and control of the Tribe with respect to the material details of the work performed, or who has the status of an employee under the usual common law rules applicable to determining the employer-employee relationship. For the purposes of this ordinance, employee shall include individuals employed by a tribal entity or Tribally Chartered corporation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Network or Information Technology (IT)"</strong> shall encompass desktop computers, laptops, network resources, internet, intranet, email, world wide web, telephone systems, social media, etc.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Officer" </strong>shall mean a person elected or appointed to serve on a board, committee, or commission of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Personal electronic devices" </strong>shall include, but shall not be limited to, employee-owned desktop, laptop, tablet, handheld or worn computing devices, whether wired or wireless, USB drives, cameras and smartphones/cellular telephones.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"Reservation or Reservation Lands"</strong> shall mean those lands located within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Entity"</strong> shall mean a corporation or other organization which is wholly owned by the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and is operated for governmental or commercial purposes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> shall mean the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, and includes all departments, divisions, business units, and other subdivisions of the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Court"</strong> shall mean the court of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong> shall mean the Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.3</num>
        <heading>Information Security</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.010</num>
          <heading>Responsibilities</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Governing Board hall oversee the Tribe's efforts to develop, implement, and maintain an effective Information Security Program. The Tribal Governing Board Counsel shall be responsible for approving this policy and the written report on the effectiveness of the Tribe's Information Security Program on an annual basis.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribe's IT Department shall assist with the enforcement and adherence to the standards and guidelines established within this policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Tribe's IT Department shall provide direction and control for information security at the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall exercise due diligence in selecting its service providers and require its service providers by contract to implement security measures that safeguard Tribal information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Employees shall know and understand their duties with respect to the Information Security Policy and comply with the terms of this policy.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Security Objectives.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall meet its business objectives by implementing business systems with due consideration of information technology (IT) related risks to the Tribe, business and trading partners, technology service providers, and customers. The Tribe shall meet this goal by striving to accomplish the following objectives:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Availability, integrity and confidentiality of data or systems</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Accountability and assurance of processes and controls</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <heading>Security Process.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall implement an ongoing security process and shall assign clear and appropriate roles and responsibilities to the Tribal Governing Board, management, and employees. The process shall be designed to identify, measure, manage and control the risks to system and data availability, integrity, and confidentiality, and ensure accountability for system actions.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.020</num>
          <heading>Risk Assessment</heading>
          <text>Information security risk assessment is the process to identify and understand risks to the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information and information systems. The Tribe shall maintain an ongoing information security risk assessment program that effectively involves three phases:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Information gathering.</heading>
            <text>Gather data regarding the information and technology assets of the Tribe, threats to those assets, vulnerabilities, existing security controls and processes, and the current security standards and requirements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Analysis.</heading>
            <text>Analyze the probability and impact associated with the known threats and vulnerabilities to its assets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Prioritize responses.</heading>
            <text>Rank the risks present due to threats and vulnerabilities to determine the appropriate level of training, controls, and testing necessary for effective mitigation.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.030</num>
          <heading>Strategy</heading>
          <text>The Tribe strives to mitigate risks while complying with legal, statutory, contractual, and internally developed requirements. In building this strategy, the Tribe shall define its control objectives and establish an implementation plan. The security strategy shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Cost comparisons of different strategic approaches appropriate to the Tribe's environment and complexity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Layered controls that establish multiple control points between threats and Tribe assets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Educating officers and employees in implementing the information security program.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.040</num>
          <heading>Controls Implementation</heading>
          <text>The following security controls shall be implemented as available:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Access rights admin.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall have an effective process to administer access to system resources. The Tribe shall strive to identify and restrict access to any system resource to the minimum required for work to be performed. The process shall include the following controls:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Assign end-users and system resources only the access required to perform their required functions;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Update access rights based on personnel or system changes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Periodically review users' access rights based on the risk to the application or system; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Design appropriate acceptable-use and end-user policies.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Authentication.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall use effective authentication methods appropriate to the level of risk by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Selecting authentication mechanisms based on the risk associated with a particular application or service;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Considering whether multiple forms of authentication are appropriate for each application, considering that multi-forms authentication is increasingly necessary for many forms of electronic communication and electronic payment activities; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Encrypting the transmission and storage of authenticators (e.g., passwords, PINs).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>Network access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure access to their computer networks through multiple layers of access controls to protect against unauthorized access. Access control measures shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Group network servers, applications, data, and users into security domains;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Require use of unique user IDs and strong passwords;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Establishing appropriate access requirements within and between each security domain; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Implementing appropriate controls to meet those access requirements consistently</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <heading>Operating System access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure access to the operating systems of all system components by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Securing access to system utilities;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Restricting and monitoring privileged access;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Logging and monitoring user or program access to sensitive resources;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Updating the operating systems with security patches; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Securing the devices that can access the operating system through physical and logical means</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <heading>Application access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall control access to applications by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Using authentication and authorization controls appropriate for the risk of the application;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Monitoring access rights to ensure they are the minimum required for the user's current business needs;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Using time of day limitations on access as appropriate; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Logging access and security events</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>Remote access.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall secure remote access to and from their systems by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Controlling access through management approvals;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Implementing controls over configuration to disallow potential malicious use;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Monitoring remote access;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Securing remote access devices; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Using strong authentication and encryption to secure communications.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <heading>Physical Security.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall implement appropriate preventative and detective controls to protect against the risk to physical security.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <heading>Encryption.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall employ encryption to mitigate the risk of disclosure or alteration of sensitive information and storage transit. Encryption implementations shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Encryption strength sufficient to protect the information while in transit between unsecure systems;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Effective encryption key management practices; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Appropriate protection of the encrypted communication's endpoints.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>USB storage devices shall not be authorized for general use. If a USB storage device is needed to store sensitive or confidential information, then something like "bit locker" with encryption that requires a username and password shall be used.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <heading>Malicious code.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall protect against the risk of malicious code by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Using anti-virus products on clients and servers;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Using an appropriate blocking strategy on the network perimeter;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Filtering input to applications; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Educating staff in appropriate computing policies and procedures</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <heading>Systems development, acquisition, and maintenance.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall ensure that systems are developed, acquired, and maintained with appropriate security controls. These steps shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Defining security requirements before developing or acquiring new systems;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Incorporating recognized standards in developing security requirements;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Incorporating appropriate security controls, audit trails, and logs for data entry and data processing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Implementing an effective change control process;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Hardening systems before deployment;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Establishing an effective patch process for new security vulnerabilities; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Overseeing vendors to protect the integrity and confidentiality of application source code.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <heading>Personnel security.</heading>
            <text>The Employee Handbook and Human Resources policies shall discuss risk mitigation posed by internal users</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <heading>Virtualization.</heading>
            <text>The Virtual environment and the Virtualization of servers shall be the responsibility of the  IT Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <heading>Electronic and paper-based media handling.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall control and protect access to paper, film, and computer-based media to avoid loss or damage. The Tribe shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Establish and ensure compliance with policies for handling and storing information;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Ensure safe and secure disposal of sensitive media and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Secure media in transit or transmission to third parties.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Employees are instructed to save data to "shared drives" or other network drives for security and backup purposes.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <heading>Logging and data collection.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall take reasonable steps to ensure that sufficient data is collected from secure log files to identify and respond to security incidents and to monitor and enforce policy compliance. The Tribe shall have appropriate logging controls to ensure that security personnel can review and analyze log data to identify unauthorized access attempts and security violations, provide support for personnel actions, and aid in reconstructing comprised systems.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(o)</num>
            <heading>Service provider oversight.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall review security responsibilities for outsourced operations through</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Appropriate due diligence in service provider research and selection;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Contractual assurances regarding security responsibilities, controls, and reporting;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Nondisclosure agreements regarding the Tribe's systems and data; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Third-party review of the service provider's security through appropriate audits and tests.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(p)</num>
            <heading>Intrusion detection and response.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall strive to detect and respond to an information system intrusion commensurate with risk. Risk mitigation practices shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Preparation.</heading>
              <text>Analysis of data flows, decisions on the nature and scope of monitoring, consideration of legal factors, appropriate procedures governing detection and response; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Response to an intrusion.</heading>
              <text>Containment and restoration of systems and appropriate reporting.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(q)</num>
            <heading>Business continuity considerations.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall develop a plan that includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Identification and training of personnel with key security roles during continuity plan implementation; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Security needs for back-up sites and alternate communications.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(r)</num>
            <heading>Insurance.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall evaluate the extent and availability of coverage in relation to the specific risks they are seeking to mitigate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(s)</num>
            <heading>Equipment disposal/destruction.</heading>
            <text>When equipment is retired from use, the hard drive shall be removed and stored or deleted and cleaned with software of a Department of Defense grade. Other equipment such as copiers, printers, and multi-function machines Shall have memory or other data storage devices deleted or destroyed. Equipment shall then be recycled, disposed of, or donated with no software or data.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.050</num>
          <heading>Security testing</heading>
          <text>The Tribe shall gain assurance of the adequacy of their risk mitigation strategy and implementation by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Basing their testing plan, test selection, and test frequency on the risk posed by potentially non-functioning controls;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Establishing controls to mitigate the risks posed to systems from testing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Using test results to evaluate whether security objectives are met.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.060</num>
          <heading>Monitoring and updating</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall continuously gather and analyze information regarding new threats and vulnerabilities, actual and potential attacks on the Tribe or others, and the effectiveness of the existing security controls.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The information in par. (a) shall be used to update the risk assessment, strategy, and implemented controls.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>To complete the goals of (a) and (b) the Tribe shall utilize malware, antivirus, and other security programs.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.070</num>
          <heading>Reporting</heading>
          <text>Employees that become aware of any system misuse; potential threat, intrusion, or unexplained occurrence; or violations of this IT policy, shall inform a member of the IT Department immediately.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.3.080</num>
          <heading>Incident response program</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Incident Response Team.</heading>
            <text>The Tribe shall establish an Incident Response Team that is available for anyone who discovers or suspects that an incident has occurred. One or more team members are responsible for handling the incident, analyzing the incident data, determining the impact of the incident, and acting appropriately to limit the damage and restore normal services.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The primary Incident Response Team shall consist of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>IT Director</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>IT Department personnel</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>More severe or extensive incidents can include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Office of Attorney General</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Tribal Law Enforcement</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Compliance/Audit Officer</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>All Tribal employees shall be aware of the possibility of system or security incidents.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Physical building incidents shall be directed to the Tribe's security officer.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Computer security related incidents shall be directed to the IT or Operations Departments.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Individuals shall work with the response team and executive management to execute an incident response.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Phases of Incident Response</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Preparation.</heading>
              <text>This initial phase involves establishing and training a response team and acquiring the necessary tools and resources. During preparation, the Tribe shall attempt to limit the number of incidents that will occur by selecting and implementing a set of controls based on the results of risk assessments. Other preparation items include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Risk Assessment</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>Host Security</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <text>Network Security</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <text>Malware Prevention</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>User Awareness and Training</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>System Hardening Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>System Access Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>Facilities Security Guidelines</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>Insurance Policies</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>Detection and analysis.</heading>
              <text>The process of monitoring and awareness. Training creates an awareness of what constitutes an incident and who to contact when it occurs. Log monitoring, with knowledge of baseline system activities, will create trigger points. Once detected, the Tribe may mitigate the impact of the incident by containing it and ultimately recovering from it.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <heading>Containment, eradication, and recovery.</heading>
              <text>The response to the Incident.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <heading>Post incident activity.</heading>
              <text>Once the incident is over, an overall assessment report of the incident shall be developed detailing the cause of the incident, steps to prevent future incidents, and steps to mitigate consequences of future incidents.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>
                <strong>Unauthorized access to tribal information procedures</strong>
              </text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <heading>Audit.</heading>
              <text>The Tribe shall utilize both internal and external audit procedures to provide independent assessments that evaluate the Tribe's:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Quality of internal controls associated with the acquisition, development, implementation, and operational use of information technology.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Exposure to risks throughout the Tribe and its service provider(s) in the areas of user and data center operations, client/server architecture, local and wide area networks, telecommunications, information security, electronic data interchange, systems development, and contingency planning, including risk management and mitigation techniques implemented by the Tribe; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Compliance with this and other related policies, procedures and processes concerning information technology related risks.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.4</num>
        <heading>Acceptable Use</heading>
        <text>Network access is deemed to be a business tool providing a source of information with the potential for benefiting all areas of the tribe and enhancing customer service, customer retention, and growth. The Information Technology department shall approve Network access as deemed appropriate and shall determine what components of the Network shall be available (email, internet, World Wide Web, etc.). All employees accessing the Network on tribal equipment, on tribal premises, or on a tribal Internet access account shall become proficient in its capabilities, practice proper network etiquette, and agree to the conditions and requirements of this agreement.</text>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.010</num>
          <heading>General principles</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Network, internet, and email privileges provided by the Tribe, shall be considered tribal resources, and shall be used for tribal business purposes. Network and Internet usage shall not be private. Usage shall be monitored for unusual or unacceptable activity and can be monitored at any time for any reason.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Internet use includes, but is not limited to:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>email received and sent,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>websites visited,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>social media posts,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>uploads, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>downloads</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall own the Network, messaging systems, and the information transmitted and stored within it.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Employees shall have no expectation of privacy or confidentiality in any of their emails or network files. Employee email, web history and phone usage may be monitored for policy, security, network and/or tribal management reasons from time to time and is subject to inspection at any time.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Correspondence, internal or external, via email, or instant messaging (IM) shall not be private. Email shall not be guaranteed protection from other employees or from others outside the tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The distribution of any information through the Network, computer-based services, or email shall be subject to the scrutiny of tribal management and its auditors. The Tribe reserves the right to determine the suitability of this information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Employees shall be restricted in their usage of employee-owned personal electronic devices and media storage devices on the Tribal Network.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Employees utilizing web sites and social media sites at work for personal use shall do so during break and lunch times in a professional manner as to not interfere with their job duties and responsibilities. Excessive use, as deemed by their supervisor and/or management, shall result in loss of privilege for the user and possibly other disciplinary action as outlined in this agreement.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.020</num>
          <heading>Conditions of use</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Users shall</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Comply with all current tribal policies</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Lock or log off computers when leaving them unattended for any length of time</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Use unique user IDs and strong passwords as indicated by tribal policy and maintain password credentials in a confidential manner</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Contact the IT and Department manager immediately upon discovering suspicious activity on the Network, Including a Tribal workstation, network resource, or email</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Immediately notify IT and management if a business-related mobile device is lost, stolen, exchanged, unusable, or no longer used</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>The user shall be required to maintain and safeguard the equipment issued and return it to the Tribe if they leave the employment position from which it was issued. This includes when an employee transfers to a new department. If the employee is leaving the employment of the Tribe, they shall return all equipment before they receive their last paycheck.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Users shall not</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Knowingly visit Internet sites that contain illegal, obscene, hateful, or other objectionable materials</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Knowingly access ads or other solicitations commonly seen in the margins of reputable website pages or that popup while on a site</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Knowingly open an attachment or access a link provided in an unsolicited, unfamiliar email. The IT Department shall review any suspicious email</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Send non-encrypted emails containing sensitive customer information.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Send or receive any material, whether by IM, email, memoranda, or oral conversation, which is obscene, defamatory, harassing, intimidating, offensive, illegal, discriminatory, or which is intended to annoy, harass, or intimidate another person.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Solicit non-tribal business for personal gain or profit</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Download any software or electronic files to a tribal workstation or the Network unless authorized by the IT department</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Represent personal opinions as those of the tribe or purport to represent the tribe when not authorized to do so.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>Upload, download, or otherwise transmit software or any copyrighted materials in violation of its copyright or license whether it belongs to parties outside of the tribal, or the tribe itself</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>Reveal or publicize confidential or proprietary information which includes, but is not limited to: financial information, customer information, marketing strategies and plans, databases and any information contained therein, customer lists, computer software source codes, computer/network access codes, passwords/login information and business relationships.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(11)</num>
              <text>Intentionally interfere with the normal operation of the Network, including the propagation of computer viruses and sustained high volume network traffic, which substantially hinders others in their use of the network.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(12)</num>
              <text>Examine, change, or use another person's username, password, files, and output, for which they do not have explicit authorization.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(13)</num>
              <text>Perform any other uses identified by the tribe as inappropriate.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(14)</num>
              <text>Use tribal equipment or other resources for any purpose other than that authorized by tribal management and IT department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(15)</num>
              <text>Use tribal email accounts (xxxxx@lco-nsn.gov) to open or maintain personal Internet accounts, such as social media, websites, blogs, etc.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(16)</num>
              <text>Use film cameras, digital cameras, digital camcorders, and personal devices with camera and/or video capabilities (i.e., a cellular phone including a camera capable of capturing and transmitting still or full motion images) in any way that violates Tribal policies, including illicit and illegal use. Photos showing tribal security measures, secure areas such as vaults, information on computer screens or any Network resources are strictly prohibited.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(17)</num>
              <text>And are prohibited from connecting personal electronic devices or media, including but not limited to smartphones, tablets, CD/DVD burners, special keyboards, mice, external hard drives, and USB "jump" drives, to Tribal workstations or Network resources; even for the purpose of charging the device unless authorized by the department manager and the IT department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(18)</num>
              <text>And are prohibited from using portable media storage devices, including but not limited to USB drives and other external drives, to duplicate and/or distribute Tribal information, including confidential information copyrighted materials, music, video, movies, and software unless authorized by the department manager and the IT Department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(19)</num>
              <text>Load a bootable, alternate operating system on any Tribal owned computer from any employee-owned source or media, including CD/DVD discs or USB devices ("jump" drives), without prior permission of the department manager and IT Department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(20)</num>
              <text>Connect any employee-owned electronic device whether desktop, laptop, tablet, handheld, wearable or media storage device, through a wired connection to Tribal provided network or Internet access without the prior permission of the department manager and IT Department. Wireless internet access is provided at the main lobby and Peter Larson room for guest and employees to use with personal devices.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.030</num>
          <heading>Personal posts</heading>
          <text>The Tribe recognizes that employees may post personal information on the Internet through personal websites, social media, blogs and/or uploading content to websites and the like. The Tribe respects our employee's interest in participating in these forms of personal expression on their own time. Employees should be aware; however, that problems can arise when personal postings identify or appear to be associated with the Tribe, or when a personal posting is used in ways that violate the Tribe's rights or the rights of other employees.</text>
          <text>Each employee is legally responsible for content they post on the Internet, whether on a social network, website or otherwise. You can be held personally liable for defaming others, revealing trade secrets, confidential information or proprietary information, etc. Tribal policies apply to what you post on the Internet. For example, you may not use personal postings to harass or threaten other employees or reveal confidential tribal information. Embarrassing or unkind comments about tribal employees or members, customers, or competitors are also inappropriate. Posting anonymously or under a pseudonym, does not protect your real identity; it can be discovered relatively easily.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.4.040</num>
          <heading>Violations</heading>
          <text>Users who violate any of the guidelines set in this agreement may be subject to disciplinary action including written warnings, revocation of access privileges, and termination. Unacceptable use of personal electronic devices will result in the immediate confiscation of the involved device(s) or media as appropriate. Depending upon the nature and severity of the violation, the confiscated device(s) or media may be held as evidence indefinitely. The Tribe also retains the right to perform personal property searches in relation to any guideline violation and report any illegal violations to the appropriate authorities.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>ITP.1.5</num>
        <heading>Backup and Recovery</heading>
        <section>
          <num>ITP.1.5.010</num>
          <heading>Backup and Recovery</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>All tribal critical data that is stored locally on the domains file server shall be backed up daily and kept off site in the cloud.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Backups shall be done on all critical information that is stored on the shared network.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The backup shall be set up to run automatically after normal working hours and a log of the success shall be kept.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>These backups shall be based on an incremental or differential backup methodology</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Backup shall be performed in such a way that information can be restored from a time frame requested up to ninety (90) days incrementally from the past.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Information shall be restored monthly at the discretion of the IT department to ensure backups are functioning properly and that the information shall be available if needed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Department Directors shall request IT to restore information from a backup by email or memo.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Generally, the requested information shall be available to the department within twenty-four (24) hours of the request.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If the data recovery is needed do to a minor or major system failure it may take longer to restore depending on the level of failure.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The servers or equipment that are performing the backups shall be in a locked and restricted location. These servers or equipment shall also be on Uninterruptible Power Supply (UPS) to help mitigate problems resulting from power fluctuations or short power outages.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <annotation app="2023-05-10" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-42" eff="2023-05-10" path="" type="History"/>
  </container>
  <xi:include href="./PAP.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="./attachments/index.xml"/>
</document>
