<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2022-123" codify:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2022-123</num>
  <heading>Revision of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippwa Indians Gaming Enterprises Banishment Policy PAP.9.13.030</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2022-12-12</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2022-123.pdf">Council Resolution No. 2022-123</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2022-12-12</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. §5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, § 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, Section 1(n) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite> shall "regulate, by the enactment of ordinances, the conduct of business within the territory of the band" and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, Section 1(h)</cite> "to engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board duly enacted <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.9.13.030">PAP.9.13.030</cite> and now wishes to amend such section as attached.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby amends <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.9.13.030">PAP.9.13.030</cite> as attached.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <codify:replace path="PAP.9.13.030" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|PAP.9.13.030">
    <section>
      <num>PAP.9.13.030</num>
      <heading>Banishment Policy</heading>
      <text>It is the responsibility of the Casino to make our best effort to keep our patrons and team members safe from harm or harassment. While Banishment is generally applied to Guests, at times Team Members may be banished for a fixed time, suspended, and/or leading up to termination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Banishment authority is provided to the Manager on Duty at the time of the incident of violation in accordance with this policy. If there is a challenge to this decision by the patron or Team Member, all available evidence of the incident is to be reviewed by a member of Executive Management team and their decision will be a final disposition of the matter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criteria for Banishment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text><u>Panhandling</u>. Unwarranted or unwelcome requests for borrowing or begging for money, items or services from another person for any reason is considered a form of harassment and will not be permitted on casino property at any time. The perpetrator will be given verbal &amp; written notification (documented and retained on file by patron name by the Manager on Duty) of the offense and informed that further incidents carry ban consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense,    Verbal Warning  90-day ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense,    Written Warning     1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense,    Final Written       3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>*Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text><u>Underage Drinking</u>. Any person under 21 years of age observed consuming alcohol on the premises shall be banned until they are the legal minimum age of 21. Such a person shall be informed that if a 2nd offense occurs, management will contact law enforcement immediately, which may result in them being detained for the local authorities to do a sobriety test. Such a person shall also be notified that a 3rd offense shall result in a permanent ban from all Casino properties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, banned from the bar and casino until minimum drinking age of 21.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense,    3-year ban*</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3<sup>rd</sup> offense,     permanent ban</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text><u>Intoxication</u>. All patrons that are visibly intoxicated will not be allowed to consume alcohol or gamble. If the intoxicated patron is disruptive, behaving offensively or is projecting a negative image, that patron will be asked to leave immediately. When an intoxicated patron has been asked to leave the premises, Security and the Manager on Duty will assist the patron in acquiring alternative transportation to their destination, whether it is finding a friend or relative the patron came with, calling someone for this person, or calling a cab if the patron has cab fare. When all other attempts fail, local law enforcement may need to be called. The perpetrator of the offense will be given a verbal &amp; written notification and be informed that further incidents carry ban consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties. Any further incidents shall result in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     90-day ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text><u>Verbal Confrontation or Threats</u>. Verbal confrontations or threats to other patrons or team members are taken very seriously. These are seen as offensive to other patrons, damaging to the Lac Courte Oreilles Band's public image and detrimental to the friendly and hospitable environment management desires to create for our guests. The perpetrator will be sent a written letter (documented and retained on file by patron name by the Manager on Duty) with date of incident, time of banishment period and a warning that future incidents carry consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     90-day ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text><u>Physical Confrontations</u>. In any incidents involving a physical confrontation with patrons or team members, local law enforcement departments will be contacted, and the patrons involved will immediately be removed from the premises by Security, or local law enforcement Department, when necessary, and placed on the appropriate ban. If the Executive Team determines the severity is great enough, the individual(s) involved could face a permanent ban.  When required, an investigation will be done by the Manager on Duty to determine the aggressor of the altercation. In all cases, the initial aggressor will be immediately banned. Through the investigation, if it is determined that the victim has engaged beyond defending themselves or third parties engage as aggressors, multiple patrons are subject to banishment. The perpetrator(s) will be sent a written letter &amp; verbal notification (documented and retained on file by patron name by the Manager on Duty) of the offense and informed that further incidents carry ban consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    2-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>*Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text><u>Controlled Substances</u>. Law enforcement will be called when Casino management personnel suspect a patron to be in possession of, using, or trafficking controlled substances. The perpetrator shall be banned up to, and including, a permanent ban from all Casino properties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    3-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  5-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text><u>Suspicious Activity</u>.  Any person determined by Casino Management to be displaying suspicious activity related to the following situations will be subject to a ban up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties:  Situations and circumstances include, but are not limited to, drug related activity, harassment, or any other reason to believe the safety and security of operations could be jeopardized:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     90-day ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>*Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text><u>Damage to Property</u>. If damage to property assets occurs, the perpetrator(s) will be sent a letter specifying the damages, the amount of damages and time of banishment along with a warning of future consequences. The perpetrator shall be banned until the damages are paid in full. This includes any charges necessary for extra cleaning or repair to the facility. Patrons are subject to a ban from all Casino properties.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Verbal Warning     90-day ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense, Written Warning    1-year ban</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense, Final Written  3-year up to permanent ban*</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text><u>Fraud, Theft or Cheating</u>. Any person determined by Casino management to have committed theft, fraud or collusion in any game of chance or promotional activity will be permanently banned from all Casino properties. A letter will be sent informing them of the date of the permanent ban. All documentation and evidence will be forwarded to the LCO Gaming Commission and to State of Wisconsin Department of Regulatory Compliance.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense, Final Written  Permanent ban and reimbursement made</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text><u>Unclaimed Funds/Property</u>. Any person determined by the Executive Management Team to have claimed another person's property, (monetary or nonmonetary), including property and goods of the Gaming Enterprises, will be subject to consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties once an investigation has been completed. Any person found to have claimed another person's property, including property and goods of the Gaming Enterprises, will also be required to re-pay the amount and/or return property taken. No person will be allowed off the ban list until full reimbursement has been satisfied and the ban has been served.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense,    1-year ban and reimbursement made</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense,    2-year ban and reimbursement made</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense,    3-year up to permanent ban and reimbursement made*</text>
            <text>* Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Quicket Tickets/ Unattended Credits. When a patron reports a quicket ticket cashed out or credits of their machine missing, any person determined by Casino Management to have claimed that ticket will be subject to consequences up to and including a permanent ban from all Casino properties once an investigation has been completed. Any person found to have claimed the missing ticket will also be required to re-pay the amount of the ticket. No person will be allowed off the ban list until full reimbursement has been satisfied and the ban has been served.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>1st offense,    1-year ban and reimbursement made</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>2nd offense,    2-year ban and reimbursement made</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>3rd offense,    3-year ban and reimbursement made*</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <text>*Upon completion of the 3-year ban, the offender must request a meeting with the Executive Staff to discuss possible reinstatement.</text>
    </section>
  </codify:replace>
  <codify:replace path="PAP.9.13.040" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|PAP.9.13.040">
    <section>
      <num>PAP.9.13.040</num>
      <heading>Banishment Procedures</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The patron should be asked if the ID bears their current residential address. If not, it shall be requested from them. If the patron refuses to cooperate with the request for current physical address the ban memo will be issued internally without it. If they should return to the property, Security will be notified immediately to provide them a copy of the ban memo and escort them off the property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A ban memo will be distributed to Security, Surveillance, Manager on Duty. Lodge, Marketing and Grindstone Creek Casino informing each business area of the patron’s name, Manager on Duty serving the notice and the start and end dates of the ban.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A ban list shall be maintained (and distributed periodically as it is updated) for reference by all aforementioned departments to determine who is permitted on property at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The ban notification shall include instructions requiring the patron to call the Casino and speak to the Manager on Duty who shall inform them of the consequence of another incident of the infraction they were banned for. Patrons who invoke the self-exclusion process  are not required to notify the Manager on Duty of their expected return to the property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The perpetrator will be sent a written letter with a date of incident, time of banishment period and a warning that future incidents carry consequences up to and including a permanent ban.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>All violations of this ban will be combined and run concurrently.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>All Tribal Governing Board members will receive notification of any individual(s) placed on the ban list.  Notification to the Tribal Governing Board members will include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>a brief description of the reason for the ban;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>a ban memo;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>the update ban list; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>a photo of the individual(s) recently placed on the ban list, when available.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </codify:replace>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>7</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>12<sup>th</sup> day of December, 2022</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>5</u></strong> members, <strong><u>1</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
