<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-128">
  <num>2023-128</num>
  <heading>Temporary Emergency Curfew for All Minors Ages 15 Years and Younger to Support Community Safety</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-10-16</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-128.pdf">Res. No. 2023-128</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-10-16</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. ยง5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, ยง 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians" to further protect the health and safety of the residents of the Reservation pursuant to Article Vยง1(s); and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>as a result of recent violence, theft, gang activity, and damage to tribal and private property within the reservation boundaries, the Tribal Governing Board is taking necessary actions to protect the community and our members; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board, in response to requests for assistance from tribal members and government entities, is establishing a TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW within the reservation to protect our community; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board hereby directs all tribal law enforcement agencies to enforce the TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW immediately; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board will review the TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW in 60 days to assess its efficacy.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby declares a TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW for any unaccompanied minors fifteen (15) years of age and younger within the boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation from 10:00 P.M. every evening until 7:00 A.M. the following morning Monday through Sunday, including weekends and holidays. This Emergency Curfew directs all minor children 15 years or younger, and not accompanied or supervised by a responsible adult, to remain indoors within their dwellings.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that this TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW will take effect on October 16, 2023, and remain in effect for 60 days and shall expire without notice on December 15, 2023.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that all Lac Courte Oreilles Law enforcement agencies are directed to detain any children found in violation of this TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW and return them to the dwelling of a relative or responsible adult.  Citations shall be issued to the parent or legal guardian for any child that violates this TEMPORARY EMERGENCY CURFEW; all parents and legal guardians will have a right to appear in the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court to contest the citation and monetary forfeiture resulting from the curfew violations.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>6</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>16<sup>th</sup> day of October 2023</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>6</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>William Trepanier, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
