<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-45">
  <num>2023-45</num>
  <heading>Repeal of Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law General Conduct GNC.4.6</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-05-10</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-45.pdf">Res. No. 2023-45</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-05-10</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. ยง5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, ยง 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V">Article V</cite>, including but not limited to, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(q)">Section 1(q)</cite> and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">(s)</cite> of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers he Tribal Governing Board to: "establish a tribal court for the purposes of enforcing tribal ordinance" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(q)">Article V, Section 1 (q)</cite> and "to promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin and providing for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by and establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">Article V, Section 1(s)</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board prioritizes protecting all  trails and roadways within the boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby repeals <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="GNC.4.6">GNC.4.6</cite>. OPERATION OF ALL-TERRAIN VEHICLES as the Tribal Governing Board has formally adopted by Resolution 2022-103 <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="VEH.4">Chapter VEH.4</cite> ALL-TERRAIN VEHICLES AND UTILITY TASK VEHICLES on October 24, 2022, as an updated more current code than the antiquated 2012 <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="GNC.4.6">GNC.4.6</cite> version.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom 6 being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this 10th day of May 2023, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of 5 members, 0 against, 0 abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:repeal doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="GNC.4.6" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|GNC.4.6.010"/>
</document>
