<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-30" codify:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2023-30</num>
  <heading>Chapter MCC.2 Meeting Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Code of Law</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-03-27</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-30.pdf">Res. No. 2023-30</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-03-27</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. §5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, § 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a Tribal Governing Board, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the Reservation" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(m)">Article V,§1(m)</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board's meeting shall follow set rules and procedures for regular, special, and general membership meetings.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby approves the attached <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="MCC.2">Chapter MCC.2</cite> Meeting Ordinance and mandates its incorporation to the digitized Lac Courte Oreilles Law Library.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>5</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this __ day of <strong><u>27<sup>th</sup> day of March, 2023</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>4</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert path="MCC" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|MCC.2.1.010">
    <container>
      <num>MCC.2</num>
      <heading>Meeting Ordinance OF THE LAC COURTE OREILLES BAND OF LAKE SUPERIOR CHIPPEWA INDIANS</heading>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians to provide for the decent, safe and sanitary dwellings for the members of the Tribe which predates its Treaties of 1825, 1826, 1837, 1842, 1847 and 1854 with the United States Government. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a Tribal Governing Board, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation." (<cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, § 1(l)</cite>). Pursuant to this inherent sovereign authority, the Tribal Governing Board hereby enacts  this ordinance.</text>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.1</num>
        <heading>General Provisions</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.010</num>
          <heading>Title.</heading>
          <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Meeting Ordinance of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.020</num>
          <heading>Authority.</heading>
          <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V">Article V, §</cite>§ 1(l) and (m) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter and regulate any association or group, including a Tribal Governing Board, for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, § 1 (l)</cite>; and "delegate to subordinate boards, officers, committees or cooperative associations which are open to all members of the Band any of the foregoing powers, reserving the right to review any action taken by virtue of such delegated powers" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(m)">Article V, § 1(m)</cite>.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.030</num>
          <heading>Purpose.</heading>
          <text>It is the purpose of this ordinance to define and prescribe the schedule and procedures for the regular, special, and general membership meetings of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.040</num>
          <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this ordinance shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.050</num>
          <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
          <text>The provisions of this ordinance:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted and applied as minimum requirements applicable to the Homeless Shelter activities subject to this ordinance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other tribal power or authority.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Shall be interpreted to be in accordance with tribal customary law. Whenever there is uncertainty or a question as to the interpretation of certain provisions of this ordinance, tribal law and custom shall be controlling, and where appropriate, may be based on the written or oral testimony of a qualified tribal elder, tribal historian, or tribal representative. If the traditions and customs of the Tribe are inconclusive in any matter, the Court may use tribal law, federal law, or the State law for guidance.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.060</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability.</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision, or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this ordinance.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.070</num>
          <heading>Relation to Other Laws.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>Applicable Law.</heading>
            <text>Unless affected or displaced by this ordinance, principles of law and equity in the common law of the Tribe and tribal customs and traditions are applicable, and the general principles of law of any other Tribe or any other state may be used as a guide to supplement and interpret this ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Conflicts with Other Laws.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <heading>Tribal Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that this ordinance may conflict with tribal laws or ordinances which have been enacted to comply with statutes or regulations of any agency of the United States, such tribal laws or ordinances shall govern over the provisions of this Code if it has specific applicability and it is clearly in conflict with the provisions of this Code.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <heading>State Law.</heading>
              <text>To the extent that the laws of any state may be applicable to the subject matter of this ordinance, such laws shall be read to be advisory and not directly binding and shall not govern the relations of the parties.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.080</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Tribal Ordinances.</heading>
          <text>All ordinances and resolutions inconsistent with this ordinance are hereby repealed. To the extent that this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in any other tribal law, code, ordinance or regulation, the provisions of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.1.090</num>
          <heading>Open Meetings.</heading>
          <text>All Board meetings shall be open to all Tribal Members as defined in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(m)">MCC.2.2.010(m)</cite> with the exception of Executive Sessions as defined in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(e)">MCC.2.2.010(e)</cite>.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.2</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.2.010</num>
          <heading>General Definitions.</heading>
          <text>Any term not defined in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010">this Section</cite> shall be given its ordinary meaning. The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows, except where the context indicates otherwise:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text><strong>"Absolute Majority Vote"</strong> means a vote at a Regular or Special Meeting of either:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>three (3) Board Members voting in agreement when only four (4) or five (5) voting Board Members (including Tribal Chairman) are present; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>four (4) Board Members voting in agreement when only six (6) or seven (7) voting Board Members (including Tribal Chairman) are present and voting.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>Any Board Member who abstains shall not be considered as casting a vote.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>The Lac Courte Oreille Tribal Chairman shall not vote except to break a tie vote.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><strong>"Abstention" </strong>means the decision by a Board Member to not vote on a motion or resolution due to the potential for personal gain or loss or other personal involvement in the subject matter, the potential for personal gain or loss or other personal involvement of an immediate family member or other reason such absence when an issue was previously discussed. Any Board Member who decides to abstain from a vote shall state the reason for their abstention to the Board on the record.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text><strong>"Board" </strong>means the Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Court Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text><strong>"Constitution and Bylaws" </strong>refers to the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreille Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text><strong>"Executive Session" </strong>means a Board Meeting or part of a Board Meeting that is closed to non-Board Members. Non-Board Members shall neither attend nor participate in these meetings, except by invitation of the Board. Invitation by the Board may be given by consensus of the Board.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text><strong>"General Membership Meeting" </strong>means a meeting of the Board held in the manner prescribed by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="MCC.2.4">Subchapter MCC.2.4</cite> of this ordinance where a quorum of the Board, as defined by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(h)">MCC.2.2.010(h)</cite>, is present.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text><strong>"Other Business" </strong>means all matters not identified by the pre-meeting agenda in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.3.040">MCC.2.3.040</cite> or by waiver of the notice required by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.3.030">MCC.2.3.030</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text><strong>"Quorum" </strong>means the presence of four (4) Members of the Board at a Regular or Special meeting. The Chairman's presence shall count toward a quorum.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><strong>"Regular Meeting" </strong>means a meeting of the Board held in the manner prescribed by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="MCC.2.3">Subchapter MCC.2.3</cite>, where a quorum of the Board is present.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text><strong>"Regular Order of Business" </strong>means the order in which matters come before the Board are taken up as prescribed by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.3.040">MCC.2.3.040</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text><strong>"Simple Majority Vote" </strong>means a majority vote of Board Members who are present and voting at a Regular or a Special Meeting where quorum requirements are met. Any Board Member who abstains shall not be considered as casting a vote. The Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Chairman shall not vote except to break a tie vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text><strong>"Special Meeting" </strong>means a meeting of the Board held in the manner prescribed by Title V of this ordinance where a quorum is present.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Members" </strong>means the membership of the Tribe as defined by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|II">Article II of the Constitution</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribe" </strong>means the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.3</num>
        <heading>Regular Meetings</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.010</num>
          <heading>Time of Regular Weekly Meetings.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall conduct regular weekly meetings to conduct tribal business every Monday, at 9:00 a.m. Should the circumstances so require, the Board shall have the authority to select an alternate time of a regular meeting on a meeting-by-meeting basis.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.020</num>
          <heading>Place of Regular Weekly Meetings.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall conduct the regular weekly meeting at the Lac Courte Oreille Tribal Government Center. The Board shall have the authority to select an alternative location for a regular weekly meeting on a meeting-by-meeting basis.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.030</num>
          <heading>Notice Required.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall give Members of the Board written notice of all regular meetings at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance. Written notice shall be posted at the Tribal Administration Building twenty-four (24) hours before the start of the regular meeting. The written notice shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Location of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Date and Time of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Agenda of the meeting; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The date and time the notice is posted.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.040</num>
          <heading>Regular Order of Business.</heading>
          <text>All matters coming before the Board and Tribal Members at a regular meeting shall be taken up pursuant to the following order of business:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Roll call;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Traditional passing of tobacco;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Approval and ratification of minutes from the immediately preceding meeting, both regular and special;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Reports of the Board's Officers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Old business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>New business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Other business, as defined in ____; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Adjournment</text>
            <text>The Board may address all matters not identified in the pre-meeting agenda as other business or by waiver of the notice required by <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.3.030">MCC.2.3.030</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.050</num>
          <heading>Majority Vote Required.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall conduct all business of the Tribe through the passage of motions and resolutions. The passage of motions and resolutions shall be by majority vote as defined in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(a)">MCC.2.2.010(a)</cite> and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(k)">(k)</cite>. An absolute majority vote is required for passage when the subject matter under consideration involves the tribal budget, land purchases, enrollment decisions, the Tribe's gaming compact, and agreements binding the Tribe for over five (5) years and/or in which the purchase price or value of goods exceeds $100,000.00. All other subject matters under consideration are allowed to pass by a simple majority vote. Meetings shall be conducted in accordance with the Constitution and Bylaws, and this ordinance.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.5.060</num>
          <heading>Removal of an Absentee Board Member.</heading>
          <text>The Board, by an affirmative vote of six (6) of its Members, may remove any Board Member for being absent from three (3) successive regularly scheduled meetings without an excuse acceptable to a majority of the Board Members in accordance with <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|7|(b)">Article III, Section 7(b) of the Constitution</cite>.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.070</num>
          <heading>Minutes Required.</heading>
          <text>The Secretary/Treasurer shall ensure that minutes are kept of all matters coming before the Board at a regular meeting.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.3.080</num>
          <heading>Approval of Previous Minutes Required.</heading>
          <text>At each regular meeting, the Board shall approve the minutes of the regular meeting. The Board shall approve the minutes of the previous meeting(s), regular or special. Prior to such approval, the minutes of the previous meetings may be corrected or modified so as to ensure their accuracy and correctness.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.4</num>
        <heading>General Membership Meeting</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.4.010</num>
          <heading>General Membership Meetings.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall conduct a general meeting at least one (1) time per year to report to the membership the state of the Tribe. The Board may, at its own discretion, have additional general meetings, but there shall be compliance with notice requirements pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.4.010">this section</cite>.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.4.020</num>
          <heading>Place of General Membership Meetings.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall have the authority to select a location for the general membership meeting on a meeting-by-meeting basis.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.4.030</num>
          <heading>Notice Required.</heading>
          <text>The Board shall post written notice for the membership of all general membership meetings. The written notice shall be posted at the Tribal Administration Building and other places of tribal business one (1) week before the start of the general membership meeting. The written notice shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Location of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Date and Time of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Agenda of the meeting; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The date and time the notice is posted.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.4.040</num>
          <heading>Minutes Required.</heading>
          <text>The Chairman shall give Members of the Board at least twenty-four (24) hours' notice of a special meeting. Such notice shall contain:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Location of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Date and Time of the meeting; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Agenda of the meeting</text>
            <text>The Board may, by a majority vote, waive this notice requirement as to date, time, location, and agenda.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.5</num>
        <heading>Special Meetings</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.5.010</num>
          <heading>Time and Location.</heading>
          <text>The Chairman of the Board shall call special meetings upon their own initiative or upon the request of four (4) Members of the Board at a date, time, and location designated by the Chairman or if called by the request of four (4) Members of the Board, at the date, time, and location specified in such request.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.5.020</num>
          <heading>Notice Required.</heading>
          <text>The Chairman shall give Members of the Board at least twenty-four (24) hours' notice of a special meeting. Such notice shall contain:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Location of the meeting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Date and Time of the meeting; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Agenda of the meeting.</text>
            <text>The Board may, by a majority vote, waive this notice requirement as to date, time, location, and agenda.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.5.030</num>
          <heading>Majority Vote Required.</heading>
          <text>All decisions of the Board upon motions made at a special meeting shall be by majority vote as defined in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(l)">MCC.2.2.010(l)</cite> and <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(k)">(k)</cite> except as otherwise provided by the Constitution and Bylaws.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.5.040</num>
          <heading>Minutes Required.</heading>
          <text>The Secretary/Treasurer shall ensure that minutes shall be kept of all matters coming before the Board at a special meeting.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>MCC.2.6</num>
        <heading>General Rules and Common Motions</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.6.010</num>
          <heading>General Rules and Common Motions.</heading>
          <text>All matters before the Board shall be under informal consideration, which is the Board shall act as a committee and be empowered to amend a request being considered before any formal vote needs to be taken. This will allow the Board to alter requests, resolutions, ordinances, letters, etc. before voting on them. The following is a list of common motions that shall be used in official meetings unless all present Board Members agree to suspend the general rules and motions in the section.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <heading>To Introduce Other Business.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to add a matter to the agenda that was not listed on the agenda or the notice for the meeting. Matters that were not on the agenda are called other business and can be added to the agenda if there is a motion made, seconded, and affirmed by a majority vote. For routine matters the Chairman may dispense with the formality of a motion and the vote and simply announce that the matter is adopted if there is no objection. In the event of an objection, the Chairman shall call for the motion to be seconded. If there is no second, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>To Go into Executive Session.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to close the meetings to non-Board Members (except those who have the consent of the Board) as per <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.2.010|(e)">MCC.2.2.010(e)</cite>. Once this motion is made, the Chairman shall ask for the motion to be seconded. If this motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote, and upon passing with a majority, the Chairman shall announce that the Board is now meeting in executive session and take the necessary steps to assure that non-Board Members are not present. Non-Board Members shall not be present once the Chairman has announced that the Board is now meeting in executive session.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <heading>To Leave Executive Session.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to close the executive session and open the meeting to non-Board Members pre <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§MCC.2.1.090">MCC.2.1.090</cite>. Once this motion is made, the Chairman shall ask for the motion to be seconded. If this motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote, and upon passing with a majority, the Chairman shall announce that the meeting is now open.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <heading>To Table.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to stop a discussion or a debate on an issue, resolution, or ordinance without taking a final vote on the issue. Usually this motion is used when more information is needed before an informed vote can be cast and the necessary information that is not readily available. This motion cannot be amended and an affirmative vote on this motion cannot be reconsidered. If the motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <heading>To Take from the Table.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to restart discussion or debate on a previously tabled issue. This motion cannot be amended and an affirmative vote on this motion cannot be reconsidered. If the motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <heading>To Postpone to a Certain Time.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to set a matter aside for a predetermined period of time. Unlike a motion to table, this motion is used when the time of reopening the issue is known at the time of making the motion. This motion can be amended by altering the time. Very limited debate is allowed for this motion, and the Chairman shall ask for the motion to be seconded and call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <heading>To Call for the Question.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to ask the Board to decide if they want to vote on the pending issue. If the Chairman determines that the debate has come to a close, they may avoid the formality of this motion and simply call for a vote, as long as there are no objections, a vote of on this motion may be avoided. In the event that there is an objection, a formal motion is required. This motion cannot be amended. If the motion is made by a Member who is not the Chairman then the motion needs to be seconded. If the motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <heading>To Call for the Orders of the Day.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to adhere to the scheduled order of business or follow the agenda. If the meeting begins to address topics that are unrelated to the topics on the agenda, a Board Member may make this motion, and the Chairman shall call for a vote. This motion cannot be amended and does not require to be seconded.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <heading>To Discuss.</heading>
            <text>This motion is utilized when a motion is under consideration and the Chairman fails to open discussion on the motion. This motion does not need to be seconded. The Chairman may call for discussion, and in the absence of an objection, the Members shall start discussion.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <heading>Motion to Reconsider.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to call for another vote on an issue or motion upon which a vote has previously been taken. This motion shall not be made by a Member who did not vote on the original motion or issue of concern. If the motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <heading>To Amend.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to alter or modify a motion that is being discussed or has already been passed. Any Board Member can make this motion even if the motion they want amended is not their own motion. If the motion is seconded, the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <heading>To Withdraw.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used when the person who made the motion wishes to withdraw their motion. The motion to withdraw can only be made before the Chairman has called for a vote on the original motion. This motion is used to rescind one's own motion, modify the motion, or substitute another motion in the original motion's place. The Chairman shall grant the motion without a vote if there are no objections. If there is an objection, the Chairman shall put the request to a vote. When a motion is withdrawn then the effect is the same as if the motion had never been made.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <heading>To Reconvene.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to take a break from the meeting and meet again to continue on the same original or amended agenda for that meeting without the need for giving formal notice again. A time to reconvene must be identified in the motion. This motion may be utilized to take short breaks for several minutes or take longer breaks that may last for no more than five (5) days. If the motion is seconded the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <heading>To Adjourn.</heading>
            <text>This motion is used to bring the meeting to a close. Once the meeting is adjourned it cannot be reopened. Once the meeting is adjourned it cannot be reopened. Once the meeting is adjourned and another meeting is desired, then a new meeting shall be called and all the formalities of a new meeting shall be followed including notice, approving minutes from previous meetings, etc. If the motion is seconded the Chairman shall call for a vote.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>MCC.2.6.020</num>
          <heading>Procedures Not Prescribed by this Ordinance.</heading>
          <text>All regular and special meetings shall be governed by Robert's Rules of Order except as otherwise provided by this ordinance and the Constitution and Bylaws, or to the extent such rules of order are inconsistent with this ordinance and the Constitution and Bylaws.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
</document>
