<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-127">
  <num>2023-127</num>
  <heading>Resolution Authorizing Adoption of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Grants Policy</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-10-16</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-127.pdf">Res. No. 2023-127</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-10-16</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Tribe") is a federally recognized Indian tribe organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. § 5101, et seq.; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, Section 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(l)">Article V, Section 1(l) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "organize, charter, and regulate any association or group. . . for the purpose of providing social or economic benefits to the members of the Band or residents of the reservation;" and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, Section 1(h)</cite> which further empowers the Tribal Governing Board the full authority to engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Lac Court Oreilles mission is provide for the educational, health, social welfare, and economic stability of the present and future generations, and the funding awarded under grant opportunities ensures our ability to protect our land and our people; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board prioritizes the health and wellbeing of its member and ensures their safety in the face of hazards is prioritized; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board supports a written policy on how the Tribe handles grant funding to ensure the success of each grant and of the specific grantee program.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby approves and adopts the attached Grant Policy to be used to promote success of all current and future grant funding opportunities.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>that the Secretary Treasurer of the Tribal Governing Board is hereby authorized to sign any other documents or take any other necessary action to carry out the intent of this resolution.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>7</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>16<sup>th</sup> day of October, 2023</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>6</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong>0<u/></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>____________________________________</text>
    <text>William Trepanier, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <codify:insert doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="PAP" after="PAP.10" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|PAP.11.1.010">
    <container>
      <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
      <num>PAP.11</num>
      <heading>Grant Management</heading>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>PAP.11.1</num>
        <heading>General Provisions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.1.010</num>
          <heading>Authority</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Governing Board holds the authority to provide for application and acceptance of grants and agreements from federal and state agencies and all other third parties pursuant to the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Article V, §1(c) which empowers the TGB to "to negotiate, make and perform contracts and agreements of every description, not inconsistent with law or with any provisions of this Constitution, with any person, association, or corporation, with any county, or with the State of Wisconsin or in the United States." All grants shall be consistent with the Tribe's goals, policies, and priorities. This policy provides guidance to ensure an orderly process in seeking, making applications for, accepting, administering grants, and assigning compliance responsibility for the provisions of all approved Tribally approved agreements. This policy is applicable to all employees of the Tribe and pertains to all activities associated with grants and other agreements with federal and other governments and other third parties. Compliance provisions of this Chapter are applicable to all employees responsible for administering programs financed under contract and compact agreements entered into under the Indian Self-Determination Act, and all other grant and cooperative agreements with federal and state agencies and other third parties.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.1.020</num>
          <heading>Purpose</heading>
          <text>To provide uniform guidance in the process of considering, applying for, accepting, and administering grants and agreements from federal agencies, state agencies, and all other third-party sources.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.1.030</num>
          <heading>Effective Date</heading>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided in specific sections, the provisions of this Grant Management policy shall be effective on the date adopted by the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.1.040</num>
          <heading>Severability and Non-Liability</heading>
          <text>If any section, provision or portion of this fiscal policy and procedural manual is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this fiscal policy and procedural manual shall not be affected thereby. The Tribe further asserts immunity on its part and that of its agencies, employees, and/or agents from any action or damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon and conformance with this fiscal policy and procedural manual.</text>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.1.050</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Inconsistent Governmental Manual(s)</heading>
          <text>All previous Grant Management policy and procedural manual(s) of the Tribe inconsistent with this manual are hereby repealed and the provisions of this manual shall govern the fiscal and accounting related activities of the Tribe.</text>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <num>PAP.11.2</num>
        <heading>Grants</heading>
        <text>(a) The Chairman of the Tribal Governing Board has been delegated authority to negotiate, execute, sign, and modify grant documents that implement programs, activities, and functions that have been approved by the Tribal Governing Board. This delegation includes signature authority for all agreements that are necessary for the successful implementation of the program, e.g., sub-contracts, etc.</text>
        <text>(b) Execution of grant awards is vested with the Tribal Chairman. Employees may not sign awards on behalf of the Tribe unless acting formally on behalf of the Chairman under written delegated authority.</text>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.010</num>
          <heading>Grant Selection</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Employees are encouraged to seek and examine grant opportunities to promote the general and specific goals of the Tribe. In general, consideration will be given to grants that meet the following criteria:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Are consistent with the Tribes long term goals and objectives as set forth in the Tribe's comprehensive plan, and/or annual work plans or as directed by Tribal Governing Board consensus.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Will advance established program goal(s) or support for already authorized programs,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Will be self-supporting (i.e., the cost for administering the grant can be paid for entirely by the grant, including its share of indirect costs, or through some other means, such as cost sharing with already available budgetary resources, or through appropriation of Tribal revenue).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Can be administered in a timely and efficient manner,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Will not place unreasonable burdens on staff and facilities, thereby compromising other Tribal services and goals,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Can be carried out consistent with the full expectations of the funding agency within the technical capability of the organization.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Does not place an inappropriate financial burden on the Tribe or create community expectations that are unreasonable to fulfill in the absence of the grant.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>With input and support of specific staff through an internal review process, the Chairman shall review grant opportunities identified by employees, authorize grant applications, and shall make a determination if a Tribal Governing Board resolution is appropriate or necessary.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Matching requirements associated with grants, whether direct, indirect, or in-kind shall be authorized consistent with budget policies.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Budgets incorporated within grant applications shall conform to the Tribe's Cost Allocation Policies, and procedures implemented by the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.020</num>
          <heading>Approval Policy</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Upon notice of award, the grant agreement shall be reviewed by the LCO Legal Department, Compliance Department, and, when relevant, the Information Technology Department prior to execution by the Chairman.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Departmental review ensures the grant conditions are appropriate for the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Departmental review ensures the necessary resources are available for the implementation of the grant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If the conditions of the grant require additional authority or resources, the Chairman and/or Secretary Treasurer will assure that budget authority is appropriately addressed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The Chairman is authorized to execute renewal of ongoing grants, contracts, and compacts on an annual basis.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.030</num>
          <heading>Implementation</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Upon acceptance and execution of a grant, the department director is responsible for implementing and carrying out the grant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The assigned department director shall have direct responsibility to assure that all activities undertaken using grant resources are applicable, allocable, and allowable under the provisions of the grant, federal regulations, applicable state regulations, and applicable Tribal policies,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The assigned department director shall have direct responsibility for all record keeping and reporting requirements of the grant are fully complied with.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Compliance Department shall establish procedures to monitor compliance of all financial and programmatic activities and reporting, consistent with grant requirements and applicable laws and regulations.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Where grants are for ongoing programs, the department director responsible for implementation of the program shall be responsible for initiating renewal applications on a timely basis with the assistance of the Grants Department for submission.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.040</num>
          <heading>Disputes and Exceptions</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>To the extent that issues arise with the granting agency regarding any aspects of grant implementation, including disputes or exceptions taken by the granting agency with procedures or activities of the Tribe in carrying out the grant, the department director charged with grant implementation shall take immediate action to resolve the issue and shall advise the Compliance Department regarding the issue.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Disputes and exceptions considered of material nature by the Compliance Manager shall be reported to the Tribal Governing Board on a timely basis along with a summary of actions being taken to resolve the issue.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.050</num>
          <heading>Pass Through Awards</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Ensure that every subaward is clearly identified to the subrecipient as a subaward and includes the following information at the time of the subaward and if any of these data elements change, include the changes in subsequent subaward modification. When some of this information is not available, the pass-through entity must provide the best information available to describe the Federal award and subaward. Required information includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Federal Award Identification:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Subrecipient name (which must match the name associated with its unique entity identifier).</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Subrecipient' s unique entity identifier.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Federal Award Identification Number (FAIN).</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>Federal Award Date of award to the recipient by the Federal agency.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>Subaward Period of Performance Start and End Date.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>Amount of Federal Funds Obligated by this action by the pass-through entity to the subrecipient.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(G)</num>
                <text>Total amount of Federal Funds Obligated to the subrecipient by the pass-through entity including the current obligation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(H)</num>
                <text>Total amount of Federal Award committed to the subrecipient by the pass-­through entity.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>Federal award project description, as required to be responsive to the Federal Funding Accountability and Transparency Act (FFATA).</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(J)</num>
                <text>Name of Federal awarding agency, pass-through entity, and contact information for awarding official of the Pass-through entity.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(K)</num>
                <text>Assistance Listing Number and Name' the pass-through entity must identify the dollar amount made available under each Federal award and the Assistance Listing number at time of disbursement.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(L)</num>
                <text>Identification of whether the award is R&amp;D; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(M)</num>
                <text>Indirect cost rate for the Federal award (including if the de minimis rate is charged.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>All requirements imposed by the pass-through entity on the subrecipient so that the Federal award is used in accordance with Federal statutes, regulations and the terms and conditions of the Federal award.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Any additional requirements that the pass-through entity imposes on the subrecipient in order for the pass-through entity to meet its own responsibility to the Federal awarding agency including identification of any required financial and performance reports.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>An approved federally recognized indirect cost rate negotiated between the subrecipient and the Federal Government or, if no such rate exists, either a rate negotiated between the pass-through entity and the subrecipient, or a de minimis indirect cost rate.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>A requirement that the subrecipient permit the pass-through entity and auditors to have access to the subrecipient's records and financial statements as necessary for the pass-through entity to meet the requirements of this part; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Appropriate terms and conditions concerning closeout of the subaward.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Evaluate each subrecipient's risk of noncompliance with Federal statutes, regulations, and the terms and conditions of the subaward for purposes of determining the appropriate subrecipient monitoring described in paragraphs (d) and (e) of <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.11.2.050">this section</cite>, which may include consideration of such factors as:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>The subrecipient's prior experience with the same or similar subawards.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>The results of previous audits include whether or not the subrecipient receives a Single Audit in accordance with Subpart F- Audit Requirements of this part, and the extent to which the same or similar subaward has been audited as a major program.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Whether the subrecipient has new personnel or new or substantially changed systems; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>The extent and results of Federal awarding agency monitoring (e.g., if the subrecipient also receives Federal awards directly from a federal awarding agency)</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>Consider imposing specific subaward conditions upon a subrecipient if appropriate as described in 2 CFR §200.207 Specific conditions.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>Monitor the activities of the subrecipient as necessary to ensure that the subaward is used for authorized purposes, in compliance with Federal statutes, regulations, and the terms and conditions of the subaward; and that subaward performance goals are achieved. Pass-through entity monitoring of the subrecipient must include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Reviewing financial and performance reports required by the pass-through entity.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Following-up and ensuring that the subrecipient takes timely and appropriate action on all deficiencies pertaining to the Federal award provided to the subrecipient from the passthrough entity detected through audits, on-site reviews, and other means.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Issuing a management decision for audit findings pertaining to the Federal award provided to the subrecipient from the passthrough entity as required by 2 CFR §200.521 Management decision.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>Depending upon the pass-through entity's assessment of risk posed by the subrecipient, the following monitoring tools may be useful for the pass-through entity to ensure proper accountability and compliance with program requirements and achievement of performance goals.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>Providing subrecipients with training and technical assistance on program-related matters.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>Performing on-site reviews of the subrecipient's program operations.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(G)</num>
                <text>Arranging for agreed-upon-procedures engagements as described in 2 CFR §200.425 Audit services.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(H)</num>
                <text>Verify that every subrecipient is audited as required by Subpart F-Audit Requirements of this part when it is expected that the subrecipient's Federal awards expended during the respective fiscal year equaled or exceeded the threshold set forth in 2 CFR §200.501 Audit requirements.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>Consider whether the results of the subrecipient's audits, onsite reviews, or other monitoring indicate conditions that necessitate adjustments to the pass-through entity's own records.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(J)</num>
                <text>Consider taking enforcement action against noncompliant subrecipients as described in 2 CFR §200.338 Remedies for noncompliance of this part and in program regulations.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.060</num>
          <heading>Proposal Development</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Grant Authorization form, attachment A, is completed by the requesting department director or Grants staff. Once all details are completed including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Assistance Listing Number,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Funding Agency,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Opportunity Title,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Requested budget amount,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Project period,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>and Description of proposal,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Required signatures of: Department Director, Planning and Grants Department Director, Compliance Manager, Executive Director, and at minimum four Tribal Governing Board Members.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The lead writer, selected by the Grants Department Director shall create a Grant Proposal and Management Team including but not limited to:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Tribal Governing Board designee</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Secretary/Treasurer of TGB</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Executive Director</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Chief Financial Officer</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Compliance Manager</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Director or designee of Department responsible for implementation of grant to be developed.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Stakeholder representatives will be assigned by their supervisors and/or TGB designees to work with the Grant Proposal and Management Team to assist with the development of each grant proposal as warranted. This will enable those responsible for administering and reporting on the grant projects to review, revise, approve, and disapprove proposed projects based upon considerations of administrative and technical capacity, attainable goals, objectives, and deliverables, budget costs versus benefits, and fund matching requirements. However, the Tribal Governing Board retains the right to accept, reject, or modify stakeholder recommendations and proposed revisions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The lead writer will work with the Grants Department Director under the purview of the Grants Department Director to coordinate the effort of all involved in the grant development process for each grant. The lead writer will continue meeting with team members and stakeholders to develop grant application and required attachments and supporting documents generally including but not limited to supporting research and data, project goals and objectives, narratives, logic models, management plans, budgets and budget narratives, assurances, standard federal forms, resolutions, etc.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>A majority vote from the Tribal Governing Board must be received by the Grants department in order to submit grant proposals to funding agencies.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.070</num>
          <heading>Awards</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Upon receipt of notice of award, the Program Director shall email the originals to the Chairman's Administrative Assistant or designee, who will obtain the Tribal Chairperson's signature, on the agreement. Once complete, the Program Director shall email a copy of the agreement to the funding agency with a copy to the Chairman's Administrative Assistant or designee, Program Director, Compliance Department and to the Financial Analyst and Accounting Specialists, so a fund number is issued, and drawdown accounts can be created.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If the Tribe receives a new award without Director assigned or Department Director;</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The Executive Director shall send the Financial Analyst and Compliance Department a copy of the signed award agreement and associated documents, approved budget in Excel format with tribal general ledger expense codes and a copy of submitted grant application.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The Compliance Department shall review the excel budget to verify match of submitted proposal, award document, and approve for funding code to be created.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The Financial Analyst shall create a fund code for new awards or add the new Fiscal Year to the existing fund code for continuing awards.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Upon budget posting in the accounting system, the Executive Director shall submit the job posting intake form for awards without identified staff upon award to Executive Director and Human Resources.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Upon Program Director implementation of the new award, the Grants Department shall provide Grant Management Orientation. This orientation shall include the Compliance Department in order to discuss award terms and conditions, programmatic and financial reporting, explain goals and objectives, assign role in grant management portal, and other pertinent information.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Accounting Specialist shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>set up the initial grant and drawdown summary reports when the Tribe is awarded a new grant; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Submit summary report to program director and appropriate management to maintain in the master grant file.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Once the Financial Analyst receives notification and supporting documentation of the new award, they shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Sets up the appropriate fund; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Enter the approved budget into the accounting system,</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Program Directors shall maintain master grant files.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.080</num>
          <heading>Maintenance and Compliance</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>All terms, conditions, and requirements of the grants and between the Tribe and the funding agencies or contractors shall be strictly complied with.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Executive Director is responsible for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Oversight of all externally funded awards and programs;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Monitor grant compliance and assist directors as needed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Ensure good stewardship and compliance with the §200 CFR Subpart A - F to avoid fraud, waste, and abuse of Federal funds; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Work with the Compliance, Accounting Department, and the Program Director to ensure all expiring grants are closed out timely and all grant files and records are retained and archived for audit purposes.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Program Director is responsible for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Ensuring good stewardship and compliance with the §200 CFR Subpart A - F to carry out the goals and objectives of the award;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Read and understand all grants;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Maintain award documents, grant summary, and provide updates and copies of all correspondence and modifications to the award or budget to the Compliance Department on an ongoing basis until the grant is closed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Review detailed general ledger transactions and budget to actual report no less than once per month to ensure expenditures are recorded correctly and are in compliance with the award; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Document matching requirements for funding agency reporting purposes.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Chief Financial Officer (or designee) is responsible for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Grant monitoring for compliance, reporting for audit purposes, and informs directors, management, and the Tribal Governing Board of any discrepancies;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Processing all drawdowns for payments from the funding agencies as requested by the Compliance Department;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Maintain grant/drawdown summaries; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Ensure all financial information provided to the Tribe and funding agencies accurately reflect audited numbers.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Compliance department is responsible for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Designating a Compliance Manager specifically tasked with the daily responsibility of monitoring grant compliance;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The Compliance Manager is the person primarily responsible for overseeing and managing grant compliance issues within the Tribe;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Assisting Program Directors and Accounting Departments as needed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Ensuring all grants are read and understood;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Ensuring all terms, conditions, and requirements of the grants between the Tribe and the funding agencies or contractors will be strictly complied with;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Document matching requirements for funding agency reporting purposes; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Responsible for preparation and submission of financial reports to the funding agencies.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>If the Tribe has grants with matching requirements, levels of effort, and/or earmarking limitations, the Program Director, Compliance Manager, and Financial Analyst, shall monitor activities to ensure that requirements and limitations are met, and amounts claimed or used for matching were determined in accordance with applicable laws and regulations.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.090</num>
          <heading>Financial Management</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe's financial management system, including records documenting compliance with all statutes, regulations, and the terms and conditions of all awards, must be sufficient to permit the preparation of reports required by general and program-specific terms and conditions; and the tracing of funds to a level of expenditures adequate to establish that such funds have been used according to the statutes, regulations, and the terms and conditions of the awards. The financial management system of the Tribe must provide for the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Identification (ID), in its accounts, of all awards received and expended and the programs under which they were received.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Program and award identification (ID) must include, as applicable:</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The federal assistance listing number,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Award identification (ID) number and year,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Name of the funding agency, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Name of the pass-through entity, if any.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Each grant will be accounted for separately by using a fund/department code issued by the Financial Analyst. Costs will not be incurred without a fund/department number.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Accurate, current, and complete disclosure of the financial results of each award or program in accordance with the reporting requirements set forth in 2 CFR §200.327, titled "Financial reporting", and 2 CFR §200.328, titled "Monitoring and reporting program performance."</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Sound internal controls require timely and accurate financial information to be prepared and presented to management for review.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Financial reports will be prepared for required accounting periods within the time imposed and on the basis of accounting required by the grantor agencies.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Compliance Department will perform all grant financial reporting for the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Program Director is responsible for maintaining the:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Grant reporting schedule to ensure all reports are submitted on time.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Master grant files for audit purposes.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Grant financial and programmatic reports are kept on file by the Compliance Manager of the Tribe.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The Financial Analyst also provides reports to the Program Directors, management, and the Tribal Governing Board so they have the most current up to date information and are able to update their grant files. These may include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Revenue/expenditure reports, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>General ledger account detail reports.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.100</num>
          <heading>Award Payments</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Drawdowns will be done according to grant guidelines provided by the funding agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>While some grants may be drawn down in advance, many will be drawn down on a reimbursement basis.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If a federal grant is drawn down in advance, the Tribe shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Need to minimize time between funds received from the U.S. Treasury and disbursements made to vendors, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If kept in an interest-bearing account pursuant to 2 CFR§200.30S(b)(8).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Interest earned amounts up to $500.00 per year may be retained by the Tribe for administrative expenses. 2 CFR §200.305(b)(9)</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Interest exceeding $500.00 per year must be remitted annually to the federal government. Pursuant to 2 CFR §200.305(b)(9).</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.110</num>
          <heading>Drawdowns</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The following cash drawdown procedures will govern the drawing of cash from the various funding agencies to ensure the drawing of federal cash will minimize the time between funds received from the U.S. Treasury and disbursements made to vendors:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>All grant drawdowns are prepared and processed by the Accounting Specialists, or other assigned staff.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Funds are requested following the protocols of each funding source and after any required reviews and approvals.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>For normal drawdowns, the Compliance Department reviews each of the Federal programs after month-end close and processes a drawdown monthly, or more often as needed.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>For construction projects, the Executive Director or designee informs the Accounting Department three (3) days in advance before a large payment is needed so funds can be drawn prior to making the payment.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Certified payroll reports are required on construction projects unless waived in writing by the funding agency, in compliance with Davis Bacon Related Acted (DBRA). Waiver of requirements must also be attached to the payment request just as certified payroll reports must be attached to all payment requests to the Accounts Payable staff before a payment can be made to the vendor.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>When the drawdown is complete, a printout is made of the cash drawdown and filed in the grant file. Copies are given to the Tribe's Accounting Department and the Compliance Department for the master file.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>The Compliance Department must provide documentation supporting the dollar amount being drawn down and to be in compliance with the Federal grants reporting requirements according to 2 CFR §200.302(b)(3), titled "Financial Management. " Supporting documentation includes:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Drawdown printout,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Grant and drawdown summary report,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(C)</num>
                <text>Revenue/expenditures report for each grant,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(D)</num>
                <text>Trial balance (TB) summary,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(E)</num>
                <text>General ledger account (GLA) detail, and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(F)</num>
                <text>Cumulative general ledger account (GLA) detail for closeout final reports.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Accounting Specialists will complete the drawdown and record the drawdown by entering the transaction in the general ledger (GL).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>The Tribe's bank account is reviewed each business day by the Accounting Specialists and when the drawdown is deposited in the bank account, cash is debited, and Grant Revenue is credited within the general ledger (GL) for the incoming cash. An adjustment is made to the receivable at year-end close with an accrued/deferred journal entry (JE).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.120</num>
          <heading>Cost Sharing and Matching</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Cost sharing or matching may be considered if it is both in accordance with Federal awarding agency regulations and specified in a notice of funding opportunity later awarded to the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>In cases where matching funds are required, it is the responsibility of the Program Director or Executive Director to ensure that adequate matching funds are secured.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Governing Board must approve all cost sharing or matching costs before submitting to the funding agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>It is also the Program Director's responsibility to make sure the matching funds meet the guidelines called for in the award documents for non-federal matches.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The in-kind form must have the match provider's signature as well as the Program Director's signature.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.130</num>
          <heading>Program Eligibility</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Many grants require that individuals who receive goods or services meet certain eligibility requirements. It is the responsibility of the Program Directors to document eligibility before providing services. It is not the responsibility of the Accounting and Compliance Departments to determine eligibility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If the Tribe provides services under award programs with eligibility requirements, a Program Director or designee will use a set checklist to review and approve the provision of services to ensure that recipients are eligible under specific program requirements.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.140</num>
          <heading>Program Income</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Program income is funds generated from specific activities approved by the funding agency and includes interest earned on loans made to program recipients with award funds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Except as otherwise provided in statutes, regulations, or the terms and conditions of awards, program income does NOT include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Interest earned on advances of award funds and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Interest earned on rebates, credits, or discounts.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Taxes, special assessments, levies, fines, and other such revenues raised by the Tribe are NOT program income unless the revenues are specifically identified in the award or awarding agency regulations as program income.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall copy the Accounting Department to record the receipt and expenditures of revenues (taxes, special assessments, levies, fines, and other such revenues raised by the Tribe, etc.) as part of program income when such revenues are earmarked for the program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Proceeds from the sale of real property or equipment are NOT program income. Such proceeds will be handled in accordance with the requirements:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Subpart D, titled "Post Federal Award Requirements Standards for Financial and Program Management" Property standards are as followed:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Real property as defined in 2 CFR §200.311(a), titled "Real property"</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Equipment as defined in 2 CFR §200.3131(a) titled "Equipment" and as §200.313</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>As specifically identified in statutes, regulations, or the terms and conditions of the award.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>If the awarding agency does not specify in its regulations or the terms and conditions of the award, or give prior approval for how program income is to be used pursuant to 2 CFR §200.307(e)(l), titled ''Program income" must apply:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Ordinarily program income must be deducted from total allowable costs to determine the net allowable costs. Program income must be used for current costs unless the awarding agency authorizes otherwise. Program income, which the Tribe did not anticipate at the time of the award, must be used to reduce the award and Tribal contributions rather than to increase the funds committed to the project.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>With prior approval of the awarding agency, program income may be added to the award by the awarding agency and the Tribe. The program income must be used for the purposes and under the conditions of the award.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>With prior approval of the awarding agency, program income may be used to meet the cost sharing or matching requirement of the award. The amount of the award remains the same.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>The Tribe will follow a formal approval process for activities generating program income.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.150</num>
          <heading>Modification</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>For grant modifications, the Tribe is required to report deviations from budget, project scope, or objective, and request written approval from awarding agencies for budget and program plan revision.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>For non-construction awards, the Program Director must request prior approval from awarding agencies for one (1) or more of the following program or budget-related reasons:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Change in the scope or the objective of the program (even if there is no associated budget revision requiring prior written approval).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Change in a key person specified in the application or the award.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The disengagement from the project for more than three (3) months, or a 25 percent (25%) reduction in time devoted to the project by the approved program.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>The inclusion, unless waived by the awarding agency, of costs that require prior approval in accordance with CFR §200 Subpart E, titled "Cost Principles"</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>The transfer of funds budgeted for participant support costs, to other categories of expense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>Unless described in the application and funded in the approved awards, the sub-awarding, transferring, or contracting out of any work under an award. This provision does not apply to the acquisition of supplies, material, equipment, or general support services.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>Changes in the amount of approved cost sharing or matching provided by the Tribe.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>For construction federal awards, the Tribe must request prior written approval promptly from the federal awarding agency for budget revisions whenever the following applies:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The revision results from changes in the scope or the objective of the project or program.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The need arises for additional federal funds to complete the project.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>A revision is desired which involves specific costs for which prior written approval requirements may be imposed consistent with applicable CFR §200 listed in Subpart E-Cost Principles</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>No other prior approval requirements for budget revisions may be imposed unless a deviation has been approved by OMB.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>When a federal awarding agency makes a federal award to the Tribe which provides support for construction and non-construction work, the federal awarding agency shall require the Tribe to obtain prior approval from the federal awarding agency before making any fund or budget transfers between the two types of work supported.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Generally, grant modifications follow most of the same guidelines for regular budget modifications, although some of the budget requirements for grants are more stringent. Some grants also will not allow any amount over the amount that was requested for administration, indirect costs, salaries, or other line items.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Departmental requests to move grant funds from one budget line item to another must be made in writing. Depending upon the amount, the request may need the approval of the Tribal Governing Board and approval from the funding source. Copies of all modifications should be given to the Compliance Department and the Financial Analyst to record in the accounting system. At the least, a budget modification is required when one (1) of the following changes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>One (1) line of the budget has exceeded more than ten percent (10%) of the total budget. The Tribal Governing Board must also approve all budget modifications if any line item exceeds ten percent (10%) of the total grant.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Plans to hire a position that is not included in the original budget.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Plans to make a large equipment purchase (over $5,000.00) not budgeted for.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>There is an increase or decrease in funding from the relevant funding source.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The Program Director, with agreement from Compliance Department and Accounting Department, must receive Tribal Governing Board approval of all budget modifications before submission to the funding agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>The Program Director will always submit to the appropriate management at the funding agency, after receiving approval from the Compliance and Accounting Departments, when a modification is needed, specifically when the budget modification exceeds an agency allowed maximum budget modification not requiring approval and moving funds from one budget line item to another that did not exist in agency approved budget.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.160</num>
          <heading>Monitoring Program Performance</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe is responsible for oversight of the operations of activities supported by an award.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The Tribe must monitor its activities under awards to assure compliance with applicable requirements.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The Compliance Manager or designee and Executive Director or designee shall constantly monitor program performance under grant-supported activities to assure adequate progress is being made toward achieving the goals of the grant.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Monitoring by the Compliance Manager or designee and Executive Director or designee must cover each program, function, or activity of each grant as set forth in the approved grant application.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The awarding agency may make site visits as warranted by program needs.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.170</num>
          <heading>Reporting Program Performance</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe will employ department directors who will be responsible for the preparation and submission of all program performance reports.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The department director shall submit performance reports to the awarding agency in the frequency established per award specifications.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Copies of the reports shall be given to the Tribe's Compliance Department.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The awarding agency may waive the requirement of any performance report if not needed.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.180</num>
          <heading>Non-Construction Performance Reports</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe must submit performance reports at the interval required by the awarding agency to best inform the agency of improvements in program outcomes and productivity. The awarding agency shall prescribe the frequency with which the performance reports will be submitted.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Intervals must be no less frequent than annually or more frequent than quarterly except in unusual circumstances.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>More frequent reporting may be necessary:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>For the effective monitoring of an award or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>When it could significantly affect program outcomes.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Annual reports are typically due ninety (90) calendar days after the reporting period, refer to award document.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Semiannual or quarterly reports must be due thirty (30) calendar days after the reporting period.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>The awarding agency may require annual reports before the anniversary dates of multiple year awards.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>The final performance report is typically due ninety (90) calendar days after the period of performance end date, refer to the award document.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>If a justified request is submitted by the Tribe, the awarding agency may extend the due date for any performance report.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribe must submit performance reports using approved government-wide standard information collections when providing performance information. The department director shall submit a performance report for each award which contains brief information on the following for each program, function, or activity involved:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>A comparison of actual accomplishments to the objectives of the award established for the period.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>Where the accomplishments of an award can be quantified, a computation of the cost (for example, related to units of accomplishment) may be required if that information is useful.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>Where performance trend data and analysis would be informative to the program and the awarding agency, the agency should include this as a performance reporting requirement.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The reasons why established goals were not met, if appropriate.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Additional pertinent information including, when appropriate, analysis and explanation of cost overruns or high unit costs.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.190</num>
          <heading>Construction Performance Reports</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>For the most part, onsite technical inspection and certified percentage of completion data are relied on heavily by awarding agencies to monitor progress under awards for construction.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The awarding agency may require additional performance reports only when considered necessary.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.200</num>
          <heading>Significant Developments</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Events may occur between the scheduled performance reporting dates which have significant impact upon the supported activity. In such cases, the Tribe's responsible department director or Executive Director or designee shall inform the awarding agency as soon as the following types of conditions become known:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Problems, delays, or adverse conditions will materially impair the ability to meet the objective of an award.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>This disclosure must include a statement of the action taken, or contemplated, and any assistance needed to resolve the situation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Favorable developments which enable meeting time schedules and objectives sooner or at less cost than anticipated or producing more or different beneficial results than originally planned.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.210</num>
          <heading>Grant Closeout</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe will adhere to procedures for closeout of grants at the end of the awarded period in accordance with 2 CFR §200.343, titled "Closeout".</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribe must submit no later than ninety (90) calendar days after the end date of the period of performance, all financial, performance, and other reports as required by or the terms and conditions of the Federal award. The Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity may approve extensions when requested by the nonfederal entity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Unless the Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity authorizes an extension, the Tribe must liquidate all obligations incurred under the Federal award not later than ninety (90) calendar days after the end date of the period of performance as specified in the terms and conditions of the Federal award.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity must make prompt payments to the Tribe for allowable reimbursable costs under the Federal award being closed out.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>The Tribe must promptly refund any balances of unobligated cash that the Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity paid in advance or paid and that is not authorized to be retained by the non-Federal entity for use in other projects pursuant to Circular A–129 and CFR §200.345 amounts due for requirements regarding unreturned amounts that become delinquent debts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Consistent with the terms and conditions of the Federal award, the Federal awarding agency or passthrough entity must make a settlement for any upward or downward adjustments to the Federal share of costs after closeout reports are received.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>The Tribe must account for any real and personal property acquired with Federal funds or received from the Federal government in accordance with 2 CFR §200.310 Insurance coverage, §200.316 Property trust relationship, and §200.329 Reporting on real property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>The Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity should complete all closeout actions for Federal awards no later than one year after receipt and acceptance of all required final reports.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.220</num>
          <heading>Post-Closeout Adjustments and Continuing Responsibilities</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe will adhere to procedures for post-closeout adjustments and continuing responsibilities of grants at the end of the awarded period in accordance with 2 CFR §200.344 and §200.344, "Post Closeout Adjustments and Continuing Responsibilities".</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The closeout of a federal award does not affect any of the following.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The right of the Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity to disallow costs and recover funds on the basis of a later audit or other review. The Federal awarding agency or passthrough entity must make any cost disallowance determination and notify the Tribe within the record retention period.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The obligation of the Tribe to return any funds due as a result of later refunds, corrections, or other transactions including final indirect cost rate adjustments.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Audit requirements in Subpart F—Audit Requirements of this part.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Property management and disposition requirements in Subpart D— Post Federal Award Requirements of this part, pursuant to 2 CFR §200.310-200.316.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Records retention as required in Subpart D—Post Federal Award Requirements of this part, 2 CFR §§200.333-200.337.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>After closeout of the Federal award, a relationship created under the Federal award may be modified or ended in whole or in part with the consent of the Federal awarding agency or pass-through entity and the Tribe, provided the responsibilities of the Tribe referred to in paragraph (a) of <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.11.2.220">this section</cite> including those for property management as applicable, are considered and provisions made for continuing responsibilities of the Tribe, as appropriate.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>PAP.11.2.230</num>
          <heading>Collection of Amounts Due</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Tribe will adhere to procedures for collection of amounts due from grants at the end of the awarded period in accordance with <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="PAP|200|200.3|200.345" proof="needed">§200.345</cite> "Collection of Amounts Due".</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Any funds paid to the Tribe in excess of the amount to which the Tribe is finally determined to be entitled under the terms of the Federal award constitute a debt to the Federal government. If not paid within ninety (90) calendar days after demand, the Federal awarding agency may reduce the debt by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Making an administrative offset against other requests for reimbursements.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Withholding advance payments otherwise due to the Tribe.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Or other action permitted by Federal statute.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Except where otherwise provided by statutes or regulations, the Federal awarding agency will charge interest on an overdue debt in accordance with the Federal Claims Collection Standards (31 CFR parts 900 through 999). The date from which interest is computed is not extended by litigation or the filing of any form of appeal.</text>
          </para>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
  </codify:insert>
</document>
