<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-16" codify:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2023-16</num>
  <heading>Amendment of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law Industrial Hemp Code CSV.8</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-03-06</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2023-16.pdf">Res. No. 2023-16</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-03-06</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. §5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, § 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people," pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, §1(h)</cite> and "to regulate by enactment of ordinances, the conduct of business within the territory of the Band, including the power to impose taxes or license fees upon members and non-members doing business within the reservation" pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, §1(n)</cite> and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Final Rule established by the Domestic Hemp Production Program mandated by the Agricultural Improvement Act of 2019 (the "2018 Farm Bill") has been issued, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>it is now necessary to update the Tribe's Industrial Hemp Code in order to comply with the updates in the Final Rule.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby pass this Resolution to amend the Industrial Hemp Code <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="CSV.8">CSV.8</cite> to as follows:</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <text>The Preamble shall be amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Preamble</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to the inherent sovereign authority of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians. In the implementation of this inherent sovereign authority, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h)</cite> and (n) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians, empowers the Tribal Governing Board to: "To engage in any business that will further the social or economic well-being of members of the Band or undertake any programs or projects designed for the economic advancement of the people," <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(h)">Article V, § 1 (h)</cite>; and "To regulate, by enactment of ordinances, the conduct of business within the territory of the Band, including the power to impose taxes or license fees upon members and non-members doing business within the reservation" <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, § 1 (n)</cite>. Pursuant to this inherent sovereign authority, the Tribal Governing Board hereby establishes the Agricultural Division of the Lac Courte Oreilles Conservation Department as a governmental instrumentality of the Tribe, and enacts this ordinance which shall establish the purposes, powers and duties of the same. The Agricultural Division shall carry out the requirements of the final rule established by the Domestic Hemp Production Program mandated by the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (the "2018 Farm Bill"). The 2018 Farm Bill recognizes the Tribe's primary regulatory authority over the production of hemp within the Tribe's territory and in accordance with federal and tribal laws, and a Tribal Hemp Plan approved by the United States Secretary of Agriculture. [remove :"Farm Bill as adopted and implemented by the Tribe pursuant to the provisions of this ordinance."]A copy of this ordinance duly certified by the Secretary/Treasurer of the Tribal Governing Board shall be admissible in evidence in any suit, action or proceedings.</text>
    </include>
    <codify:find-replace path="CSV.8" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.1.010">
      <find>The Agricultural Division shall carry out the requirements of the 2018 Farm Bill as adopted and implemented by the Tribe pursuant to the provisions of this ordinance. A copy of this ordinance duly certified by the Secretary/Treasurer of the Tribal Governing Board shall be admissible in evidence in any suit, action or proceedings.</find>
      <replace>The Agricultural Division shall carry out the requirements of the final rule established by the Domestic Hemp Production Program mandated by the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (the "2018 Farm Bill"). The 2018 Farm Bill recognizes the Tribe's primary regulatory authority over the production of hemp within the Tribe's territory and in accordance with federal and tribal laws, and a Tribal Hemp Plan approved by the United States Secretary of Agriculture. A copy of this ordinance duly certified by the Secretary/Treasurer of the Tribal Governing Board shall be admissible in evidence in any suit, action or proceedings.</replace>
    </codify:find-replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <text>Section 2. To insert the following definitions to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="CSV.8.2">Subchapter CSV.8.2</cite>:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(pp)</num>
        <text>"Disposal" means an activity that transitions the non-complaint product into a non-retrievable or non-ingestible form. Such activities include plowing, tilling, or disking plant materials into the soil; mulching, composting, chopping, or bush mowing plant material into green manure; burning plant material; burying plant material into the earth and covering with soil.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>"Dry weight basis" means the ration of the amount of moisture in a sample to the amount of dry solid in a sample. Percentage of THC on a dry weight basis means the percentage of THC, by weight, in a non-compliant hemp item, after excluding moisture from the item.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(hh)</num>
        <text>"Remediation" means the process of rending non-compliant cannabis, complaint. Remediation can occur by removing and destroying flower material, while retaining stalk, stem, leaf material, and seeds. Remediation can also occur by shredding the entire plant into a biomass like material, then re-testing the shredded biomass material for compliance.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.2.010" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.2.010">
      <section>
        <num>CSV.8.2.010</num>
        <heading>General Definitions</heading>
        <text>The following terms, wherever used in this ordinance, shall be construed to apply as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><strong>"Agricultural Division" or "Division"</strong> means the Agricultural Division of the Lac Courte Oreilles Conservation Department as established by the Tribal Governing Board through this ordinance which shall serve as a governmental instrumentality and arm of the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><strong>"Applicant"</strong> means a natural Person, or a business entity, who submits an application to participate in the Tribe's Hemp program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><strong>"Cannabis sativa L."</strong> means all parts of the plant Cannabis sativa L., whether being cultivated or not, including its seeds, resin, compounds, salts, derivatives, and extracts, and does not mean Publicly Marketable Hemp Product, as defined by this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><strong>"CBD"</strong> means cannabidiol.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text><strong>"Certified Seed"</strong> means Seed for which a certificate or other instrument has been issued by a review board or certifying agency authorized under the laws of the Tribe, a state, federal law, any other federally recognized Indian tribe, or U.S. territory or possession to certify Hemp Seed varietals if cultivated to maturity would test at or below 0.3% Delta-9-THC  concentration on a dry weight basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><strong>"Citizen"</strong> means an enrolled member of the Lac Courte Oreilles Lake Superior Band of Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text><strong>"Conservation Department" or "Department" </strong>means the Conservation Department of the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><strong>"Decarboxylated" or "Decarboxylation"</strong> means the completion of the chemical reaction that converts tetrahydrocannabinolic acid into Delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol, the intoxicating component of cannabis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text><strong>"Delta-9-THC"</strong> means Delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol concentration (the primary intoxicating component of Cannabis sativa L.), accounting for Decarboxylation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text><strong>"Director"</strong> shall mean the Director of the Agricultural Division of the Lac Courte Oreilles Conservation Department, as established by this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text><strong>"Disposal"</strong> means an activity that transitions the non-complaint product into a non-retrievable or non-ingestible form. Such activities include plowing, tilling, or disking plant materials into the soil; mulching, compositing, chopping, or bush mowing plant material into green manure; burning plant material; burying plant material into the earth and covering with soil.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text><strong>"Drug Enforcement Administration" or "DEA"</strong> means the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text><strong>"Dry weight basis"</strong> means the ratio of the amount of moisture in a sample to the amount of dry solid in a sample. Percentage of THC on a dry weight basis means the percentage of THC, by weight, in  a non-compliant hemp item, after excluding moisture from the item.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text><strong>"Farm Service Agency" or "FSA"</strong> is an agency of the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text><strong>"Financial Interest"</strong> is a person or entity that has more than a five (5) percent interest, share or ownership in a Hemp Business or in the revenues of a Hemp Business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text><strong>"Geospatial location"</strong> means a location designated through a global system of navigational satellites used to determine the precise ground position of a place or object which may be available from the USDA Farm Service Agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text><strong>"Cultivation Licensing Agreement"</strong> means a document executed by an Applicant and the Agricultural Division authorizing the person to possess, cultivate, dry, harvest and store Hemp at one (1) or more specified locations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text><strong>"Hemp"</strong> means the plant Cannabis sativa L. and any part of that plant, including the seeds thereof and all derivatives, extracts, cannabinoids, isomers, acids, salts, and salts of isomers, whether being cultivated or not, with a Delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol concentration of not more than 0.3 percent on a dry weight basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text><strong>"Hemp Business"</strong> means a business entity of any kind that engages in any aspect of Hemp related activities authorized by this ordinance including, but not limited to, a Tribally Owned Corporation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text><strong>"Law Enforcement Agency"</strong> means the Lac Courte Oreilles Police Department and any state or federal law enforcement agency having applicable jurisdiction within Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text><strong>"Licensee"</strong> means a person or business that has been issued a valid Cultivation Licensing Agreement or Processor Licensing Agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text><strong>"Licensed Cultivator"</strong> means a person authorized by the Agriculture Division to cultivate Hemp for market under the terms established by this ordinance.  Consistent with the requirements of 7 C.F.R. §718.2, a Licensed Cultivator includes an owner, operator, landlord, tenant, or sharecropper who shares in the risk of cultivating the Hemp crop and who is entitled to share in marketed Hemp crop.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text><strong>"Licensed Processor"</strong> means a person authorized by the Agriculture Division to process, handle, store, and market Hemp within the Tribe's jurisdiction under the terms established by this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text><strong>"Location" or "Land"</strong> means the particular land, building or buildings where Hemp will be cultivated, handled, stored, or processed, which can include a field name or building name.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text><strong>"Nonviable Seed"</strong> means a seed that has been crushed, dehulled, or otherwise rendered to have a zero percent germination rate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text><strong>"Person"</strong> means an individual or business entity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text><strong>"Pesticide"</strong> means any substance or mixture of substances intended to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Prevent, destroy, control, repel, attract, or mitigate any pest; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Be used as a plant regulator, defoliant, or desiccant; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Be used as a spray adjuvant, once they have been mixed with a U.S. Environmental Protection Agency registered product.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text><strong>"Police Department"</strong> shall mean the Lac Courte Oreilles Police Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(cc)</num>
          <text>"<strong>Processor Licensing Agreement"</strong> means a document executed by a person and the Agriculture Division authorizing the person to process, handle, convert Hemp into a marketable form, and store processed Hemp at one (1) or more specified locations within the Tribe's jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(dd)</num>
          <text><strong>"Program"</strong> means the Tribe's Hemp Program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ee)</num>
          <text><strong>"Propagule"</strong> means a plant or plant part that can be utilized to cultivate a new plant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ff)</num>
          <text>"<strong>Publicly Marketable Hemp Product"</strong> means a Hemp product that meets one (1) or more of the following descriptions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Bare stalks, bast fiber, hurd fiber, nonviable roots, nonviable seeds, seed oils, and plant extracts (excluding products containing Delta- 9-THC below zero and three-tenths (0.3) percent); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Products produced by a Federally Recognized American Indian Tribe or State pursuant to a program adopted under the 2014 Farm Bill; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Products produced by a Federally Recognized American Indian Tribe or State pursuant to a State or Tribal plan approved by the U.S. Department of Agriculture pursuant to the 2018 Farm Bill; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Products that are CBD derived from Hemp, as defined by this ordinance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Does not include: any living Hemp plants, viable Seeds, leaf materials, floral materials, or Delta-9-THC content above 0.3%.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(gg)</num>
          <text><strong>"Registered Land Area"</strong> a contiguous area in a field, greenhouse, or indoor structure where Hemp is cultivated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(hh)</num>
          <text><strong>"Remediation"</strong> means the process of rendering non-complaint cannabis, complaint. Remediation can occur by removing and destroying flower material, while retaining stalk, stems, leaf material, and seeds. Remediation can also occur by shredding the entire plant into a biomass like material, then re-testing the shredded biomass material for compliance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text><strong>"Reservation" or "Reservation Lands"</strong> means the tribe's Indian Country, as defined by 18 U.S.C. § 1151, those lands, including the beds of any streams and flowages, located within the exterior boundaries of the Lac Courte Oreilles Reservation lands as well as off-reservation lands under the jurisdiction and purview of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(jj)</num>
          <text><strong>"Seed"</strong> means Hemp's unit of reproduction, capable of developing into a Hemp plant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(kk)</num>
          <text><strong>"Seed Source"</strong> means the origin of the Seed or Propagules as determined by the Agricultural Division or the Director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ll)</num>
          <text><strong>"Signing Authority"</strong> means an officer or agent of a legal entity with written authorization to commit the legal entity to a binding agreement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(mm)</num>
          <text><strong>"Test Result Report"</strong> shall mean a report prepared by an Agricultural Division approved laboratory that conducts tests on samples of Cannabis sativa L. from Licensed Cultivators.  The report will include the license number, the name and address of the Licensed Cultivator, the Registered Land Area, date of test, test results including Delta-9-THC, identification of retest, the name and address of the laboratory, the DEA registration number of the laboratory (if available), and the measurement of uncertainty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(nn)</num>
          <text><strong>"Tribal Governing Board"</strong> means the Tribal Governing Board of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(oo)</num>
          <text><strong>"Tribal Court"</strong> means the court of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(pp)</num>
          <text><strong>"Tribally Owned Corporation"</strong> shall mean a business entity organized under the laws of the Tribe, Federal law, and wholly owned and operated by the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(qq)</num>
          <text><strong>"Tribe"</strong> means the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(rr)</num>
          <heading>"U.S.</heading>
          <text><strong>Department of Agriculture" or "USDA"</strong> is a Federal agency within the U.S. Government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ss)</num>
          <text>"<strong>Variety"</strong> means a subdivision of a species that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Uniform, in the sense that the variations in essential and distinctive characteristics are describable; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Stable, in the sense that the variety will remain unchanged in its essential and distinctive characteristics and its uniformity if reproduced or reconstituted as required by the different categories of varieties; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Distinct, in the sense that the variety can be differentiated by one or more identifiable morphological, physiological, other characteristics from all other publicly known varieties, or other characteristics from all other publicly known varieties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>3</num>
    <text>To insert the following language to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.5.020|(b)">CSV.8.5.020(b)</cite> Contents of Cultivation and/or Processor Licensing Agreements.</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Consent to entry onto, and inspection of, all land and buildings where Hemp or Cannabis satvia L. is known to be located or licensed to be located by the Agricultural Division, by the Director and/or by a Law Enforcement Agency, <u>and USDA inspectors with or without cause, with or without advance notice.</u></text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.5.020|(b)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.5.020">
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Consent to entry onto, and inspection of, all land and buildings where Hemp or Cannabis satvia L. is known to be located or licensed to be located by the Agricultural Division, by the Director and/or by a Law Enforcement Agency, and USDA inspectors with or without cause, with or without advance notice.</text>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>4</num>
    <text>Amend <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(2)">CSV.8.6.010(e)(2)</cite> from fifteen days to thirty days as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sampling must occur within <u>thirty (30) days</u> prior to the harvest of any Cannabis satvia L;</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(2)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(2)">
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sampling must occur within thirty (30) days prior to the harvest of any Cannabis satvia L;</text>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>5</num>
    <text>Amend <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(6)">CSV.8.6.010(e)(6)</cite> as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Agricultural Division will design its sampling program to ensure, with a 95% level of confidence, that <u>no more than [remove: "testing will identify if more than"] 1</u>% of the Cannabis satvia L. sampled from the Registered Land Area will fail to meet the definition of Hemp under this ordinance;</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(6)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(6)">
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Agricultural Division will design its sampling program to ensure, with a 95% level of confidence, that no more than 1% of the Cannabis satvia L. sampled from the Registered Land Area will fail to meet the definition of Hemp under this ordinance;</text>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>6</num>
    <text>Insert <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(10)">CSV.8.6.010(e)(10)</cite> as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Samples shall be obtained from the flowering tops of plants when flowering tops are present, and shall be approximately five to eight inches in length from the main stem, terminal bud, or central cola of the flowering top of the plant.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:insert path="CSV.8.6.010|(e)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.6.010|(e)|(10)">
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Samples shall be obtained from the flowering tops of plants when flowering tops are present, and shall be approximately five to eight inches in length from the main stem, terminal bud, or central cola of the flowering top of the plant.</text>
      </para>
    </codify:insert>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>7</num>
    <text>Amend <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="CSV.8.7">Subchapter CSV.8.7</cite> to replace "Destruction" to "Remediation" as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <container>
        <num>CSV.8.7</num>
        <heading>Disposal or Remediation[Destruction] of Non-Compliant Hemp</heading>
        <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
        <section>
          <num>CSV.8.7.010</num>
          <heading>Procedures for Disposal or Remediation [remove; Destruction] of Non-Compliant Hemp</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The Agricultural Division may order a different method of <u>remediation [remove: destruction]</u> than proposed by the Licensee.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Upon disposal or <u>remediation [ remove:  destruction/disposition] </u>of any Cannabis satvia L. under this provision…</text>
          </para>
        </section>
      </container>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.7|heading" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.7">
      <heading>Disposal or Remediation of Non-Compliant Hemp</heading>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>8</num>
    <text>Insert a new additional section in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="CSV.8.7.010|(b)">CSV.8.7.010(b)</cite> as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Non-complaint hemp that tests higher than the acceptable THC level, constitutes marijuana, which is a schedule I controlled substance under the Controlled Substances Act 21 U.S.C.§ 801 et. seq.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.7.010" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.7.010">
      <section>
        <num>CSV.8.7.010</num>
        <heading>Procedures for Disposal or Remediation of Non-Compliant Hemp</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any Cannabis sativa L. that is required by the Agricultural Division to be destroyed pursuant to the provisions of this ordinance shall be destroyed under the supervision of the Agricultural Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Non-compliant hemp that tests higher than the acceptable THC level, constitutes marijuana, which is a schedule I controlled substance under the Controlled Substances Act 21 U.S.C § 801 <em>et. seq</em>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If Cannabis sativa L.in a Registered Land Area is determined by the Agricultural Division to have Delta-9-THC concentration of greater than .3% on a dry weight basis, the Cannabis sativa L. shall be promptly disposed of and destroyed. The following procedures shall be used in disposal and destruction:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Licensee will be promptly notified;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The U.S. Department of Agriculture will be promptly notified;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Cannabis sativa L. from this Registered Land Area may not be further handled, processed or enter the stream of commerce unless and until it is resampled or disposed of and destroyed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>No later than thirty (30) days from the Agricultural Division's determination, all Cannabis sativa L. will be disposed of on-site in a manner approved of and verified by the Agricultural Division and in accordance with applicable federal law and regulations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The Agricultural Division and/or Tribal Law Enforcement shall be present for the on-site disposal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The Licensee shall be present and/or observe the handling of the Cannabis sativa L. during the disposal until it is rendered non-retrievable. The disposal shall be conducted by a person or entity authorized by the Agricultural Division;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>The Licensees shall notify the Agricultural Division of the method of disposal or remediation, the completion date, and the total acreage destroyed or remediated.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Hemp stalks (denuded) may be harvested, processed and used for fiber and/or any other lawful purpose, to the extent permitted by federal law; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Hemp Seed may be harvested, processed, and rendered non-viable for food products, provided it is permitted by federal law; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>All other Cannabis sativa L. must be destroyed on the Registered Land Area in a manner approved of and verified by the Agricultural Division.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Agricultural Division shall have the authority to require any other procedures required by 21 C.F.R. § 1317.15(c)(3).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Licensee shall be responsible for the cost of crop destruction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Agricultural Division may order a different method of remediation than proposed by the Licensee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Upon disposal or remediation  of any Cannabis sativa L. under this provision, the Agricultural Division shall prepare written certification of the crop destruction/disposition, give a copy of the certification to the Licensee and applicable law enforcement agencies, and shall maintain records of the destruction/disposition for a minimum of three (3) calendar years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Agricultural Division will prepare a hemp disposal report for the U.S. Department of Agriculture pursuant to the requirements of <cite path="§CSV.8.11.010|(d)" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2023-16">Section CSV.8.11.010(d)</cite> of this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
      </section>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>9</num>
    <text>Insert a new additional section in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="CSV.8.7.010|(c)|(7)">CSV.8.7.010(c)(7)</cite> as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Licensee shall notify the Agricultural Division of the method of disposal or remediation, the completion date, and the total acreage destroyed or remediated.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.7.010|(c)|(7)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.7.010|(c)|(7)">
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Licensee shall notify the Agricultural Division of the method of disposal or remediation, the completion date, and the total acreage destroyed or remediated.</text>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>10</num>
    <text>Remove <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.5.010|(i)|(6)">CSV.8.5.010(i)(6)</cite> that states:</text>
    <include>
      <text>[Remove: (6) If cultivation is to occur outdoors, certification that only feminized Seed and/or female Hemp plants will be cultivated and that any male plants discovered during cultivation will be immediately destroyed.]</text>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.5.010|(i)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.5.010|(i)">
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>A business plan and/or operations plan shall be included with the application that includes at a minimum the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Registered Land Area to be used for Hemp cultivation or processing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A brief description of Hemp cultivation and/or processing activities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The anticipated or actual number of employees and the name of the project manager if not the same as Applicant's Signing Authority; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>A description of Seed, Certified Seed, Variety, or Propagule to be used for cultivation and the planned Seed Source or source of Propagules; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The number of anticipated Hemp plants under cultivation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>A list of all Pesticides and other chemicals proposed for use; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Identification of all persons with a Financial Interest in the Hemp Business; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>A statement of previous farming experience, if any.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>11</num>
    <text>Remove <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="§CSV.8.5.020|(j)">CSV.8.5.020(j)</cite> that states:</text>
    <include>
      <text>[Remove: (j) Agreement that if cultivation of  Hemp is to occur outdoors, only feminized Seed and/or female  Hemp plants will be cultivated and that any male plants discovered during cultivation will be immediately destroyed.]</text>
    </include>
    <codify:replace path="CSV.8.5.020" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|CSV.8.5.020">
      <section>
        <num>CSV.8.5.020</num>
        <heading>Contents of Cultivation and/or Processor Licensing Agreements</heading>
        <text>Any Cultivation Licensing Agreement or Processor Licensing Agreement issued by the Agricultural Division shall contain the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A unique license or registration number in the format prescribed by the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Consent to entry onto, and inspection of, all land and buildings where Hemp or Cannabis sativa L. is known to be located or licensed to be located, by the Agricultural Division, by the Director and/or by a Law Enforcement Agency, and USDA inspectors with or without cause, with or without advance notice</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consent to forfeiture and destruction, without compensation, of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any and all Cannabis sativa L. found to have a measured Delta-9-THC content in excess of zero and three-tenths (0.3) percent on a dry weight basis; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Hemp or Cannabis sativa L. located in an area that is not licensed by the Agricultural Division or located in a Registered Land Area; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Hemp or Cannabis sativa L. not accounted for in any required reporting to the Agricultural Division.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that the Cultivation Licensing Agreement and/or Processor Licensing Agreement cannot be assigned or transferred to another business, person or entity, without approval of the Agricultural Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that any changes to Applicant contact information must be provided in writing to the Agricultural Division within ten (10) days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that the Applicant will abide by all requirements of this ordinance and any amendments thereto.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that prior written approval from the Agricultural Division will be sought before modification of any Registered Land Area or licensed cultivation or processing of Hemp.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement by the Applicant that Hemp shall not be cultivated or processed in any location other than the Registered Land Area approved by the Agricultural Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that the risk of financial or other loss of the Hemp Business shall be borne solely by the Licensed Cultivator and/or Licensed Processor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Agreement that any time Hemp is in transit, a copy of the Cultivation Licensing Agreement and/or Processor Licensing Agreement, and Test Result Report, shall be available for inspection upon the request of the Agricultural Division, Director or Law Enforcement Agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Agreement that, upon request from a representative of the Agricultural Division, Director or Law Enforcement Agency, a Licensed Cultivator and/or Licensed Processor shall immediately produce a copy of his or her Cultivation and/or Processor Licensing Agreement for inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Agreement to submit Planting Reports, Harvest/Destruction Reports, Cultivation Reports, and any other reports required by the Agriculture Division to which the Licensed Cultivator and/or Licensed Processor has agreed, on or before the deadlines established in this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Agreement to notify the Agricultural Division of any interaction with a Law Enforcement Agency, pertaining to the implementation of the provisions of this ordinance, immediately by phone and follow-up in writing within three (3) calendar days of the occurrence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Agreement to notify the Agricultural Division of any theft of Hemp materials, whether they are being used for cultivation or not.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that failure to comply with terms and conditions established in the Cultivation Licensing Agreement and/or Processor Licensing Agreement shall constitute grounds for appropriate Agricultural Division action including termination of any license issued under this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Acknowledgement that any Person or Hemp Business which has suffered a license revocation or denial from the Tribe's Hemp program shall not be eligible to reapply to the program for a period of one (1) year from the date on which the revocation or denial became final. Any Person or Hemp Business that negligently violates the provisions of this Ordinance three times in a 5-year period shall be ineligible to produce/cultivate hemp for a period of 5 years beginning on the date of the third violation.</text>
        </para>
      </section>
    </codify:replace>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>5</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>6<sup>th</sup> day of March, 2023</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>4</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Tweed Shuman, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
