<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2024-24" codify:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2024-24</num>
  <heading>Amendment to the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law Children's Code DMR.1.2.010.</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-02-12</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2024-24.pdf">Res. No. 2024-24</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-02-12</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. ยง5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, ยง 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "establish a tribal court for the purpose of enforcing tribal ordinance" pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(g)">Article V, Section 1(g)</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians and provide for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers" pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">Article V, Section 1(s)</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "provide for the regulation of child custody and domestic relations matters by ordinances;" pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(t)">Article V, Section 1(t)</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>it is in the best interest of the Tribe for the Lac Courte Oreilles DMR Code to adopt the definition for the word "days" that is consistent with the entirety of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law to ensure less confusion among the Tribe, the Court, and all affected parties.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby adopts the definition for the term "Days" in the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court Code <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|DMR.1.2.010|(n)">DMR.1.2.010(n)</cite> as follows in order for there to be consistency with the entirety of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Court Code.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <codify:replace path="|DMR.1.2.010|(n)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|DMR.1.2.010|(n)"/>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>"Days" means a twenty-four-hour time period. In computing any period of time prescribed or allowed by this Tribal Code of Law, or any other ordinance or statute, or by order of the court, the day of the act, event, or default from which the designated time period begins to run shall not be included. The last day of the period shall be included unless it is a day that the clerk of court's office is closed, in which case the period shall extend until the day that the clerk of court's office is open next. When the period of time prescribed or allowed is ten days or less, Saturdays and Sundays are excluded in the computation.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>5</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>12<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2024</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>4</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>0</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>William Trepanier, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
