<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2025-143">
  <num>2025-143</num>
  <heading>Amendment of Title PAP, Chapter PAP.7 of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-08-22</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-143.pdf">Res. No. 2025-143</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-08-22</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. §5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, § 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, § 1(n) of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>, the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "regulate, by enactment of ordinances, the conduct of business within the territory of the band"; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board duly enacted the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwe School – Waadookodaading personnel policies and procedures on August 15, 2016 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 16-81; as amended on September 12, 2016 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 16-89; as amended on January 24, 2017 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 17-11; and as amended on March 11, 2019 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 19-29.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby determines that it is in the best interest of the Tribe to amend the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwe School – Waadookodaading Personnel Policies and Procedures.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that Title PAP, <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="PAP.7">Chapter PAP.7</cite> of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code of Law shall be, and hereby is, amended and enacted as ordinance of the Tribe, pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(n)">Article V, § 1(n) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite> as follows:</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.7.8.200">PAP.7.8.200</cite> is amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <section>
        <codify:replace doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.7.8.200" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|PAP.7.8.200"/>
        <num>PAP.7.8.200</num>
        <heading>Policy Regarding Use of Social Media by Employees</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>While the School encourages its employees to enjoy and make good use of their off-duty time, certain activities on the part of employees may become a concern if they have the effect of impairing the work of any employee; harassing, demeaning, or creating a hostile working environment for any employee; disrupting the smooth and orderly flow of work within the office; or harming the goodwill and reputation of the School. In the area of social media (print, broadcast, digital, and online services such as Facebook, LinkedIn, MySpace, Plaxo, and Twitter, among others), employees may use such media in any way they choose as long as such use does not produce the adverse consequences noted above. For this reason, the following provisions apply regarding an employee's use of social media, both on and off duty:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Social media use is restricted during work hours unless explicitly for school purposes such as creating social media for the school or to communicate directly with parents.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An employee shall be subject to disciplinary action, up to and including termination of employment, depending upon the severity and repeat nature of the offense, if an employee publishes any personal information about the employee, another employee of the School, the School and its officials, the Tribe and its officials, or a tribal member in any public medium (print, broadcast, digital, or online) that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>has the potential or effect of involving the employee, their coworkers, tribal members or the School in any kind of dispute or conflict with other employees or third parties;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>interferes with the work of any employee;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>creates a harassing, demeaning, or hostile working environment for any employee;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>disrupts the smooth and orderly flow of work within the office, or the delivery of services to tribal members;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>harms the goodwill and reputation of the School in the community at large; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>tends to place in doubt the reliability, trustworthiness, or sound judgment of the person who is the subject of the information.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>No employee may use the School's equipment or facilities for furtherance of non-work-related social media related activities or relationships without the express advance permission of their program Director.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Employees who conduct themselves in such a way that their social media related actions toward and relationships with each other interfere with or damage work relationships, disrupt the flow of work or tribal member relations, or cause unfavorable publicity in the community, may be subject to discipline.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Use of social media that involves any kind of criminal activity or harms the rights of others may result in criminal prosecution or civil liability to those harmed, or both.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Social media access and use involving School equipment and resources are subject to the School's computer and internet policy at all times.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>The provisions in this policy are not intended to restrict communications regarding the terms and conditions of the workplace.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>How an employee uses social media is not a matter of concern as long as it is consistent with the aforementioned provisions on this policy.</text>
        </para>
      </section>
    </include>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.7.13.060|(d)">PAP.7.13.060 (d)</cite> is amended as follows:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <codify:replace doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|PAP.7.13.060|(d)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|PAP.7.13.060|(d)"/>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text><u>Transportation of Students</u>. All staff who transport students are required to have a copy of their driver's license and proof of insurance on file in the business office. Procedures to use school vehicles must be followed and requests submitted to the transportation department. Written permission from a parent or guardian is required in order to transport a student in a personal vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
  </section>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>7</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>22<sup>nd</sup> day of August 2025</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>3</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>3</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>Michelle Beaudin, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
