<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2025-57" codify:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2025-57</num>
  <heading>Amending LCO TCL ELE, Election Code and Attachments</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-03-24</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2025-57.pdf">Res. No. 2025-57</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-03-24</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians is a federally recognized Indian tribe ("Tribe") organized pursuant to the provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, 25 U.S.C. §5101, et seq.; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board serves as the governing body of Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|III|1">Article III, § 1 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|IV|3">Article IV, § 3 of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>, the Tribal Governing Board is empowered to "prescribe rules and regulations conducting all subsequent elections"; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|V|1|(s)">Article V, Section 1 (s) of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>, the Tribal Governing Board possesses certain powers, including: "To promulgate and enforce ordinances governing the conduct of members of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin and providing for the maintenance of law and order and the administration of justice by establishing a tribal court and defining its duties and powers."; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Governing Board duly enacted the Lac Courte Oreilles Election Code on April 29, 2005 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 05-29; as amended on May 16, 2005 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 05-50; as amended on May 29, 2007 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 07-59; as amended on March 11, 2011 by the Tribal Governing Board at the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal General Membership meeting; as amended on May 27, 2015 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 15-53; as amended on April 18, 2017 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 17-53; as amended on April I, 2019 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 19-39; as Amended on March 1, 2021 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 20-2021; as amended on March 6, 2023 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 2023-25; and as amended on March 24, 2025 pursuant to Tribal Governing Board Resolution No. 2025-XX.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Tribal Governing Board hereby determines that it is in the best interest of the Tribe to amend the Election Code and its Attachments.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the attached amendment Title ELE Elections Code of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law, including all Attachments, shall be, and hereby is, amended and enacted as an ordinance of the Tribe, pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|IV|3">Article IV, § 3 of the Amended Constitution and Bylaws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite> as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.2.010|(x)">ELE.1.2.010(x)</cite> General Definitions is amended as follows: "(x) "Working Day" means business days, (8:00am-4:30pm), and excludes all observed holidays including tribal holidays."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.2.010|(x)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.2.010|(x)">
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text><strong>"Working Day"</strong> means business days, (8:00am-4:30pm), and excludes all observed holidays including tribal holidays.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.3.050">ELE.1.3.050</cite> is amended as follows: "The Attorney General's Office will appoint a tribal attorney to act as advisor to the Election Committee."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.3.050" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.3.050">
          <section>
            <num>ELE.1.3.050</num>
            <heading>Election Committee Advisor</heading>
            <text>The Attorney General's Office will appoint a tribal attorney to act as advisor to the Election Committee.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.3.070">ELE.1.3.070</cite> is amended as follows: "Observers shall be selected on the day of the Caucus as established pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.010|(c)">ELE.1.5.010 (d)</cite>, by virtue of nominations by the general membership. Upon the completion of the election process, on the date of the election, the observers shall sign a final statement stating whether or not they have witnessed a properly run voting and tallying process (<cite doc="Election Form M">Attachment "M"</cite>). If the statement is not signed and returned to the Chairperson of the Election Committee upon the completion of the election process, it shall be noted that they are in agreement that the process was carried out according to policy. If they are not in agreement that the process was carried out according to policy, the observer must so indicate on the final statement and state their reasons.  Observers shall not transmit any premature information regarding the election results. If they do so, the observers shall not be paid, shall not be permitted to act as observers in future elections, and may be subject to disciplinary action."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.3.070" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.3.070">
          <section>
            <num>ELE.1.3.070</num>
            <heading>Observers</heading>
            <text>Observers shall be selected on the day of the Caucus as established pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.010|(d)">ELE.1.5.010 (d)</cite>, by virtue of nominations by the general membership. Upon the completion of the election process, on the date of the election, the observers shall sign a final statement stating whether or not they have witnessed a properly run voting and tallying process (<cite doc="Election Form M">Attachment "M"</cite>). If the statement is not signed and returned to the Chairperson of the Election Committee upon the completion of the election process, it shall be noted that they are in agreement that the process was carried out according to policy. If they are not in agreement that the process was carried out according to policy, the observer must so indicate on the final statement and state their reasons.  Observers shall not transmit any premature information regarding the election results. If they do so, the observers shall not be paid, shall not be permitted to act as observers in future elections, and may be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.3.090">ELE.1.3.090</cite> is a duplicate of <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.3.090">ELE.1.3.090</cite> and is hereby struck from the ordinance."</text>
        <codify:remove path="|ELE.1.3.090" warning="false" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.3.010|annos"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.4.010|(i)">ELE.1.4.010(i)</cite> is amended as follows: "(i) Distribution of Ballots. The Election Committee Chairperson shall distribute a predetermined number of ballots, as determined by the Election Committee, at the polling site. The Chairperson and a designated Election Committee Member shall certify as to the number of official ballots received by the printer at time of pick up. The ballots shall be secured in lots of two hundred (200) in large envelopes, signed and sealed by each Election Committee Member present at that time. Upon opening an envelope at the time of election, an Election Committee Member for that site, shall open and verify the number of ballots and sign the envelope in the designated space. Upon receipt of the official ballots from the Election Committee Chairperson, the Election Committee members at the site shall receive from the Election Committee Chairperson the Distribution of Official Ballots Certification, which shall be signed by both the Election Committee Chairperson and the Election Committee members. (<cite doc="Election Form L">Attachment "L"</cite>)"</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.4.010|(i)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.4.010|(i)">
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <heading>Distribution of Ballots.</heading>
            <text>The Election Committee Chairperson shall distribute a predetermined number of ballots, as determined by the Election Committee, at the polling site. The Chairperson and a designated Election Committee Member shall certify as to the number of official ballots received by the printer at time of pick up. The ballots shall be secured in lots of two hundred (200) in large envelopes, signed and sealed by each Election Committee Member present at that time. Upon opening an envelope at the time of election, an Election Committee Member for that site, shall open and verify the number of ballots and sign the envelope in the designated space. Upon receipt of the official ballots from the Election Committee Chairperson, the Election Committee members at the site shall receive from the Election Committee Chairperson the Distribution of Official Ballots Certification, which shall be signed by both the Election Committee Chairperson and the Election Committee members. (<cite doc="Election Form L">Attachment "L"</cite>)</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.4.030|(b)">ELE.1.4.303(b)</cite> is amended as follows: "(b) Designated Locations. The following business establishments have been designated as the locations to hang posters pursuant to subs. (a) above: Tribal Administration Building, Housing Authority, LCO Commercial Center, LCO Quick Stop, Gaming Enterprises, LCO Convenience Store, LCO Community Health Center, LCOOS-Waadookodaading, LCO Ojibwe University, LCO Head Start — Early Head Start, Daycare, Reserve Elderly Center, Food Distribution, Big Fish Golf Course, Signor Community Center, New Post Community Center, Aging and Disability Resource Center, Land Management Division and WOJB."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.4.030|(b)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.4.030|(b)">
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <heading>Designated Locations.</heading>
            <text>The following business establishments have been designated as the locations to hang posters pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="ELE.1.4.030|(a)">subs. (a)</cite> above: Tribal Administration Building, Housing Authority, LCO Commercial Center, LCO Quick Stop, Gaming Enterprises, LCO Convenience Store, LCO Community Health Center, LCOOS-Waadookodaading, LCO Ojibwe University, LCO Head Start — Early Head Start, Daycare, Reserve Elderly Center, Food Distribution, Big Fish Golf Course, Signor Community Center, New Post Community Center, Aging and Disability Resource Center, Land Management Division and WOJB.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.4.030|(c)">ELE.1.4.030(c)</cite> is amended as follows: "(c) No campaign materials shall be posted at the designated locations listed above. (This includes the Right of Way for these establishments.)"</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.4.030|(c)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.4.030|(c)">
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>No campaign materials shall be posted at the designated locations listed above. (This includes the Right of Way for these establishments.)</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.020|(a)">ELE.1.5.020(a)</cite> is amended as follows: "(a) All persons nominated as candidates for the election to the Tribal Governing Board at the time of the Caucus, whether or not personally present, shall notify the Election Committee, in writing, within three (3) working days of the day of Caucus, of their acceptance or rejection of their nomination to stand for election (<cite doc="Election Form K">Attachment "K"</cite>) and verification that they have satisfied the prerequisites pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.030">ELE.1.5.030</cite> (<cite doc="Election Form I">Attachment "I"</cite>)."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.020|(a)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.020|(a)">
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>All persons nominated as candidates for the election to the Tribal Governing Board at the time of the Caucus, whether or not personally present, shall notify the Election Committee, in writing, within three (3) working days of the day of Caucus, of their acceptance or rejection of their nomination to stand for election (<cite doc="Election Form K">Attachment "K"</cite>) and verification that they have satisfied the prerequisites pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.030">ELE.1.5.030</cite> <cite doc="Election Form I">(Attachment "I")</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.020|(b)">ELE.1.5.020(b)</cite> is amended as follows: "(b) Those that do not sign the "Acceptance Form" (<cite doc="Election Form H">Attachment "H"</cite>) and complete the "Prerequisite Certification for Primary Ballot" (<cite doc="Election Form I">Attachment "I"</cite>) within the allotted time shall automatically be removed as a candidate for election to the Tribal Governing Board."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.020|(b)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.020|(b)">
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Those that do not sign the "Acceptance Form" (<cite doc="Election Form H">Attachment "H"</cite>) and complete the "Prerequisite Certification for Primary Ballot" (<cite doc="Election Form I">Attachment "I"</cite>) within the allotted time shall automatically be removed as a candidate for election to the Tribal Governing Board.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.030|(a)|(3)|(A)">ELE.1.5.030(a)(3)(A)</cite> is amended as follows: "(A) The Election Committee shall provide the prospective candidate with an Election Background Waiver when the prospective candidate establishes that fifteen years or more has passed since the disposition and punishment (including sentencing and probation) of the felony or other serious offense charge as established in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law">subs. (3)</cite>, above, that has caused the prospective candidate to fail the background check. Any prospective candidate requesting an Election Background Waiver must complete an "Election Background Waiver Petition" which is attached and incorporated as <cite doc="Election Form K">Attachment "K"</cite> to this ordinance."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.030" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.030">
          <section>
            <num>ELE.1.5.030</num>
            <heading>Candidate Prerequisites Prior to Being Placed on the Primary Ballot</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Prior to a person's acceptance of their nomination to stand for election to the Tribal Governing Board, the following prerequisites as determined by the Election Committee shall be met prior to the candidate's "Prerequisite Certification for Primary Ballot" (<cite doc="Election Form I">Attachment "I"</cite>) being completed:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The prospective candidate shall be a member of the Tribe.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The prospective candidate shall have attained the age of twenty-one (21) years on the date of election.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The prospective candidate shall provide consent for the completion of a comprehensive background check within three (3) working days from the day of Caucus. If a comprehensive background check establishes that a prospective candidate has a record of a conviction of election fraud (or other similar classification substantially similar to election fraud) or a felony of any crime in any tribal, county, district, state, or federal court, the Election Committee shall establish that the prospective candidate thereby fails to pass the background check. A prospective candidate that fails to pass the background check shall be prohibited from being placed on the Primary Ballot, unless:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>The Election Committee shall provide the prospective candidate with an Election Background Waiver when the prospective candidate establishes that fifteen years or more has passed since the disposition and punishment (including sentencing and probation) of the felony or other serious offense charge as established in <cite path="ELE.1.5.030|(a)|(3)" doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board Res. No. 2025-57">subs. (3)</cite>, above, that has caused the prospective candidate to fail the background check. Any prospective candidate requesting an Election Background Waiver must complete an "Election Background Waiver Petition" which is attached and incorporated as <cite doc="Election Form K">Attachment "K"</cite> to this ordinance.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Upon the Election Committee's review of the prerequisites established in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="ELE.1.5.030|(a)">subs. (a)</cite> above and receipt of the results of the comprehensive background check for each candidate, the Election Committee shall notify the LCO Human Resources Director of whether each candidate has satisfied or failed to meet the prerequisites established in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="ELE.1.5.030|(a)">subs. (a)</cite> above.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>The prospective candidate must contact the LCO Human Resources Department within five (5) working days from the close of the three (3) working day period allowed pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.020">ELE.1.5.020</cite> to learn if they have satisfied or failed to meet the prerequisites established in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="ELE.1.5.030|(a)">subs. (a)</cite> above.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Tribal Court Challenge to Decision on Meeting Prerequisites. Upon the Election Committee's determination that a prospective candidate has failed to meet the prerequisites established in <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="ELE.1.5.030|(a)">subs. (a)</cite> above, the prospective candidate may file an appeal of the Election Committee's determination in Tribal Court by filing a typed or written statement setting forth the grounds for and evidence supporting the challenge(s) along with the established court filing fee. Any such challenge shall be filed no later than twenty-four (24) hours following the prospective candidate's notification of the Election Committee's determination from the LCO Human Resources Department. Upon receipt of the filing of the appeal of the Election Committee's determination, the Tribal Court shall provide for a hearing and render a decision within two working days of the appeal. The decision of the tribal court shall be final and not subject to further appeal.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>11.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.040|(a)|(1)">ELE.1.5.040(a)(1)</cite> is amended as follows: "(1) The Nominee has signed the "Acceptance Form" (<cite doc="Election Form H">Attachment "H"</cite>) within the three (3) working days allowed pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.020">ELE.1.5.020</cite>;"</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.040|(a)|(1)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.040|(a)|(1)">
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Nominee has signed the "Acceptance Form" (<cite doc="Election Form H">Attachment "H"</cite>) within the three (3) working days allowed pursuant to <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.020">ELE.1.5.020</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>12.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(a)">ELE.1.5.080(a)</cite> is amended as follows: "(a) No absentee ballot can be received without first being requested for in writing, by the person desiring to vote. Each eligible voter must request their own separate ballot in a separate envelope and sign the request for each election. (See Sample Request Form — <cite doc="Election Form C">Attachment "C"</cite> and <cite doc="Election Form D">Attachment "D"</cite>)."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.080|(a)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.080|(a)">
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>No absentee ballot can be received without first being requested for in writing, by the person desiring to vote. Each eligible voter must request their own separate ballot in a separate envelope and sign the request for each election. (See Sample Request Form — <cite doc="Election Form C">Attachment "C"</cite> and <cite doc="Election Form D">Attachment "D"</cite>).</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The use of the forms established in <cite doc="Election Form C">Attachment C</cite> and <cite doc="Election Form D">Attachment D</cite> are not required but recommended.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>13.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(a)|(1)">ELE.1.5.080(a)(1)</cite> is amended as follows: "(1) The use of the forms established in Attachment C and Attachment D are not required but recommended."</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>14.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(1)">ELE.1.5.080(f)(1)</cite> is amended as follows: "(1) Determine if absentee voter meets the eligibility requirements by checking the enrollment status of the absentee voter; and"</text>
        <text>Deliver the Official Ballot, Absentee Ballot Certification (<cite doc="Election Form E">Attachment "E"</cite>), and Instructions for Voting by Absenteeism (<cite doc="Election Form B">Attachment "B"</cite>) to the requesting voter by US Mail."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(1)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(1)">
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Determine if absentee voter meets the eligibility requirements by checking the enrollment status of the absentee voter; and</text>
            <text>Deliver the Official Ballot, Absentee Ballot Certification (<cite doc="Election Form E">Attachment "E"</cite>), and Instructions for Voting by Absenteeism (<cite doc="Election Form B">Attachment "B"</cite>) to the requesting voter by US Mail.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>15.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(2)">ELE.1.5.080(f)(2)</cite> is amended as follows: "(2) Log (<cite doc="Election Form F">Attachment "F"</cite>) the listing and numbering of all individuals that have requested, and shall receive, an "Absentee Ballot.""</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(2)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(2)">
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Log (<cite doc="Election Form F">Attachment "F"</cite>) the listing and numbering of all individuals that have requested, and shall receive, an "Absentee Ballot."</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>16.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(4)">ELE.1.5.080(f)(4)</cite> is amended as follows: "(4) Provide a copy of the absentee ballot log (<cite doc="Election Form F">Attachment "F"</cite>) to the Election Committee members at each polling site."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(4)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.080|(f)|(4)">
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Provide a copy of the absentee ballot log (<cite doc="Election Form F">Attachment "F"</cite>) to the Election Committee members at each polling site.</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>17.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.080|(g)">ELE.1.5.080(g)</cite> is amended as follows: "(g) Cast Absentee Ballots shall be received via regular mail or hand-delivery to the Tribal Administration Building; no later than 4:30 P.M. on the day prior to the Election;"</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.080|(g)" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.080|(g)">
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Cast Absentee Ballots shall be received via regular mail or hand-delivery to the Tribal Administration Building; no later than 4:30 P.M. on the day prior to the Election;</text>
          </para>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>18.</num>
        <text><cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" path="|ELE.1.5.090">ELE.1.5.090</cite> is amended as follows: "Upon completion of the ballot counting, the Election Committee Chairperson, or another member of the Election Executive Committee if the Election Committee Chairperson is unavailable, shall certify the number of votes received by each candidate on a form approved by the Election Committee (<cite doc="Election Form N">Attachment "N"</cite>). The Election Chairperson, or other member of the Executive Committee if the Chairperson is unavailable, shall then certify the Election results and declare the Election winners in accordance with <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|IV">Article IV of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>. The Election Committee must complete their respective tasks of ballot counting, certification of election results, and the declaration of Election winners in one sitting without recess or adjournment. Once the Election results have been certified and the Election winners declared, a member of the Executive Committee shall ensure that the ballots are placed in a locked location to which all persons having access are known by the Executive Committee.  No person shall gain access to the locked ballot storage location without prior approval of Executive Committee. The Chairperson, or other member of the Election Executive Committee if the Chairperson is unavailable, shall maintain a log of all persons obtaining access to the ballots indicating the date and time of such access."</text>
        <codify:replace path="|ELE.1.5.090" codified:doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Code of Law" codified:path="|ELE.1.5.090">
          <section>
            <num>ELE.1.5.090</num>
            <heading>Certification of Election Results</heading>
            <text>Upon completion of the ballot counting, the Election Committee Chairperson, or another member of the Election Executive Committee if the Election Committee Chairperson is unavailable, shall certify the number of votes received by each candidate on a form approved by the Election Committee (<cite doc="Election Form N">Attachment "N"</cite>). The Election Chairperson, or other member of the Executive Committee if the Chairperson is unavailable, shall then certify the Election results and declare the Election winners in accordance with <cite doc="Lac Courte Oreilles Constitution and By-laws" path="containers|Constitution|IV">Article IV of the Amended Constitution and By-laws of the Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians</cite>. The Election Committee must complete their respective tasks of ballot counting, certification of election results, and the declaration of Election winners in one sitting without recess or adjournment. Once the Election results have been certified and the Election winners declared, a member of the Executive Committee shall ensure that the ballots are placed in a locked location to which all persons having access are known by the Executive Committee.  No person shall gain access to the locked ballot storage location without prior approval of Executive Committee. The Chairperson, or other member of the Election Executive Committee if the Chairperson is unavailable, shall maintain a log of all persons obtaining access to the ballots indicating the date and time of such access.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text class="center">CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary/Treasurer of the Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board, hereby certify that the Tribal Governing Board is composed of seven (7) members, of whom <strong><u>6</u></strong> being present, constituted a quorum at a meeting thereof, duly called, convened, and held on this <strong><u>24<sup>th</sup> day of March, 2025</u></strong>, that the foregoing Resolution was duly adopted at said meeting by an affirmative vote of <strong><u>4</u></strong> members, <strong><u>0</u></strong> against, <strong><u>1</u></strong> abstaining, and that said Resolution is a lawful act of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>___________________________________</text>
    <text>William Trepanier, Secretary/Treasurer</text>
    <text>Lac Courte Oreilles Tribal Governing Board</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
